Job 16

1 Then Job, answering, said:

2 I have often heard such things; you are all aggravating comforters.

3 Will there be no end to windy words? Or is it at all a burden to you, if you speak?

4 I, too, can speak like you; and I also wish that your soul favored my soul.

5 I would also comfort you with speeches and would wag my head over you.

6 I would strengthen you with my mouth, and would move my lips, as if being lenient to you.

7 But what can I do? When I am speaking, my grief will not be quiet; and if I am quiet, it will not withdraw from me.

8 But now my grief has crushed me, and all my limbs have been reduced to nothing.

9 My wrinkles bear witness against me, and a liar rises up against my face, contradicting me.

10 He has gathered together his fury towards me, and, threatening me, he has roared against me with his teeth; my enemy has beheld me with terrible eyes.

11 They have opened their mouths against me, and, reproaching me, they have struck me on the cheek; they are nourished by my sufferings.

12 God has confined me with the immoral, and he has delivered me into the hands of the impious.

13 I, who once was wealthy, am now crushed. He has grabbed me by my neck; he has broken me and has place me before him as a sign.

14 He has surrounded me with his lances. He has severely wounded my lower back, he has not been lenient, and he has poured out my organs upon the earth.

15 He has cut me with wound after wound. He has rushed upon me like a giant.

16 I have sewn sackcloth over my skin, and I have covered my body with ashes.

17 My face is swollen from weeping, and my eyelids have dimmed my vision.

18 These things I have endured without iniquity in my hand, while I held pure prayers before God.

19 O earth, do not conceal my blood, nor let my outcry find a hiding place in you.

20 For behold, my witness is in heaven, and my confidante is on high.

21 My friends are full of words; my eye rains tears upon God.

22 And I wish that a man might be so judged before God, just as the son of man is judged with his assistant!

23 For behold, a few years pass by, and I am walking a path by which I will not return.

Job 17

1 My spirit will be wasted, my days will be shortened, and only the grave will left for me.

2 I have not sinned, yet my eye remains in bitterness.

3 Free me, O Lord, and set me beside you, and let the hand of anyone you wish fight against me.

4 You have set their heart far from discipline; therefore, they will not be praised.

5 He promises prey to his companions, but the eyes of his sons will grow faint.

6 He has posted me like a proverb to the people, and I am an example in their presence.

7 My eyesight has been clouded by indignation, and my limbs have been reduced, as if to nothing.

8 The just will be astounded over this, and the innocent will be stirred up against the hypocrite.

9 And the just will cling to his way, and clean hands will increase strength.

10 Therefore, be converted, all of you, and approach, for I do not find in you any wisdom.

11 My days have passed away; my thoughts have been scattered, tormenting my heart.

12 They have turned night into day, and I hope for light again after the darkness.

13 If I should wait, the underworld is my house, and in darkness I have spread out my bed.

14 I have said to decay and to worms: "You are my father, my mother, and my sister."

15 Therefore, where is my expectation now, and who is it that considers my patience?

16 Everything of mine will descend into the deepest underworld; do you think that, in that place at least, there will be rest for me?

Job 18

1 But Baldad the Suhite responded by saying:

2 How long will you throw around words? Understand first, and then let us speak.

3 Why have we been treated like mules, as if we were unworthy before you?

4 You, who ruins your own soul in your fury, will the earth be forsaken because of you, and will the cliffs be moved from their place?

5 Will not the light of the impious be put out, and the flame of his fire refuse to shine?

6 Light will become darkness in his tabernacle, and the lamp that is over him will be extinguished.

7 His strong steps will be constrained, and his own counsel will cast him down uncontrollably.

8 For he has caused his own feet to go into a net, and he has walked into its web.

9 His heel will be held in a snare, and thirst will rage against him.

10 A trap has been hidden for him in the earth, and a decoy, along his path.

11 Horrifying things will terrify him everywhere and will entangle his feet.

12 Let his strength be diminished by famine, and let starvation invade his ribs.

13 Let it devour the beauty of his skin; let the ancient death consume his arms.

14 Let his confidence be torn away from his tabernacle, and let ruin trample over him like a king.

15 Let the companions of he who is not, dwell in his tabernacle; let brimstone rain down upon his tabernacle.

16 Let his roots be dried up from beneath him, and his harvest be crushed from above.

17 Let the memory of him perish from the earth, and let not his name be celebrated in the streets.

18 He will expel him from light into darkness, and he will remove him from the world.

19 Neither his offspring, nor his descendents, will exist among his people, nor will there be any remnants in his country.

20 The last will be astonished at his day, and the first will be overcome with horror.

21 And so, these are the tabernacles of the sinful, and this the place of he who does not know God.

Job 19

1 But Job answered by saying:

2 How long will you afflict my soul and wear me down with words?

3 So, ten times you confound me and are not ashamed to oppress me.

4 Now, of course, if I have been ignorant, my ignorance will be with me.

5 But you have risen up against me, and you accuse me to my disgrace.

6 At least now you should understand that God has not afflicted me with a balanced judgment, though he has encompassed me with his scourges.

7 Behold, I will cry out, enduring violence, and no one will hear. I will announce loudly, but there is no one who may judge.

8 He has hemmed in my path, and I cannot pass; he has added darkness to my difficult path.

9 He has plundered me of my glory, and he has stolen the crown from my head.

10 He has destroyed me on every side, and I am lost, and, like an uprooted tree, he has taken away my hope.

11 His fury has raged against me, and in this way he has treated me like his enemy.

12 His troops have gathered together, and they have made their way to me, and they have besieged my tabernacle all around.

13 He has put my brothers far from me, and my friends have withdrawn from me like strangers.

14 My kinsmen have forsaken me, and those who knew me, have forgotten me.

15 The inhabitants of my house and my maidservants treat me just as if I were a stranger, and I have been like an sojourner in their eyes.

16 I called my servant, and he did not respond; I pleaded with him with my own mouth.

17 My wife has shuddered at my breath, and I have begged the sons of my loins.

18 Even the foolish have looked down on me, and, when I withdrew from them, they spoke ill of me.

19 Those who were sometime my counselors, treat me like an abomination; and he whom I valued the most has turned against me.

20 Since my flesh has been consumed, my bone adheres to my skin, and only my lips have been left around my teeth.

21 Have mercy on me, have compassion on me, at least you my friends, because the hand of the Lord has touched me.

22 Why do you pursue me just as God does, and satiate yourselves with my flesh?

23 Who will grant to me that my words may be written down? Who will grant to me that they may be inscribed in a book,

24 with an iron pen and a plate of lead, or else be carved in stone?

25 For I know that my Redeemer lives, and on the last day I will rise out of the earth.

26 And I will be enveloped again with my skin, and in my flesh I will see my God.

27 It is he whom I myself will see, and he whom my eyes will behold, and no other. This, my hope, has taken rest in my bosom.

28 Why then do you now say: "Let us pursue him, and let us find a basis to speak against him?"

29 So then, flee from the face of the sword, for the sword is the avenger of iniquities; but know this: there is to be a judgment.

Job 20

1 Then Zophar the Naamathite answered by saying:

2 In response, various thoughts succeed one another in me, and my mind moves quickly through different ideas.

3 The teaching you use to admonish me, I will hear, and the spirit of my understanding will respond for me.

4 This, I know, is from the beginning, from the time that man was set over the earth:

5 that the praise of the impious shall be short, and the joy of the hypocrite lasts only a moment.

6 If his pride ascends even towards the heavens, and his head touches the clouds,

7 in the end, he will be destroyed like a trash heap, and those who had seen him will say: "Where is he?"

8 Like a dream that flies away, he will not be found; he will pass away like a nightmare.

9 The eyes that had seen him, will not see him; no longer will his own place admire him.

10 His sons will be worn away by poverty, and his own hands will deliver his grief to him.

11 His bones will be filled with the vices of his youth, and they will sleep with him in the dust.

12 For, when evil will be sweet in his mouth, he will hide it under his tongue.

13 He will permit it, and not abandon it, and he will conceal it in his throat.

14 His bread in his belly will be turned into the venom of snakes within him.

15 The riches that he devours, he will vomit up, and from his stomach God will draw them out.

16 He will suck the head of snakes, and the tongue of the viper will kill him.

17 (May he never see the streams of the river, the torrents of honey and butter.)

18 He will be repaid for all he has done, yet he will not be consumed; according to the multitude of his schemes, so also will he suffer.

19 For, having broken in, he stripped the poor. He has quickly stolen away a house he did not build.

20 And yet his stomach will not be satisfied, and when he has the things he desires, he will not be able to possess them.

21 Nothing remained of his portion, and, because of this, nothing will continue of his kind.

22 When he will be satisfied, he will be constrained; he will seethe, and all anguish will fall upon him.

23 May his stomach be filled, so that God may send forth the fury of his wrath to him and may rain down his battle upon him.

24 He will flee from weapons of iron, and he will fall in an arc of brass,

25 which had been drawn and had issued forth from its sheath, glittering in its bitterness: the horrible ones will go forth and approach over him.

26 All darkness has been hidden in his secrecy. A fire that has not been set will devour him; he will be thrown down and forsaken in his tabernacle.

27 The heavens will reveal his sinfulness, and the earth will rise up against him.

28 The offspring of his house will be exposed; he will be pulled down in the day of God's wrath.

29 This is the portion of a wicked man from God, and the inheritance of his words from the Lord.

Job 21

1 Then Job responded by saying:

2 I beseech you to hear my words and to do penance.

3 Permit me, and I will speak, and afterwards, if you see fit, you can laugh at my words.

4 Is my dispute against man, so that I would have no reason to be discouraged?

5 Listen to me and be astonished, and place a finger over your mouth.

6 As for me, when I think it over, I am afraid, and trembling convulses my body.

7 Why then do the impious live, having been lifted up and strengthened with riches?

8 They see their offspring continue before them: a commotion of close relatives and of children's children in their sight.

9 Their houses have been secure and peaceable, and there is no staff of God over them.

10 Their cattle have conceived and have not miscarried; their cow has given birth and is not deprived of her newborn.

11 Their little ones go out like a flock, and their children jump around playfully.

12 They take up the timbrel and the lyre, and they rejoice at the sound of the organ.

13 Their days are prolonged in wealth, yet, in an instant, they descend into hell.

14 Who has said to God, "Depart from us, for we do not want the knowledge of your ways.

15 Who is the Almighty that we should serve him? And how is it helpful to us if we pray to him?"

16 It is true that their good things are not in their power. May the counsel of the impious be far from me!

17 How often will the lamp of the wicked be extinguished, and a deluge overtake them, and how often will he distribute the afflictions of his wrath?

18 They will be like chaff before the face of the wind, and like ashes that the whirlwind scatters.

19 God will preserve the grief of the father for his sons, and, when he repays, then he will understand.

20 His eyes will see his own destruction, and he will drink from the wrath of the Almighty.

21 For what does he care what happens to his house after him, or if the number of its months are reduced by half?

22 Can anyone teach holy knowledge to God, who judges the exalted?

23 This one dies strong and healthy, rich and happy.

24 His gut is full of fat and his bones are moistened with marrow.

25 In truth, another dies in bitterness of soul, without any resources.

26 And yet they will sleep together in the dust, and worms will cover them.

27 Surely, I know your thoughts and your sinful judgments against me.

28 For you say, "Where is the house of the ruler, and where are the tabernacles of the impious?"

29 Ask any passerby whom you wish, and you will realize that he understands these same things:

30 that the evil-doer is reserved for the day of destruction, and he will be led to the day of wrath.

31 Who will reprove his way to his face, and who will repay him for what he has done?

32 He will be led to the tomb, and he will remain awake in the chaos of the dead.

33 He has been found acceptable to the banks of the River of Lamentation, and he will draw any man towards him, and there are countless before him.

34 Therefore, how long will you console me in vain, when your answer is shown to be repugnant to truth?

Job 22

1 Then Eliphaz the Themanite responded by saying:

2 Can man be compared with God, even if he were perfect in knowledge?

3 What advantage is it to God, if you were just? Or what do you provide for him, if your way should be immaculate?

4 Will he reprove you and take you to judgment for being afraid,

5 and not because of your many evil deeds and your infinite unfairness?

6 For you have taken away the collateral of your brothers without cause, and stripped them naked of their clothing.

7 You have not given water to the weary; you have taken bread away from the hungry.

8 By the strength of your arm, you took possession of the land, and you retain it by being the strongest.

9 You have sent widows away empty, and you have crushed the shoulders of orphans.

10 Because of this, you are surrounded by traps, and unexpected fears will disturb you.

11 And did you think that you would not see darkness and that you were not to be overwhelmed by the on-rush of overflowing waters?

12 Have you not considered that God is higher than the heavens and is lifted above the height of the stars?

13 And you say: "Well, what does God know?" and, "He judges, as if through a fog,"

14 and, "The clouds are his hiding-place," and, "He does not examine us closely," and, "He makes his rounds at the limits of the heavens."

15 Do you not want to tend the path of the ages, which wicked men have spurned?

16 These were taken away before their time, and a flood overthrew their foundation.

17 They said to God, "Withdraw from us," and they treated the Almighty as if he could do nothing,

18 though he had filled their houses with good things. May their way of thinking be far from me.

19 The just will see and will rejoice, and the innocent will mock them.

20 Has not their haughtiness been cut down, and has not fire devoured the remnants of them?

21 So, repose yourself with him and be at peace, and, in this way, you will have the best fruits.

22 Accept the law from his mouth, and place his words in your heart.

23 If you will return to the Almighty, you will be rebuilt, and you will put sinfulness far from your tabernacle.

24 He will give you stone in place of dirt, and torrents of gold in place of stone.

25 And the Almighty will be against your enemies, and silver will be gathered together for you.

26 Then will you flock together in delight over the Almighty, and you will lift up your face to God.

27 You will plead with him, and he will listen to you, and you will pay your vows.

28 You will decide on something, and it will come to you, and the light will shine in your ways.

29 For he who had been humbled, will be in glory; and he who will lower his eyes, will be the one saved.

30 The innocent will be saved, and he will be saved with purity in his hands.

Job 23

1 Then Job answered by saying:

2 Now again my conversation is in bitterness, and the force of my scourging weighs more heavily on me because of my mourning.

3 Who will grant me that I might know and find him, and that I may approach even to his throne?

4 I would place judgment before his eye, and my mouth would fill with criticism,

5 so that I may know the words that he will answer me and understand what he will say to me.

6 I do not want him to contend with me with much strength, nor to overwhelm me with the bulk of his greatness.

7 Let him show fairness in response to me, and let my judgment reach to victory.

8 If I go to the east, he does not appear; if I go to the west, I will not understand him.

9 If I turn to the left, what can I do? I will not take hold of him. If I turn myself to the right, I will not see him.

10 Truly, he knows my way and has tested me like gold that passes through fire.

11 My feet have been following his footsteps; I have kept to his way and have not strayed from it.

12 I have not withdrawn from the commands of his lips, and the words of his mouth I have hidden in my sinews.

13 For he is alone, and no one is able to disturb his intention; and whatever his spirit wills, that he accomplishes.

14 And when he fulfills his will in me, many other similar ones will also be present with him.

15 And, for this reason, I have been troubled at his presence, and, when I consider him, I am approached by fear.

16 God has weakened my heart, and the Almighty has confused me.

17 Yet I have not perished because of the threatening darkness, nor has gloom covered my face.

Job 24

1 The times are not hidden from the Almighty; even those who know him, do not know his days.

2 Some have crossed the boundaries, plundered the flocks, and given them pasture.

3 They have driven away the donkey of orphans, and have taken the cow from the widow as collateral.

4 They have undermined the way of the poor, and have pressed together the meek of the earth.

5 Others, like wild asses in the desert, go forth to their work; by watching for prey, they obtain bread for their children.

6 They reap a field that is not their own, and they harvest a vineyard that they have taken by force.

7 They send men away naked, having taken the clothing of those who have no covering in the cold;

8 these are wet with the mountain rain, and, having no covering, they embrace the rocks.

9 They have used violence to deprive orphans, and they have robbed the poor common people.

10 From the naked and those who do not have enough clothing, and from the hungry, they have taken away sheaves of grain.

11 They take their midday rest among the stockpiles of those who, though they have trodden the winepresses, suffer thirst.

12 In the cities, they caused the men to groan and the spirit of the wounded to cry out, and so God does not allow this to go unpunished.

13 They have been rebellious against the light; they have not known his ways, nor have they returned by his paths.

14 The killer of men rises at first light; he executes the destitute and the poor, but, in truth, he is like a thief in the night.

15 The eye of the adulterer waits for darkness, saying, "No eye will see me," and he covers his face.

16 He passes through houses in the nighttime, just as they had agreed among themselves in the daytime; and they are ignorant of the light.

17 If sunrise should suddenly appear, it is treated by them like the shadow of death; and they walk in darkness, as if in light.

18 He is nimble on the surface of water. His place on land is to be accursed. May he not walk by way of the vineyards.

19 May he cross from the snowy waters to excessive heat, and his sin, all the way to hell.

20 Let mercy forget him. His charm is worms. Let him not be remembered, but instead be broken like an unfruitful tree.

21 For he has fed on the barren, who does not bear fruit, and he has not done good to the widow.

22 He has pulled down the strong by his strength, and, when he stands up, he will not have trust in his life.

23 God has given him a place for repentance, and he abuses it with arrogance, but his eyes are upon his ways.

24 They are lifted up for a little while, but they will not continue, and they will be brought low, just like all things, and they will be taken away, and, like the tops of the ears of grain, they will be crushed.

25 But, if this is not so, who is able to prove to me that I have lied and to place my words before God?

Job 26

1 Then Job responded by saying:

2 Whose assistant are you? Is he weak-minded? And do you sustain the arm of him that is not strong?

3 To whom have you given advice? Perhaps it is to him that has no wisdom or prudence that you have revealed your many ideas.

4 Who is it that you wanted to teach? Was it not him that created the breath of life?

5 Behold, giant things groan under the waters, and they dwell with them.

6 The underworld is naked before him, and there is no covering for perdition.

7 He stretched out the North over emptiness, and he suspended the land over nothing.

8 He secures the waters in his clouds, so that they do not burst forth downward all at once.

9 He holds back the face of his throne, and he stretches his cloud over it.

10 He has set limits around the waters, until light and darkness shall reach their limit.

11 The pillars of heaven tremble and are frightened at his nod.

12 By his strength, the seas suddenly gather together, and his foresight has struck the arrogant.

13 His spirit has adorned the heavens, and his birthing hand has brought forth the winding serpent.

14 Behold, these things have been said about his ways in part, and, since we barely have heard a small drop of his word, who will be able to gaze upon the thunder of his greatness?

Job 27

1 Job also added to this, using figures of speech, and he said:

2 As God lives, who has taken away my judgment, and the Almighty, who has led my soul to bitterness,

3 as long as my breath remains in me and the breath of God remains in my nostrils,

4 my lips will not speak iniquity, nor will my tongue devise lies.

5 Far be it from me that I should judge you to be right, for, until I expire, I will not withdraw from my innocence.

6 I will not forsake my justification, which I have just begun to grasp, for my heart does not find blame for me in my whole life.

7 Let the impious be as my enemy, and the sinful, as my adversary.

8 For what hope is there for the hypocrite, if he greedily plunders and God does not free his soul?

9 Will God pay attention to his cry, when anguish overcomes him?

10 Or will he take delight in the Almighty and call upon God at all times?

11 I will teach you through the hand of God, what the Almighty holds, and I will not conceal it.

12 Behold, you know all this, and so why do you speak vain things without a reason?

13 This is the portion of the impious man with God, and the inheritance of the violent, which they will receive from the Almighty.

14 If his sons should happen to increase, they will be for the sword, and his grandsons will not be satisfied with bread.

15 Whatever will remain of him will be buried in the ruins, and his widows will not weep.

16 If he will amass silver as if it were dirt and fabricate garments as if they were clay,

17 then yes, he will gather, but the just will be clothed with it and the innocent will divide the silver.

18 He has built his house like a moth, and he has made a makeshift shelter like a sentry.

19 When he falls asleep, the rich man will leave him with nothing; he will open his eyes and find nothing.

20 Destitution will surround him like water; a storm will overwhelm him in the night.

21 A burning wind will pick him up and carry him away, and, like a whirlwind, it will rush him from his place.

22 And it will hurl over him and will not spare him; fleeing from its power, he will go into exile.

23 He will clasp his hands over himself, and he will hiss at himself, while considering his situation.

Job 28

1 Silver has its fissures where it is first found, and gold has a place where it is melted.

2 Iron is taken from the earth, and ore, unbound by heat, is turned into brass.

3 He has established a time for darkness, and he has settled on an end for all things, as well as for the stone that is in the gloom and shadow of death.

4 The burning separates a pilgrim people from those who have been forgotten by the feet of the destitute man and from the unapproachable.

5 The land, where bread appeared in its place, has been destroyed by fire.

6 Its stones are embedded with sapphires, and its soil, with gold.

7 The bird does not know its path, nor has the eye of the vulture beheld it.

8 The sons of merchants have not walked there, nor has the lioness traveled through it.

9 He has stretched out his hand to the rocks; he has overturned the foundations of the mountains.

10 He has cut rivers through the rocks, and his eye has seen all precious things.

11 The depths of rivers he has also examined, and he has brought hidden things into the light.

12 But, in truth, where is wisdom to be found, and where is the place of understanding?

13 Man does not know its price, nor is it found in the land of those who live in sweetness.

14 The abyss declares, "It is not in me." And the sea says, "It is not with me."

15 The finest gold will not be paid for it, nor will silver be weighed in exchange for it.

16 It will not be compared with the dyed colors of India, nor with the very costly stone sardonyx, nor with the sapphire.

17 Neither gold nor crystal will be its equal; neither will vessels of gold be fitted for it.

18 The exalted and the eminent will not be remembered in comparison with it. Yet wisdom is drawn out of concealment.

19 The topaz of Ethiopia will not be equal to it, nor will it be compared to the purest dyes.

20 So then, where does wisdom begin, and where is the place of understanding?

21 It has been hidden from the eyes of all living things, just as the birds of the heavens escape notice.

22 Perdition and death have said, "With our ears, we have heard its fame."

23 God understands its way, and he knows its location.

24 For he beholds the limits of the world, and he looks upon all things that are under heaven.

25 He created a counterweight for the winds, and he suspended the waters to measure them.

26 At that time, he gave a law to the rain and a path to the resounding storms.

27 Then he saw and explained it, and he made ready and examined it.

28 And he said to man, "Behold the fear of the Lord. Such is wisdom. And to withdraw from evil, this is understanding."

Job 29

1 Job also added to this, using figures of speech, and he said:

2 Who will grant to me that I might be as I was in former months, according to the days when God kept watch over me?

3 At that time, his lamp shined over my head, and by his light, I walked through the darkness.

4 I was then just as in the days of my youth, when God was privately in my tabernacle.

5 At that time, the Almighty was with me and my children surrounded me.

6 Then, I washed my feet with butter, and a boulder poured out rivers of oil for me.

7 When I went to the gate of the city, or to the main street, they prepared a chair for me.

8 The youths saw me and hid themselves, and the elders, rising up, remained standing.

9 The leaders stopped talking, and they placed a finder over their mouth.

10 The commanders subdued their voice, and their tongue adhered to their throat.

11 The ear that heard me, blessed me, and the eye that saw me, gave testimony for me.

12 This was because I had freed the poor, who cried out, and the orphan, who had no helper.

13 The blessing of him who would have been destroyed came upon me, and I consoled the heart of the widow.

14 I put on justice, and I clothed myself with my judgment, like a robe and a diadem.

15 I was an eye for the blind and a foot for the lame.

16 I was the father of the poor; and if I lacked knowledge about any case, I investigated very diligently.

17 I crushed the jaws of the impious, and I took away prey from his teeth.

18 And I said, "I will die in my little nest, and like a palm tree, I will multiply my days.

19 My root has been spread beside the waters, and the dew will remain with my harvest.

20 My glory will always be restored, and my bow will be restored to my hand."

21 Those who heard me, expected vindication, and they listened closely in silence to my counsel.

22 To my words, they dared to add nothing, and my eloquence poured over them.

23 They waited for me as for rain, and they opened their mouth as for belated rains.

24 If I had ever laughed at them, they would not have believed it, and the light of my face was not cast down towards the ground.

25 If I wished to go to them, I sat down first, and, though I sat like a king surrounded by an army, yet I was a comforter to whose who mourned.

Job 30

1 But now, those younger in years scorn me, whose fathers I would not have seen fit to place with the dogs of my flock,

2 the strength of whose hands was nothing to me, and they were considered unworthy of life itself.

3 They were barren from poverty and hunger; they gnawed in solitude, layered with misfortune and misery.

4 And they chewed grass and the bark from trees, and the root of junipers was their food.

5 They took these things from the steep valleys, and when they discovered one of these things, they rushed to the others with a cry.

6 They lived in the parched desert and in caves underground or above the rocks.

7 They rejoiced among these kinds of things, and they considered it delightful to be under thorns.

8 These are the sons of foolish and base men, not even paying any attention to the land.

9 Now I become their song, and I have been made into their proverb.

10 They loathe me, and so they flee far from me, and they are not reluctant to spit in my face.

11 For he has opened his quiver and has afflicted me, and he has placed a bridle in my mouth.

12 Immediately, upon rising, my calamities rise up to the right. They have overturned my feet and have pressed me down along their way like waves.

13 They have diverted my journeys; they have waited to ambush me, and they have prevailed, and there was no one who might bring help.

14 They have rushed upon me, as when a wall is broken or a gate opened, and they have been pulled down into my miseries.

15 I have been reduced to nothing. You have taken away my desire like a wind, and my health has passed by like a cloud.

16 But now my soul withers within myself, and the days of affliction take hold of me.

17 At night, my bone is pierced with sorrows, and those who feed on me, do not sleep.

18 By the sheer number of them my clothing is worn away, and they have closed in on me like the collar of my coat.

19 I have been treated like dirt, and I have been turned into embers and ashes.

20 I cry to you, and you do not heed me. I stand up, and you do not look back at me.

21 You have changed me into hardness, and, with the hardness of your hand, you oppose me.

22 You have lifted me up, and, placing me as if on the wind, you have thrown me down powerfully.

23 I know that you will hand me over to death, where a home has been established for all the living.

24 Truly, then, you do not extend your hand in order to consume them, and if they fall down, you will save them.

25 Once, I wept over him who was afflicted, and my soul had compassion on the poor.

26 I expected good things, but evil things have come to me. I stood ready for light, yet darkness burst forth.

27 My insides have seethed, without any rest, for the days of affliction have prevented it.

28 I went forth mourning, without anger, and rising up, I cried out in confusion.

29 I was the brother of snakes, and the companion of ostriches.

30 My skin has become blackened over me, and my bones have dried up because of the heat.

31 My harp has been turned into mourning, and my pipes have been turned into a voice of weeping.

Job 31

1 I reached an agreement with my eyes, that I would not so much as think about a virgin.

2 For what portion should God from above hold for me, and what inheritance should the Almighty from on high keep?

3 Is not destruction held for the wicked and repudiation kept for those who work injustice?

4 Does he not examine my ways and number all my steps?

5 If I have walked in vanity, or if my foot has hurried towards deceitfulness,

6 let him weigh me in a just balance, and let God know my simplicity.

7 If my steps have turned aside from the way, or if my heart has followed my eyes, or if a blemish has clung to my hands,

8 then may I sow, and let another consume, and let my offspring be eradicated.

9 If my heart has been deceived over a woman, or if I have waited in ambush at my friend's door,

10 then let my wife be the harlot of another, and let other men lean over her.

11 For this is a crime and a very great injustice.

12 It is a fire devouring all the way to perdition, and it roots out all that springs forth.

13 If I have despised being subject to judgment with my servant or my maid, when they had any complaint against me,

14 then what will I do when God rises to judge, and, when he inquires, how will I respond to him?

15 Is not he who created me in the womb, also he who labored to make him? And did not one and the same form me in the womb?

16 If I have denied the poor what they wanted and have made the eyes of the widow wait;

17 if I have eaten my morsel of food alone, while orphans have not eaten from it;

18 (for from my infancy mercy grew with me, and it came out with me from my mother's womb;)

19 if I have looked down on him who was perishing because he had no clothing and the poor without any covering,

20 if his sides have not blessed me, and if he were not warmed with the fleece of my sheep;

21 if I have lifted up my hand over an orphan, even when it might seem to me that I the advantage over him at the gate;

22 then may my shoulder fall from its joint, and may my arm, with all its bones, be broken.

23 For I have always feared God, like waves flowing over me, whose weight I was unable to bear.

24 If I have considered gold to be my strength, or if I have called purified gold 'my Trust;'

25 if I have rejoiced over my great success, and over the many things my hand has obtained;

26 if I gazed upon the sun when it shined and the moon advancing brightly,

27 so that my heart rejoiced in secret and I kissed my hand with my mouth,

28 which is a very great iniquity and a denial against the most high God;

29 if I have been glad at the ruin of him who hated me and have exulted that evil found him,

30 for I have not been given my throat to sin by asking for a curse on his soul;

31 if the men around my tabernacle have not said: "He might give us some of his food, so that we will be filled,"

32 for the foreigner did not remain at the door, my door was open to the traveler;

33 if, as man does, I have hidden my sin and have concealed my iniquity in my bosom;

34 if I became frightened by an excessive crowd, and the disrespect of close relatives alarmed me, so that I would much rather have remained silent or have gone out the door;

35 then, would he grant me a hearing, so that the Almighty would listen to my desire, and he who judges would himself write a book,

36 which I would then carry on my shoulder and wrap around me like a crown?

37 With each of my steps, I would pronounce and offer it, as if to a prince.

38 So, if my land cries out against me, and if its furrows weep with it,

39 if I have used its fruits for nothing but money and have afflicted the souls of its tillers,

40 then, may thistles spring forth for me instead of grain, and thorns instead of barley. (This ended the words of Job.)

Job 32

1 But these three men ceased to answer Job, because he considered himself justified.

2 And Eliu the son of Barachel the Buzite, of the kindred of Ram, was angry and indignant. But he was angry against Job because he described himself to be just in the presence of God.

3 Moreover, he was indignant with his friends because they had not found a reasonable response, except in so far as they condemned Job.

4 Therefore, Eliu waited while Job was talking, for these were his elders that were speaking.

5 But when he saw that these three were not able to respond, he was extremely angry.

6 And so Eliu the son of Barachel the Buzite responded by saying: I am younger in years, and you are more ancient; therefore, I kept my head low, for I was afraid to reveal to you my opinion.

7 For I had hoped that greater age would speak, and that a multitude of years would teach wisdom.

8 But I see now that there is only breath in men, and that it is the inspiration of the Almighty that gives understanding.

9 The wise are not the aged, nor do the elders understand judgment.

10 Therefore, I will speak. Listen to me, and so I will show you my wisdom.

11 For I have endured your words; I have paid attention to your deliberations, while you were being argumentative with words.

12 And as long as I supposed that you were saying something, I considered; but now I see that there is none of you that is able to argue with Job and to respond to his words.

13 So that you will not say, "We have found wisdom," God has thrown him down, not man.

14 He has said nothing to me, and I will not respond to him according to your words.

15 Then they were filled with dread, and so they no longer responded, and they withdrew from their speechmaking.

16 Therefore, because I have waited and they have not been speaking, for they stood firm and did not respond at all,

17 I also will answer in my turn, and I will reveal my knowledge.

18 For I am full of words, and the feeling in my gut inspires me.

19 Yes, my stomach is like fermenting wine without a vent, which bursts the new containers.

20 I should speak, but I will also breathe a little; I will open my lips, and I will answer.

21 I will not esteem the reputation of a man, and I will not equate God with man.

22 For I do not know how long I will continue, and whether, after a while, my Maker might take me away.

Job 33

1 Therefore, hear my speeches, Job, and listen to all my words.

2 Behold, I have opened my mouth; let my tongue speak along with my throat.

3 My words are from my simple heart, and my lips will speak a pure judgment.

4 The Spirit of God made me, and the breath of the Almighty gave me life.

5 If you can, answer me, and oppose me to my face.

6 Behold, God has made me, just as he also has made you, and I, likewise, have been formed of the same clay.

7 So, truly, do not let my wonders terrify you, and do not let my eloquence be burdensome to you.

8 For you have spoken in my hearing, and I have heard the voice of your words, saying:

9 "I am clean and without sin; I am immaculate, and there is no iniquity in me.

10 Yet he has discovered blame in me, and so he has treated me like his enemy.

11 He has put my feet in fetters; he has kept watch over all my ways."

12 Therefore, it is for this reason that you have not been justified. For I tell you that God is greater than man.

13 Do you contend against him because he has not responded to all of your words?

14 God speaks once, and he does not repeat the same thing a second time.

15 Through a dream in a vision of the night, when a deep sleep falls over men, and they are sleeping in their beds,

16 then, he opens the ears of men, and, educating them, he teaches discipline,

17 so that he may divert a man from the things that he is doing, and may free him from pride,

18 rescuing his soul from corruption and his life from passing away by the sword.

19 Likewise, he rebukes by sorrow in bed, and he causes all of his bones to become weak.

20 Bread becomes abominable to him in his life, and, to his soul, the meat which before he desired.

21 His body will waste away, and his bones, which had been covered, will be revealed.

22 His soul has approached corruption, and his life has drawn near to what is deadly.

23 If there were an angel speaking for him, one among thousands, to declare the fairness of the man,

24 he will have mercy on him, and he will say, "Free him, so that he will not descend to destruction. I have found a reason to be favorable to him.

25 His body is consumed by suffering. Let him return to the days of his youth."

26 He will beg pardon from God, and he will be soothing to him; and he will look upon his face in jubilation, and he will restore his justice to man.

27 He will consider mankind, and he will say: "I have sinned and truly I have offended, yet I was not treated as I deserved."

28 He has freed his soul from continuing into destruction, so that, in living, it may see the light.

29 Behold, all these things God works three times within each one,

30 so that he may revive their souls from corruption and enlighten them with the light of life.

31 Pay attention Job, and listen to me; and remain silent, while I speak.

32 Yet, if you have anything to say, answer me and speak, for I want you to be treated justly.

33 But if you do not have anything to say, then listen to me. Be quiet and I will teach you wisdom.

Job 34

1 After proclaiming these things, Eliu now had this to say:

2 May the wise hear my words, and may the educated listen to me.

3 For the ear examines words, and the mouth discerns foods by the taste.

4 Let us choose judgment for ourselves, and let us consider among ourselves what is best.

5 For Job has said: "I am just, yet God has subverted my judgment.

6 For, within my judgment, there is a lie: my vehement barbs are without any sin."

7 What man is there that is like Job, who drinks up derision as if it were water,

8 who accompanies those who work iniquity, and who walks with impious men?

9 For he has said, "Man will not please God, even if he should travel with him."

10 Therefore, prudent men, hear me: impiety is far from God, and iniquity is far from the Almighty.

11 For he will restore to man his works, and according to the ways of each, he will repay them.

12 For truly, God will not condemn in vain, nor will the Almighty repudiate judgment.

13 What other is established over the earth? Or whom has he placed over the world, which he made?

14 But, if he directs his heart towards him, he will draw his spirit and breath to himself.

15 All flesh will fail together, and man will return to ashes.

16 Therefore, if you have understanding, hear what is said, and heed the sound of my eloquence.

17 Is he that does not love judgment able to be corrected? And how can you so greatly condemn him who is just?

18 He says to the king, "You are an apostate." He calls commanders impious.

19 He does not accept the reputation of leaders; nor does he recognize the tyrant as he contends against the poor. For all are the work of his hands.

20 They will die suddenly, and the people will be troubled in the middle of the night, but they will pass through it, and the violent will be taken away without a hand.

21 For his eyes are upon the ways of men, and he examines all of their steps.

22 There is no darkness and no shadow of death, where those who work iniquity may be hidden.

23 For it is no longer within the power of man to enter into judgment with God.

24 He will break into many innumerable pieces, and he will cause others to stand up in their place.

25 For he knows their works, and, as a result, he will bring the night, and they will be crushed.

26 Just as the impious do, he has struck them in a place where they can be seen.

27 They, as if with great diligence, have withdrawn from him, and they refused to understand all his ways,

28 so that they caused the outcry of the needy to reach him, and he heard the voice of the poor.

29 For, when he grants peace, who is there that can condemn? When he hides his face, who is there that can contemplate him, either among the nations, or among all men?

30 He causes a hypocritical man to reign because of the sins of the people.

31 Therefore, since I have been speaking about God, I will not prevent you from doing the same.

32 If I have erred, you may teach me; if I have spoken unfairly, I will add no more.

33 Does God require this of you because it is displeasing to you? For you were the first to speak, and not I. But if you know something better, speak.

34 Let men of understanding speak to me, and let a wise man listen to me.

35 But Job has been speaking foolishly, and his words contain unsound teaching.

36 My father, let Job be tested even to the end; may you not retreat from a man of iniquity.

37 For he adds blasphemy on top of his sins; nevertheless, let him be constrained to be among us, and then let him provoke God to judgment with his speeches.

Job 35

1 After this, Eliu again spoke in this way:

2 Does it seem right to you in your thoughts, that you should say, "I am more just than God?"

3 For you said, "Having done what is right does not please you," and, "How will it benefit you, if I sin?"

4 And so, I will respond to your words, and to your friends who are with you.

5 Look up towards heaven and consider; also, think about the sky, which is higher than you.

6 If you sin, how will it hurt him? And if your iniquities are multiplied, what will you do against him?

7 Furthermore, if you act justly, what will you give him, or what will he receive from your hand?

8 Your impiety may hurt a man who is like you, though your justice may help the son of the man.

9 Because of the multitude of false accusers, they will cry out; and they will lament because of the strong arm of the tyrants.

10 Yet he has not said: "Where is God, who made me, who has given songs in the night,

11 who teaches us in addition to the beasts of the earth, and who educates us along with the birds of the air?"

12 There they will cry, and he will not heed them, because of the arrogance of the wicked.

13 Therefore, God does not hear in vain, and the Almighty will look into each and every case.

14 And so, when you say, "He does not examine," be judged before him, but wait for him.

15 For, at the present time, he does not bring forth his fury, nor does he punish sin exceedingly.

16 Therefore, Job has opened his mouth in vain and has multiplied words without knowledge.

Job 36

1 Continuing in a similar manner, Eliu had this to say:

2 Bear with me for a little while and I will show you; for I have still more to say in favor of God.

3 I will review my knowledge from the beginning, and I will prove my Maker to be just.

4 For truly my words are without any falsehood and perfect knowledge will be proven to you.

5 God does not abandon the powerful, for he himself is also powerful.

6 But he does not save the impious, though he grants judgment to the poor.

7 He will not take his eyes away from the just, and he continually establishes kings on their throne, and they are exalted.

8 And, if they are in captivity, or are bound with the chains of poverty,

9 he will reveal to them their works, as well as their sinfulness, in that they were violent.

10 Likewise, he will open their ears to his correction, and he will speak to them, so that they may return from iniquity.

11 If they listen and obey, they will fill their days with goodness and complete their years in glory.

12 But if they will not listen, they will pass away by the sword and will be consumed by foolishness.

13 The false and the crafty provoke the wrath of God, yet they do not cry out to him when they are chained.

14 Their soul will die in a storm, and their life, among the unmanly.

15 He will rescue the poor from his anguish, and he will open his ear during tribulation.

16 Therefore, he will save you from the narrow mouth very widely, even though it has no foundation under it. Moreover, your respite at table will be full of fatness.

17 Your case has been judged like that of the impious; you will withdraw your plea and your judgment.

18 Therefore, do not let anger overwhelm you so that you oppress another; neither should you allow a multitude of gifts to influence you.

19 Lay down your greatness without distress, and put aside all of your power with courage.

20 Do not prolong the night, even if people rise on their behalf.

21 Be careful that you do not turn to iniquity; for, after your misery, you have begun to follow this.

22 Behold, God is exalted in his strength, and there is no one like him among the law-givers.

23 Who is able to investigate his ways? And who can say, "You have done iniquity," to him?

24 Remember that you are ignorant of his work, yet men have sung its praises.

25 All men consider him; and each one ponders from a distance.

26 Behold, God is great, defeating our knowledge; the number of his years is inestimable.

27 He carries away the drops of rain, and he sends forth showers like a raging whirlpool;

28 they flow from the clouds that are woven above everything.

29 If he wills it, he extends the clouds as his tent

30 and shines with his light from above; likewise, he covers the oceans within his tent.

31 For he judges the people by these things, and he gives food to a multitude of mortals.

32 Within his hands, he hides the light, and he commands it to come forth again.

33 He announces it to his friend, for it is his possession and he is able to reach out to it.

Job 37

1 At this, my heart became frightened, and it has been moved from its place.

2 Pay close attention to the alarm of his voice and to the sound that proceeds from his mouth.

3 He beholds everything under the heavens, and his light reaches beyond the ends of the earth.

4 After this, a noise will sound; he will thunder with the voice of his greatness, and it will not be tracked down, yet his voice will be obeyed.

5 God will thunder with his voice miraculously, for he performs great and unsearchable things.

6 He commands the snow to descend on earth, and the winter rains, and the shower of his strength.

7 He signs the hand of all men, so that each one may know his works.

8 The beast will enter his hiding-place, and he will remain in his cave.

9 From the interior, a storm will come forth, and a cold winter from the north.

10 As God breathes out, frost forms, and the waters are poured forth very widely again.

11 Crops desire clouds, and the clouds scatter their light.

12 It shines all around, wherever the will of him that governs them will lead, to anywhere he will command, over the whole face of the earth,

13 whether in one tribe, or in his own region, or in whatever place of his mercy that he will order them to be found.

14 Listen to these things, Job. Stand up and consider the wonders of God.

15 Do you know when God ordered the rains, so as to show the light of his clouds?

16 Do you know the great paths of the clouds, and the perfect sciences?

17 Are not your garments hot, when the south wind blows across the land?

18 Perhaps you have made the heavens with him, which are very solid, as if they had been cast from brass.

19 Reveal to us what we should say to him, for, of course, we are wrapped in darkness.

20 Who will explain to him the things that I am saying? Even while a man is still speaking, he will be devoured.

21 Although they do not see the light, the air will be thickened suddenly into clouds, and the wind, passing by, will drive them away.

22 Riches arrive from the north, and fearful praise reaches out to God.

23 We are not worthy to be able to find him. Great in strength, great in judgment, great in justice: he is indescribable.

24 Therefore, men will fear him, and all those who seem to themselves to be wise, will not dare to contemplate him.

Job 38

1 But the Lord, responding to Job from a whirlwind, said:

2 Who is this that wraps sentences in unskilled words?

3 Gird your waist like a man. I will question you, and you must answer me.

4 Where were you, when I set the foundations of the earth? Tell me, if you have understanding.

5 Who set its measurements, if you know, or who stretched a line over it?

6 Upon what have its bases been grounded, and who set forth its cornerstone,

7 when the morning stars praised me together, and all the sons of God made a joyful noise?

8 Who enclosed the sea with doors, when it broke forth as if issuing from the womb,

9 when I stationed a cloud as its garment and wrapped it in a mist as if swaddling an infant?

10 I encircled it with my limits, and I positioned its bars and doors.

11 And I said: "This far you will approach, and you will proceeded no further, and here you will break your swelling waves."

12 Did you, after your birth, command the birth of the sun and show the sunrise its place?

13 And did you hold the extremities of the earth, shaking them, and have you shaken the impious out of it?

14 The seal will be restored like clay, and it will remain in place like a garment.

15 From the impious, the light will be taken away, and the exalted arm will be broken.

16 Have you entered the depths of the sea, and have you taken a walk in the uttermost parts of the abyss?

17 Have the gates of death been opened to you, and have you seen the doors of darkness?

18 Have you considered the breadth of the earth? If you know all things, reveal them to me.

19 Which is the way that holds the light, and which is the place of darkness?

20 In this way, you might lead each thing to its final place, and understand the paths of its house.

21 So then, did you know when you were to be born? And did you know the number of your days?

22 Have you been admitted into the storehouses of the snows, and have you gazed upon the stockpile of the brimstone,

23 which I have prepared for the time of the enemy, for the day of the battle and the war?

24 In what way is the light scattered, and the heat distributed, over the earth?

25 Who gave a course to the rainstorms, and a path to the resounding thunder,

26 so that it would rain on the earth far from man, in the wilderness where no mortal lingers,

27 so that it would fill impassable and desolate places, and would bring forth green plants?

28 Who is the father of rain, or who conceived the drops of dew?

29 From whose womb did the ice proceed, and who created the frost from the air?

30 The waters are hardened to become like stone, and the surface of the abyss freezes over.

31 Will you have the strength to join together the sparkling stars of the Pleiades, or are you able to disperse the circling of Arcturus?

32 Can you bring forth the morning star, in its time, and make the evening star rise over the sons of the earth?

33 Do you know the order of heaven, and can you explain its rules here on the earth?

34 Can you lift up your voice to the clouds, so that an onslaught of waters will cover you?

35 Can you send forth lightning bolts, and will they go, and on returning, say to you: "Here we are?"

36 Who placed discernment in the guts of man, or who gave the rooster intelligence?

37 Who can describe the rules of the heavens, or who can put to rest the harmony of heaven?

38 When was the dust cast to become the earth, and when were its clods fastened together?

39 Will you seize prey for the lioness, and will you sustain the lives of her young,

40 as they rest in their dens or lie in wait in pits?

41 Who provides the raven with its meal, when her chicks cry out to God, as they wander around because they have no food?

Job 39

1 Do you know at what time the wild goats have given birth among the rocks, or do you observe the deer when they go into labor?

2 Have you numbered the months since their conception, and do you know at what time they gave birth?

3 They bend themselves for their offspring, and they give birth, and they emit roars.

4 Their young are weaned and go out to feed; they depart and do not return to them.

5 Who has set the wild ass free, and who has released his bonds?

6 I have given a house in solitude to him, and his tabernacle is in the salted land.

7 He despises the crowded city; he does not pay attention to the bellow of the tax collector.

8 He looks around the mountains of his pasture, and he searches everywhere for green plants.

9 Will the rhinoceros be willing to serve you, and will he remain in your stall?

10 Can you detain the rhinoceros with your harness to plough for you, and will he loosen the soil of the furrows behind you?

11 Will you put your faith in his great strength, and delegate your labors to him?

12 Will you trust him to return to you the seed, and to gather it on your drying floor?

13 The wing of the ostrich is like the wings of the heron, and of the hawk.

14 When she leaves eggs behind in the earth, will you perhaps warm them in the dust?

15 She forgets that feet may trample them, or that the beasts of the field may shatter them.

16 She is hardened against her young, as if they were not hers; she has labored in vain, with no fear compelling her.

17 For God has deprived her of wisdom; neither has he given her understanding.

18 Yet, when the time is right, she raises her wings on high; she ridicules the horse and his rider.

19 Will you supply strength to the horse, or envelope his throat with neighing?

20 Will you alarm him as the locusts do? His panic is revealed by the display of his nostrils.

21 He digs at the earth with his hoof; he jumps around boldly; he advances to meet armed men.

22 He despises fear; he does not turn away from the sword.

23 Above him, the quiver rattles, the spear and the shield shake.

24 Seething and raging, he drinks up the earth; neither does he pause when the blast of the trumpet sounds.

25 When he hears the bugle, he says, "Ha!" He smells the battle from a distance, the exhortation of the officers, and the battle cry of the soldiers.

26 Does the hawk grow feathers by means of your wisdom, spreading her wings towards the south?

27 Will the eagle lift herself up at your command and make her nest in steep places?

28 She dwells among the rocks, and she lingers among broken boulders and inaccessible cliffs.

29 From there, she looks for food, and her eyes catch sight of it from far away.

30 Her young will drink blood, and wherever the carcass will be, she is there immediately.

31 And the Lord continued, and he said to Job:

32 Will he who contends with God be so easily silenced? Certainly, he who argues with God must also respond to him.

33 Then Job answered the Lord, saying:

34 What could I possibly answer, since I have been speaking thoughtlessly? I will place my hand over my mouth.

35 One thing I have spoken, which I wish I had not said; and another, to which I will add no more.

Job 40

1 But the Lord, answering Job out of the whirlwind, said:

2 Gird your waist like a man. I will question you, and you must answer me.

3 Will you make my judgment null and void; and will you condemn me so that you may be justified?

4 And do you have an arm like God, or a voice like thunder?

5 Envelop yourself with splendor, and raise yourself up on high, and be glorious, and put on splendid garments.

6 Scatter the arrogant with your wrath, and, when you see all the arrogant, humble them.

7 Look down upon each of the arrogant and confound them, and crush the impious in their place.

8 Hide them in the dust together and plunge their faces into the pit.

9 Then I will confess that your right hand is able to save you.

10 Behold, the behemoth, whom I created along with you, eats hay like an ox.

11 His strength is in his lower back, and his power is in the center of his abdomen.

12 He draws up his tail like a cedar; the sinews of his thighs have been drawn together.

13 His bones are like pipes of brass; his cartilage is like plates of iron.

14 He is the beginning of the ways of God, who made him; he will use him as his sword.

15 The mountains bring forth grass for him; all the beasts of the field will play there.

16 He sleeps in the shadows, under the cover of branches, and in moist places.

17 The shadows cover his shadow; the willows of the brook will encircle him.

18 Behold, he will drink a river and not be amazed, and he has confidence that the Jordan could flow into his mouth.

19 He will seize him through his eyes, as if with a hook, and he will bore through his nostrils, as if with stakes.

20 Can you draw out the leviathan with a hook, and can you bind his tongue with a cord?

21 Can you place a ring in his nose, or bore through his jaw with an arm band?

22 Will he offer many prayers to you, or speak to you quietly?

23 Will he form a covenant with you, and will you accept him as a servant forever?

24 Will you play with him as with a bird, or tether him for your handmaids?

25 Will your friends cut him into pieces, will dealers distribute him?

26 Will you fill up bags with his hide, and let his head be used as a home for fishes?

27 Place your hand upon him; remember the battle and speak no more.

28 Behold, his hope will fail him, and in the sight of all, he will be thrown down.

Job 41

1 I will not rouse him, as the cruel would do, for who is able to withstand my countenance?

2 Who has given to me beforehand, so that I should repay him? All things that are under heaven are mine.

3 I will not spare him, nor his powerful words and counterfeit attempts at supplication.

4 Who can reveal the beauty of his garment? And who can enter the middle of his mouth?

5 Who can open the doors of his face? I gave fear to the circle of his teeth.

6 His body is like shields fused together, like dense scales pressed over one another.

7 One is joined to another, and not even air can pass between them.

8 They adhere to one another, and they hold themselves in place and will not be separated.

9 His sneezing has the brilliance of fire, and his eyes are like the eyelids of the morning.

10 Lamps proceed from his mouth, like torches of fire burning brightly.

11 Smoke passes out of his nostrils, like a pot that is heated and boiling.

12 His breath causes coal to burn, and a flame comes forth from his mouth.

13 Strength dwells in his neck, and destitution goes before his presence.

14 The parts of his body work in harmony together. He will send lightning bolts against him, and they will not be carried to another place.

15 His heart will be as hard as a stone and as dense as a blacksmith's anvil.

16 When he will be raised up, the angels will be afraid, and, because they are terrified, they will purify themselves.

17 When a sword catches up with him, it will not be able to settle in, nor a spear, nor a breastplate.

18 For he will consider iron as if it were chaff, and brass as if it were rotten wood.

19 The archer will not cause him to flee; the stones of the sling have been turned into stubble for him.

20 He will treat the hammer as if it were stubble, and he will ridicule those who brandish the spear.

21 The beams of the sun will be under him, and he will dispense gold to them as if it were clay.

22 He will make the depths of the sea boil like a pot, and he will set it to bubble just as ointments do.

23 A path will shine after him; he will esteem the abyss as if it were weakening with age.

24 There is no power on the earth that is being compared to him, who has been made so that he fears no one.

25 He sees every prominent thing; he is king over all the sons of arrogance.

Job 42

1 Then Job, responding to the Lord, said:

2 I know that you are able to do all things, and that no thoughts are hidden from you.

3 So, who is it that would disguise a lack of knowledge as counsel? Therefore, I have been speaking foolishly, about things whose measure exceeds my knowledge.

4 Listen, and I will speak. I will question you, and you may answer me.

5 By paying attention with the ear, I have heard you, but now my eye sees you.

6 Therefore, I find myself reprehensible, and I will do penance in embers and ashes.

7 But after the Lord had finished speaking these words to Job, he said to Eliphaz the Themanite: My wrath has been kindled against you, and against your two friends, because you have not been speaking correctly in my eyes, as my servant Job has done.

8 Therefore, have seven bulls and seven rams brought to you, and go to my servant Job, and offer these as a holocaust for yourselves. But also, my servant Job will pray for you; I will accept his face, so that foolishness will not be imputed to you. For you have not been speaking correctly about me, as my servant Job has done.

9 So Eliphaz the Themanite, and Baldad the Suhite, and Zophar the Naamathite departed, and they did just as the Lord had spoken to them, and the Lord accepted the face of Job.

10 Likewise, the Lord was moved by the repentance of Job, when he prayed for his friends. And the Lord gave to Job twice as much as he had before.

11 Yet all his brethren came to him, and all his sisters, and everyone who had known him before, and they ate bread with him in his house. They also shook their heads over him and comforted him, because of all the bad things that God had inflicted on him. And each one of them gave him one female sheep, and one earring of gold.

12 And the Lord blessed the latter end of Job even more than his beginning. And he had fourteen thousand sheep, and six thousand camels, and a thousand pairs of oxen, and a thousand she-donkeys.

13 And he had seven sons and three daughters.

14 And he called the name of one, Daylight, and the name of the second, Cinnamon, and the name of the third, Horn of Cosmetics.

15 And, in the whole world, there were not found women so beautiful as the daughters of Job. And so their father gave them an inheritance along with their brothers.

16 But Job lived long after these events, for a hundred and forty years, and he saw his children, and his children's children, all the way to the fourth generation, and he died an old man and full of days.

Psalms 2

1 Why have the Gentiles been seething, and why have the people been pondering nonsense?

2 The kings of the earth have stood up, and the leaders have joined together as one, against the Lord and against his Christ:

3 "Let us shatter their chains and cast their yoke away from us."

4 He who dwells in heaven will ridicule them, and the Lord will mock them.

5 Then will he speak to them in his anger and trouble them with his fury.

6 Yet I have been appointed king by him over Zion, his holy mountain, preaching his precepts.

7 The Lord has said to me: You are my son, this day have I begotten you.

8 Ask of me and I will give to you: the Gentiles for your inheritance, and the ends of the earth for your possession.

9 You will rule them with an iron rod, and you will shatter them like a potter's vessel.

10 And now, O kings, understand. Receive instruction, you who judge the earth.

11 Serve the Lord in fear, and exult in him with trembling.

12 Embrace discipline, lest at any time the Lord might become angry, and you would perish from the way of the just.

13 Though his wrath can flare up in a short time, blessed are all those who trust in him.

Psalms 5

1 Unto the end. For her who pursues the inheritance. A Psalm of David.

2 O Lord, listen closely to my words. Understand my outcry.

3 Attend to the voice of my prayer, my King and my God.

4 For to you, I will pray. In the morning, Lord, you will hear my voice.

5 In the morning, I will stand before you, and I will see. For you are not a God who wills iniquity.

6 And the malicious will not dwell close to you, nor will the unjust endure before your eyes.

7 You hate all who work iniquity. You will destroy all who speak a lie. The bloody and deceitful man, the Lord will abominate.

8 But I am in the multitude of your mercy. I will enter your house. I will show adoration toward your holy temple, in your fear.

9 Lord, lead me in your justice. Because of my enemies, direct my way in your sight.

10 For there is no truth in their mouth: their heart is vain.

11 Their throat is an open sepulcher. They have acted deceitfully with their tongues. Judge them, O God. Let them fall by their own intentions: according to the multitude of their impiety, expel them. For they have provoked you, O Lord.

12 But let all those who hope in you rejoice. They will exult in eternity, and you will dwell in them. And all those who love your name will glory in you.

13 For you will bless the just. You have crowned us, O Lord, as if with a shield of your good will.

Psalms 7

1 A Psalm of David, which he sang to the Lord because of the words of Cush, the son of Jemini.

2 O Lord, my God, in you I have hoped. Save me from all those who persecute me, and free me:

3 lest at any time, like a lion, he might seize my soul, while there is no one to redeem me, nor any who can save.

4 O Lord, my God, if there is iniquity in my hands, if I have done this:

5 if I have repaid those who rendered evils to me, may I deservedly fall away empty before my enemies:

6 let the enemy pursue my soul, and take hold of it, and trample my life into the earth, and drag down my glory into the dust.

7 Rise up, Lord, in your anger. And be exalted to the borders of my enemies. And rise up, O Lord my God, according to the precept that you commanded,

8 and a congregation of people will surround you. And, because of this, return on high.

9 The Lord judges the people. Judge me, O Lord, according to my justice and according to my innocence within me.

10 The wickedness of sinners will be consumed, and you will direct the just: the examiner of hearts and temperaments is God.

11 Just is my help from the Lord, who saves the upright of heart.

12 God is a just judge, strong and patient. How could he be angry throughout every day?

13 Unless you will be converted, he will brandish his sword. He has extended his bow and made it ready.

14 And with it, he has prepared instruments of death. He has produced his arrows for those on fire.

15 Behold him who has given birth to injustice: he has conceived sorrow and has begotten iniquity.

16 He has opened a pit and enlarged it. And he has fallen into the hole that he made.

17 His sorrow will be turned upon his own head, and his iniquity will descend upon his highest point.

18 I will confess to the Lord according to his justice, and I will sing a psalm to the name of the Lord Most High.

Psalms 9

1 Unto the end. For the secrets of the Son. A Psalm of David.

2 I will confess to you, Lord, with my whole heart. I will recount all your wonders.

3 I will rejoice and exult in you. I will sing a psalm to your name, O Most High.

4 For my enemy will be turned back. They will be weakened and perish before your face.

5 For you have accomplished my judgment and my cause. You have sat upon the throne that judges justice.

6 You have rebuked the Gentiles, and the impious one has perished. You have deleted their name in eternity and for all generations.

7 The spears of the enemy have failed in the end, and their cities, you have destroyed. Their memory has perished with a loud noise.

8 But the Lord remains in eternity. He has prepared his throne in judgment.

9 And he will judge the whole world in equity. He will judge the people in justice.

10 And the Lord has become a refuge for the poor, a helper in opportunity, in tribulation.

11 And may they hope in you, who know your name. For you have not abandoned those seeking you, Lord.

12 Sing a psalm to the Lord, who dwells in Zion. Announce his study among the Gentiles.

13 Because of those who yearned for their blood, he has remembered them. He has not forgotten the cry of the poor.

14 Have mercy on me, Lord. See my humiliation from my enemies.

15 You lift me up from the gates of death, so that I may announce all your praises at the gates of the daughter of Zion.

16 I will exult in your salvation. The Gentiles have become trapped in the ruin that they made. Their foot has been caught in the same snare that they themselves had hidden.

17 The Lord will be recognized when making judgments. The sinner has been caught in the works of his own hands.

18 The sinners will be turned into Hell: all the Gentiles who have forgotten God.

19 For the poor will not be forgotten in the end. The patience of the poor will not perish in the end.

20 Rise up, Lord: do not let man be strengthened. Let the Gentiles be judged in your sight.

21 O Lord, establish a lawgiver over them, so that the Gentiles may know that they are only men.

22 So then, why, O Lord, have you withdrawn far away? Why have you overlooked us in opportunity, in tribulation?

23 While the impious is arrogant, the poor is enflamed. They are held by the counsels that they devise.

24 For the sinner is praised by the desires of his soul, and the iniquitous is blessed.

25 The sinner has provoked the Lord; according to the multitude of his wrath, he will not seek him.

26 God is not before his sight. His ways are stained at all times. Your judgments are removed from his face. He will be master of all his enemies.

27 For he has said in his heart, "I will not be disturbed: from generation to generation without evil."

28 His mouth is full of curses, and bitterness, and deceit. Under his tongue are hardship and sorrow.

29 He sits in ambush, with resources in hidden places, so that he may execute the innocent.

30 His eyes catch sight of the poor. He lies in ambush, in hiding like a lion in his den. He lies in ambush, so that he may seize the poor, to seize the poor as he draws him in.

31 With his snare, he will bring him down. He will crouch down and pounce, when he has power over the poor.

32 For he has said in his heart, "God has forgotten, he has turned away his face, lest he see to the end."

33 O Lord God, rise up. Let your hand be exalted. Do not forget the poor.

34 How has the impious one provoked God? For he has said in his heart, "He will not inquire."

35 You do see, for you examine hardship and sorrow, so that you may deliver them into your hands. The poor one has been abandoned to you. You will be a helper to the orphan.

36 Break the arm of the sinner and the malicious. His sin will be sought, and it will not be found.

37 The Lord shall reign in eternity, even forever and ever. You will perish the Gentiles from his land.

38 The Lord has heeded the desire of the poor. Your ear has listened to the preparation of their heart,

39 so as to judge for the orphan and the humble, so that man may no longer presume to magnify himself upon the earth.

Psalms 13

1 Unto the end. A Psalm of David. The fool has said in his heart, "There is no God." They were corrupted, and they have become abominable in their studies. There is no one who does good; there is not even one.

2 The Lord has looked down from heaven upon the sons of men, to see if there were any who were considering or seeking God.

3 They have all gone astray; together they have become useless. There is no one who does good; there is not even one.

4 Their throat is an open sepulcher. With their tongues, they have been acting deceitfully; the venom of asps is under their lips. Their mouth is full of curses and bitterness.

5 Their feet are swift to shed blood. Grief and unhappiness are in their ways; and the way of peace, they have not known.

6 There is no fear of God before their eyes.

7 Will they never learn: all those who work iniquity, who devour my people like a meal of bread?

8 They have not called upon the Lord. There, they have trembled in fear, where there was no fear.

9 For the Lord is with the just generation. You have confounded the counsel of the needy because the Lord is his hope.

10 Who will grant the salvation of Israel from Zion? When the Lord turns away the captivity of his people, Jacob will exult, and Israel will rejoice.

Psalms 15

1 The inscription of a title: of David himself. Preserve me, O Lord, because I have hoped in you.

2 I have said to the Lord: "You are my God, so you have no need of my goodness."

3 As for the saints, who are in his land: he has made all my desires wonderful in them.

4 Their infirmities have been multiplied; after this, they acted more quickly. I will not gather for their convocations of blood, nor will I remember their names with my lips.

5 The Lord is the portion of my inheritance and my cup. It is you who will restore my inheritance to me.

6 The lots have fallen upon me with clarity. And, indeed, my inheritance has been very clear to me.

7 I will bless the Lord, who has bestowed understanding upon me. Moreover, my temperament has also corrected me, even through the night.

8 I have made provision for the Lord always in my sight. For he is at my right hand, so that I may not be disturbed.

9 Because of this, my heart has been joyful, and my tongue has exulted. Moreover, even my body will rest in hope.

10 For you will not abandon my soul to Hell, nor will you allow your holy one to see corruption.

11 You have made known to me the ways of life; you will fill me with joy by your countenance. At your right hand are delights, even to the end.

Psalms 16

1 A Prayer of David. Lord, listen to my justice, attend to my supplication. Pay attention to my prayer, which is not from deceitful lips.

2 Let my judgment proceed from your presence. Let your eyes behold fairness.

3 You have tested my heart and visited it by night. You have examined me by fire, and iniquity has not been found in me.

4 Therefore, may my mouth not speak the works of men. I have kept to difficult ways because of the words of your lips.

5 Perfect my steps in your paths, so that my footsteps may not be disturbed.

6 I have cried out because you, O God, have listened to me. Incline your ear to me and heed my words.

7 Make your mercies wonderful, for you save those who hope in you.

8 From those who resist your right hand, preserve me like the pupil of your eye. Protect me under the shadow of your wings,

9 from the face of the impious who have afflicted me. My enemies have surrounded my soul.

10 They have concealed their fatness; their mouth has been speaking arrogantly.

11 They have cast me out, and now they have surrounded me. They have cast their eyes down to the earth.

12 They have taken me, like a lion ready for the prey, and like a young lion dwelling in hiding.

13 Rise up, O Lord, arrive before him and displace him. Deliver my soul from the impious one: your spear from the enemies of your hand.

14 Lord, divide them from the few of the earth in their life. Their gut has been filled from your hidden stores. They have been filled with sons, and they have bequeathed to their little ones the remainder.

15 But as for me, I will appear before your sight in justice. I will be satisfied when your glory appears.

Psalms 17

1 Unto the end. For David, the servant of the Lord, who spoke the words of this canticle to the Lord, in the day that the Lord delivered him from the hand of all his enemies and from the hand of Saul. And he said:

2 I will love you, O Lord my strength.

3 The Lord is my firmament, my refuge, and my liberator. My God is my helper, and I hope in him: my protector, and the horn of my salvation, and my support.

4 Praising, I will call upon the Lord. And I will be saved from my enemies.

5 The sorrows of death surrounded me, and the torrents of iniquity dismayed me.

6 The sorrows of Hell encompassed me, and the snares of death intercepted me.

7 In my tribulation, I called upon the Lord, and I cried out to my God. And he listened to my voice from his holy temple. And my cry in his presence entered into his ears.

8 The earth was shaken, and it trembled. The foundations of the mountains were disturbed, and they were shaken, because he was angry with them.

9 A smoke ascended by his wrath, and a fire flared up from his face: coals were kindled by it.

10 He bent the heavens, and they descended. And darkness was under his feet.

11 And he ascended upon the cherubim, and he flew: he flew upon the feathers of the winds.

12 And he set darkness as his hiding place, with his tabernacle all around him: dark waters in the clouds of the air.

13 At the brightness that was before his sight, the clouds crossed by, with hail and coals of fire.

14 And the Lord thundered from heaven, and the Most High uttered his voice: hail and coals of fire.

15 And he sent forth his arrows and scattered them. He multiplied lightnings, and he set them in disarray.

16 Then the fountains of waters appeared, and the foundations of the world were revealed, by your rebuke, O Lord, by the inspiration of the Spirit of your wrath.

17 He sent from on high, and he accepted me. And he took me up, out of many waters.

18 He rescued me from my strongest enemies, and from those who hated me. For they had been too strong for me.

19 They intercepted me in the day of my affliction, and the Lord became my protector.

20 And he led me out, into a wide place. He accomplished my salvation, because he willed me.

21 And the Lord will reward me according to my justice, and he will repay me according to the purity of my hands.

22 For I have preserved the ways of the Lord, and I have not behaved impiously before my God.

23 For all his judgments are in my sight, and his justice, I have not pushed away from me.

24 And I will be immaculate together with him, and I will keep myself from my iniquity.

25 And the Lord will reward me according to my justice and according to the purity of my hands before his eyes.

26 With the holy, you will be holy, and with the innocent, you will be innocent,

27 and with the elect, you will be elect, and with the perverse, you will be perverse.

28 For you will save the humble people, but you will bring down the eyes of the arrogant.

29 For you illuminate my lamp, O Lord. My God, enlighten my darkness.

30 For in you, I will be delivered from temptation; and with my God, I will climb over a wall.

31 As for my God, his way is undefiled. The eloquence of the Lord has been examined by fire. He is the protector of all who hope in him.

32 For who is God, except the Lord? And who is God, except our God?

33 It is God who has wrapped me with virtue and made my way immaculate.

34 It is he who has perfected my feet, like the feet of deer, and who stations me upon the heights.

35 It is he who trains my hands for battle. And you have set my arms like a bow of brass.

36 And you have given me the protection of your salvation. And your right hand sustains me. And your discipline has corrected me unto the end. And your discipline itself will teach me.

37 You have expanded my footsteps under me, and my tracks have not been weakened.

38 I will pursue my enemies and apprehend them. And I will not turn back until they have failed.

39 I will break them, and they will not be able to stand. They will fall under my feet.

40 And you have wrapped me with virtue for the battle. And those rising up against me, you have subdued under me.

41 And you have given the back of my enemies to me, and you have destroyed those who hated me.

42 They cried out, but there was none to save them, to the Lord, but he did not heed them.

43 And I will crush them into dust before the face of the wind, so that I will obliterate them like the mud in the streets.

44 You will rescue me from the contradictions of the people. You will set me at the head of the Gentiles.

45 A people I did not know has served me. As soon as their ears heard, they were obedient to me.

46 The sons of foreigners have been deceitful to me, the sons of foreigners have grown weak with time, and they have wavered from their paths.

47 The Lord lives, and blessed is my God, and may the God of my salvation be exalted:

48 O God, who vindicates me and who subdues the people under me, my liberator from my enraged enemies.

49 And you will exalt me above those who rise up against me. From the iniquitous man, you will rescue me.

50 Because of this, O Lord, I will confess to you among the nations, and I will compose a psalm to your name:

51 magnifying the salvation of his king, and showing mercy to David, his Christ, and to his offspring, even for all time.

Psalms 18

1 Unto the end. A Psalm of David.

2 The heavens describe the glory of God, and the firmament announces the work of his hands.

3 Day proclaims the word to day, and night to night imparts knowledge.

4 There are no speeches or conversations, where their voices are not being heard.

5 Their sound has gone forth through all the earth, and their words to the ends of the world.

6 He has placed his tabernacle in the sun, and he is like a bridegroom coming out of his bedroom. He has exulted like a giant running along the way;

7 his departure is from the summit of heaven. And his course reaches all the way to its summit. Neither is there anyone who can hide himself from his heat.

8 The law of the Lord is immaculate, converting souls. The testimony of the Lord is faithful, providing wisdom to little ones.

9 The justice of the Lord is right, rejoicing hearts. The precepts of the Lord are brilliant, enlightening the eyes.

10 The fear of the Lord is holy, enduring for all generations. The judgments of the Lord are true, justified in themselves:

11 desirable beyond gold and many precious stones, and sweeter than honey and the honeycomb.

12 For, indeed, your servant keeps them, and in keeping them, there are many rewards.

13 Who can understand transgression? From my hidden faults, cleanse me, O Lord,

14 and from those of others, spare your servant. If they will have no dominion over me, then I will be immaculate, and I will be cleansed from the greatest transgression.

15 And the eloquence of my mouth will be so as to please, along with the meditation of my heart, in your sight, forever, O Lord, my helper and my redeemer.

Psalms 20

1 Unto the end. A Psalm of David.

2 In your virtue, Lord, the king will rejoice, and over your salvation, he will exult exceedingly.

3 You have granted him the desire of his heart, and you have not cheated him of the wish of his lips.

4 For you have gone ahead of him with blessings of sweetness. You have placed a crown of precious stones on his head.

5 He petitioned you for life, and you have granted him length of days, in the present time, and forever and ever.

6 Great is his glory in your salvation. Glory and great adornment, you will lay upon him.

7 For you will give him as a blessing forever and ever. You will make him rejoice with gladness in your presence.

8 Because the king hopes in the Lord, and in the mercy of the Most High, he will not be disturbed.

9 May your hand be found by all your enemies. May your right hand discover all those who hate you.

10 You will make them like an oven of fire, in the time of your presence. The Lord will stir them up with his wrath, and fire will devour them.

11 You will destroy their fruit from the earth and their offspring from the sons of men.

12 For they have turned evils upon you; they have devised plans, which they have not been able to accomplish.

13 For you will make them turn their back; with your remnants, you will prepare their countenance.

14 Be exalted, Lord, by your own power. We will play music and sing psalms to your virtues.

Psalms 21

1 Unto the end. For the tasks of early morning. A Psalm of David.

2 O God, my God, look upon me. Why have you forsaken me? Far from my salvation are the words of my offenses.

3 My God, I will cry out by day, and you will not heed, and by night, and it will not be foolishness for me.

4 But you dwell in holiness, O Praise of Israel.

5 In you, our fathers have hoped. They hoped, and you freed them.

6 They cried out to you, and they were saved. In you, they hoped and were not confounded.

7 But I am a worm and not a man: a disgrace among men, and an outcast of the people.

8 All those who saw me have derided me. They have spoken with the lips and shook the head.

9 He has hoped in the Lord, let him rescue him. Let him save him because he chooses him.

10 For you are the one who has drawn me out of the womb, my hope from the breasts of my mother.

11 I have been thrown upon you from the womb; from the womb of my mother, you are my God.

12 Do not depart from me. For tribulation is near, since there is no one who may help me.

13 Many calves have surrounded me; fat bulls have besieged me.

14 They have opened their mouths over me, just like a lion seizing and roaring.

15 And so, I have been poured out like water, and all my bones have been scattered. My heart has become like wax, melting in the midst of my chest.

16 My strength has dried up like clay, and my tongue has adhered to my jaws. And you have pulled me down, into the dust of death.

17 For many dogs have surrounded me. The council of the malicious has besieged me. They have pierced my hands and feet.

18 They have numbered all my bones. And they have examined me and stared at me.

19 They divided my garments among them, and over my vestment, they cast lots.

20 But you, O Lord, do not take your help far from me; be attentive to my defense.

21 O God, rescue my soul from the spear, and my only one from the hand of the dog.

22 Save me from the mouth of the lion, and my humility from the horns of single-horned beast.

23 I will declare your name to my brothers. In the midst of the Church, I will praise you.

24 You who fear the Lord, praise him. All the offspring of Jacob, glorify him.

25 May all the offspring of Israel fear him. For he has neither spurned nor despised the pleas of the poor. Neither has he turned his face away from me. And when I cried out to him, he heeded me.

26 My praise is with you, within a great church. I will pay my vows in the sight of those who fear him.

27 The poor will eat and be satisfied, and those who yearn for the Lord will praise him. Their hearts will live forever and ever.

28 All the ends of the earth will remember, and they will be converted to the Lord. And all the families of the Gentiles will adore in his sight.

29 For the kingdom belongs to the Lord, and he will have dominion over the Gentiles.

30 All the fat of the earth have gnashed their teeth, and they have adored. In his sight, they will fall down, all those who descend to the ground.

31 And my soul will live for him, and my offspring will serve him.

32 There will be announced for the Lord a future generation, and the heavens will announce his justice to a people who will be born, whom the Lord has made.

Psalms 24

1 Unto the end. A Psalm of David. To you, Lord, I have lifted up my soul.

2 In you, my God, I trust. Let me not be put to shame.

3 And do not let my enemies laugh at me. For all who remain with you will not be confounded.

4 May all those who act unjustly over nothing be confounded. O Lord, demonstrate your ways to me, and teach me your paths.

5 Direct me in your truth, and teach me. For you are God, my Saviour, and I remain with you all day long.

6 O Lord, remember your compassion and your mercies, which are from ages past.

7 Do not remember the offenses of my youth and my ignorances. Remember me according to your mercy, because of your goodness, O Lord.

8 The Lord is sweet and righteous. Because of this, he will grant a law to those who fall short in the way.

9 He will direct the mild in judgment. He will teach the meek his ways.

10 All the ways of the Lord are mercy and truth, to those who yearn for his covenant and his testimonies.

11 Because of your name, O Lord, you will pardon my sin, for it is great.

12 Which is the man who fears the Lord? He has established a law for him, on the way that he has chosen.

13 His soul will dwell upon good things, and his offspring will inherit the earth.

14 The Lord is a firmament to those who fear him, and his covenant will be made manifest to them.

15 My eyes are ever toward the Lord, for he will pull my feet from the snare.

16 Look upon me and have mercy on me; for I am alone and poor.

17 The troubles of my heart have been multiplied. Deliver me from my needfulness.

18 See my lowliness and my hardship, and release all my offenses.

19 Consider my enemies, for they have been multiplied, and they have hated me with an unjust hatred.

20 Preserve my soul and rescue me. I will not be ashamed, for I have hoped in you.

21 The innocent and the righteous have adhered to me, because I have remained with you.

22 Free Israel, O God, from all his tribulations.

Psalms 25

1 Unto the end. A Psalm of David. Judge me, Lord, for I have been walking in my innocence, and by hoping in the Lord, I will not be weakened.

2 Examine me, Lord, and test me: enkindle my temperament and my heart.

3 For your mercy is before my eyes, and I am serene in your truth.

4 I have not sat with the council of emptiness, and I will not enter with those who carry out injustice.

5 I have hated the assembly of the malicious; and I will not sit with the impious.

6 I will wash my hands among the innocent, and I will surround your altar, O Lord,

7 so that I may hear the voice of your praise and describe all your wonders.

8 O Lord, I have loved the beauty of your house and the dwelling place of your glory.

9 O God, do not let my soul perish with the impious, nor my life with the men of blood,

10 in whose hands are iniquities: their right hand has been filled by bribes.

11 But as for me, I have been walking in my innocence. Redeem me, and have mercy on me.

12 My foot has stood firm in the straight path. In the churches, I will bless you, O Lord.

Psalms 26

1 A Psalm of David, before he was sealed. The Lord is my light and my salvation, whom shall I fear? The Lord is the protector of my life, of whom shall I be afraid?

2 Meanwhile, the guilty draw near to me, so as to eat my flesh. Those who trouble me, my enemies, have themselves been weakened and have fallen.

3 If entrenched armies were to stand together against me, my heart would not fear. If a battle were to rise up against me, I would have hope in this.

4 One thing I have asked of the Lord, this I will seek: that I may dwell in the house of the Lord all the days of my life, so that I may behold the delight of the Lord, and may visit his temple.

5 For he has hidden me in his tabernacle. In the day of evils, he has protected me in the hidden place of his tabernacle.

6 He has exalted me upon the rock, and now he has exalted my head above my enemies. I have circled around and offered a sacrifice of loud exclamation in his tabernacle. I will sing, and I will compose a psalm, to the Lord.

7 Hear my voice, O Lord, with which I have cried out to you. Have mercy on me, and hear me.

8 My heart has spoken to you; my face has sought you. I yearn for your face, O Lord.

9 Do not turn your face away from me. In your wrath, do not turn aside from your servant. Be my helper. Do not abandon me, and do not despise me, O God, my Saviour.

10 For my father and my mother have left me behind, but the Lord has taken me up.

11 O Lord, establish a law for me in your way, and direct me in the right path, because of my enemies.

12 Do not surrender me to the souls of those who trouble me. For unjust witnesses have risen up against me, and iniquity has lied to itself.

13 I believe that I shall see the good things of the Lord in the land of the living.

14 Wait for the Lord, act manfully; and let your heart be strengthened, and remain with the Lord.

Psalms 27

1 A Psalm of David himself. To you, Lord, I will cry out. My God, do not be silent toward me. For if you remain silent toward me, I will become like those who descend into the pit.

2 Hear, O Lord, the voice of my supplication, when I pray to you, when I lift up my hands toward your holy temple.

3 Do not draw me away together with sinners; and let me not perish with those who work iniquity, who speak peacefully to their neighbor, yet evils are in their hearts.

4 Give to them according to their works and according to the wickedness of their inventions. Assign to them according to the works of their hands. Repay them with their own retribution.

5 Since they have not understood the works of the Lord and the works of his hands, you will destroy them, and you will not build them up.

6 Blessed is the Lord, for he has heard the voice of my supplication.

7 The Lord is my helper and my protector. In him, my heart has hoped and I have been helped. And my flesh has flourished again. And from my will, I shall confess to him.

8 The Lord is the strength of his people and the protector of the salvation of his Christ.

9 O Lord, save your people and bless your inheritance, and reign over them and exalt them, even unto eternity.

Psalms 28

1 A Psalm of David, at the completion of the tabernacle. Bring to the Lord, O sons of God, bring to the Lord the sons of rams.

2 Bring to the Lord, glory and honor. Bring to the Lord, glory for his name. Adore the Lord in his holy court.

3 The voice of the Lord is over the waters. The God of majesty has thundered. The Lord is over many waters.

4 The voice of the Lord is in virtue. The voice of the Lord is in magnificence.

5 The voice of the Lord shatters the cedars. And the Lord will shatter the cedars of Lebanon.

6 And it will break them into pieces, like a calf of Lebanon, and in the same way as the beloved son of the single-horned beast.

7 The voice of the Lord cuts through the flame of fire.

8 The voice of the Lord shakes the desert. And the Lord will quake the desert of Kadesh.

9 The voice of the Lord is preparing the stags, and he will reveal the dense woods. And in his temple, all will speak his glory.

10 The Lord causes the great flood to dwell. And the Lord will sit as King in eternity.

11 The Lord will give virtue to his people. The Lord will bless his people in peace.

Psalms 29

1 A Canticle Psalm. In dedication to the house of David.

2 I will extol you, Lord, for you have sustained me, and you have not allowed my enemies to delight over me.

3 O Lord my God, I have cried out to you, and you have healed me.

4 Lord, you led my soul away from Hell. You have saved me from those who descend into the pit.

5 Sing a psalm to the Lord, you his saints, and confess with remembrance of his holiness.

6 For wrath is in his indignation, and life is in his will. Toward evening, weeping will linger, and toward morning, gladness.

7 But I have said in my abundance: "I will never be disturbed."

8 O Lord, in your will, you made virtue preferable to beauty for me. You turned your face away from me, and I became disturbed.

9 To you, Lord, I will cry out. And I will make supplication to my God.

10 What use would there be in my blood, if I descend into corruption? Will dust confess to you or announce your truth?

11 The Lord has heard, and he has been merciful to me. The Lord has become my helper.

12 You have turned my mourning into gladness for me. You have cut off my sackcloth, and you have surrounded me with joy.

13 So then, may my glory sing to you, and may I not regret it. O Lord, my God, I will confess to you for eternity.

Psalms 30

1 Unto the end. A Psalm of David according to an ecstasy.

2 In you, Lord, I have hoped; let me never be confounded. In your justice, deliver me.

3 Incline your ear to me. Hasten to rescue me. Be for me a protector God and a house of refuge, so as to accomplish my salvation.

4 For you are my strength and my refuge; and for the sake of your name, you will lead me and nourish me.

5 You will lead me out of this snare, which they have hidden for me. For you are my protector.

6 Into your hands, I commend my spirit. You have redeemed me, O Lord, God of truth.

7 You have hated those who practice emptiness to no purpose. But I have hoped in the Lord.

8 I will exult and rejoice in your mercy. For you have looked upon my humility; you have saved my soul from needfulness.

9 And you have not enclosed me in the hands of the enemy. You have set my feet in a spacious place.

10 Have mercy on me, Lord, for I am troubled. My eye has been disturbed by wrath, along with my soul and my gut.

11 For my life has fallen into sorrow, and my years into sighing. My virtue has been weakened in poverty, and my bones have been disturbed.

12 I have become a disgrace among all my enemies, and even more so to my neighbors, and a dread to my acquaintances. Those who catch sight of me, flee away from me.

13 I have become forgotten, like one dead to the heart. I have become like a damaged utensil.

14 For I have heard the harsh criticism of many who linger in the area. While assembled together against me in that place, they deliberated on how to take away my life.

15 But I have hoped in you, O Lord. I said, "You are my God."

16 My fate is in your hands. Rescue me from the hand of my enemies and from those who are persecuting me.

17 Shine your face upon your servant. Save me in your mercy.

18 Do not let me be confounded, Lord, for I have called upon you. Let the impious be ashamed and be drawn down into Hell.

19 May deceitful lips be silenced: those that speak iniquity against the just, in arrogance and in abusiveness.

20 How great is the multitude of your sweetness, O Lord, which you keep hidden for those who fear you, which you have perfected for those who hope in you, in the sight of the sons of men.

21 You hide them in the concealment of your face, from the disturbance of men. You protect them in your tabernacle, from the contradiction of tongues.

22 Blessed is the Lord. For he has shown his wonderful mercy to me, in a fortified city.

23 But I said in the excess of my mind: "I have been cast away from the glance of your eyes." And so, you heeded the voice of my prayer, while I was still crying out to you.

24 Love the Lord, all you his saints. For the Lord will require truth, and he will abundantly repay those who act with arrogance.

25 Act manfully, and let your heart be strengthened, all you who hope in the Lord.

Psalms 31

1 The understanding of David himself. Blessed are they whose iniquities have been forgiven and whose sins have been covered.

2 Blessed is the man to whom the Lord has not imputed sin, and in whose spirit there is no deceit.

3 Because I was silent, my bones grew old, while still I cried out all day long.

4 For, day and night, your hand was heavy upon me. I have been converted in my anguish, while still the thorn is piercing.

5 I have acknowledged my offense to you, and I have not concealed my injustice. I said, "I will confess against myself, my injustice to the Lord," and you forgave the impiety of my sin.

6 For this, everyone who is holy will pray to you in due time. Yet truly, in a flood of many waters, they will not draw near to him.

7 You are my refuge from the tribulation that has surrounded me. You are my exultation: rescue me from those who are surrounding me.

8 I will give you understanding, and I will instruct you in this way, in which you will walk. I will fix my eyes upon you.

9 Do not become like the horse and the mule, which have no understanding. Their jaws are constrained with bit and bridle, so as not to draw near to you.

10 Many are the scourges of the sinner, but mercy will surround him that hopes in the Lord.

11 Rejoice in the Lord and exult, you just ones, and glory, all you upright of heart.

Psalms 32

1 A Psalm of David. Exult in the Lord, you just ones; together praise the upright.

2 Confess to the Lord with stringed instruments; sing psalms to him with the psaltery, the instrument of ten strings.

3 Sing to him a new song. Sing psalms to him skillfully, with loud exclamation.

4 For the word of the Lord is upright, and all his works are in faith.

5 He loves mercy and judgment. The earth is full of the mercy of the Lord.

6 By the word of the Lord, the heavens were established, and all their power, by the Spirit of his mouth:

7 gathering together the waters of the sea, as if in a container, placing the depths in storage.

8 Let all the earth fear the Lord, and may all the inhabitants of the world quake before him.

9 For he spoke, and they became. He commanded, and they were created.

10 The Lord scatters the counsels of the nations. Moreover, he reproves the thoughts of the people, and he rejects the counsels of the leaders.

11 But the counsel of the Lord remains for eternity, the thoughts of his heart from generation to generation.

12 Blessed is the nation whose God is the Lord, the people whom he has chosen as his inheritance.

13 The Lord has looked down from heaven. He has seen all the sons of men.

14 From his well-prepared dwelling place, he has gazed upon all who dwell on the earth.

15 He has formed the hearts of each one of them; he understands all their works.

16 The king is not saved by great power, nor will the giant be saved by his many powers.

17 The horse is false safety; for he will not be saved by the abundance of his powers.

18 Behold, the eyes of the Lord are on those who fear him and on those who hope in his mercy,

19 so as to rescue their souls from death and to feed them during famine.

20 Our soul remains with the Lord. For he is our helper and protector.

21 For in him, our heart will rejoice, and in his holy name, we have hoped.

22 Let your mercy be upon us, O Lord, just as we have hoped in you.

Psalms 33

1 To David, when he changed his appearance in the sight of Abimelech, and so he dismissed him, and he went away.

2 I will bless the Lord at all times. His praise will be ever in my mouth.

3 In the Lord, my soul will be praised. May the meek listen and rejoice.

4 Magnify the Lord with me, and let us extol his name in itself.

5 I sought the Lord, and he heeded me, and he carried me away from all my tribulations.

6 Approach him and be enlightened, and your faces will not be confounded.

7 This poor one cried out, and the Lord heeded him, and he saved him from all his tribulations.

8 The Angel of the Lord will encamp around those who fear him, and he will rescue them.

9 Taste and see that the Lord is sweet. Blessed is the man who hopes in him.

10 Fear the Lord, all you his saints. For there is no destitution for those who fear him.

11 The rich have been needy and hungry, but those who seek the Lord will not be deprived of any good thing.

12 Come forward, sons. Listen to me. I will teach you the fear of the Lord.

13 Which is the man who wills life, who chooses to see good days?

14 Prohibit your tongue from evil and your lips from speaking deceit.

15 Turn away from evil, and do good. Inquire about peace, and pursue it.

16 The eyes of the Lord are on the just, and his ears are with their prayers.

17 But the countenance of the Lord is upon those who do evil, to perish the remembrance of them from the earth.

18 The just cried out, and the Lord heard them, and he freed them from all their tribulations.

19 The Lord is near to those who are troubled in heart, and he will save the humble in spirit.

20 Many are the afflictions of the just, but from them all the Lord will free them.

21 The Lord preserves all of their bones, not one of them shall be broken.

22 The death of a sinner is very harmful, and those who hate the just will fare badly.

23 The Lord will redeem the souls of his servants, and none of those who hope in him will fare badly.

Psalms 34

1 Of David himself. O Lord, judge those who harm me; assail those who attack me.

2 Take hold of weapons and a shield, and rise up in assistance to me.

3 Bring forth the spear, and close in on those who persecute me. Say to my soul, "I am your salvation."

4 Let them be confounded and in awe, who pursue my soul. Let them be turned back and be confounded, who think up evil against me.

5 May they become like dust before the face of the wind, and let the Angel of the Lord hem them in.

6 May their way become dark and slippery, and may the Angel of the Lord pursue them.

7 For, without cause, they have concealed their snare for me unto destruction. Over nothing, they have rebuked my soul.

8 Let the snare, of which he is ignorant, come upon him, and let the deception, which he has hidden, take hold of him: and may he fall into that very snare.

9 But my soul will exult in the Lord and delight over his salvation.

10 All my bones will say, "Lord, who is like you?" He rescues the needy from the hand of the stronger one, the indigent and the poor from those who plunder him.

11 Unfair witnesses have risen up, interrogating me about things of which I am ignorant.

12 They repaid me evil for good, to the deprivation of my soul.

13 But as for me, when they were harassing me, I was clothed with haircloth. I humbled my soul with fasting, and my prayer will become my sinews.

14 Like a neighbor, and like our brother, so did I please; like one mourning and contrite, so was I humbled.

15 And they have been joyful against me, and they joined together. Scourges have been gathered over me, and I was ignorant of it.

16 They have been scattered, yet they were unremorseful. They have tested me. They scoffed at me with scorn. They gnashed their teeth over me.

17 Lord, when will you look down upon me? Restore my soul from before their malice, my only one from before the lions.

18 I will confess to you in a great Church. I will praise you among a weighty people.

19 May those who are my unjust adversaries not be glad over me: those who have hated me without cause, and who nod agreement with their eyes.

20 For indeed, they spoke peacefully to me; and speaking with passion to the earth, they intended deceit.

21 And they opened their mouth wide over me. They said, "Well, well, our eyes have seen."

22 You have seen, O Lord, do not be silent. Lord, do not depart from me.

23 Rise up and be attentive to my judgment, to my cause, my God and my Lord.

24 Judge me according to your justice, O Lord, my God, and do not let them be glad over me.

25 Do not let them say in their hearts, "Well, well, to our soul." Neither let them say, "We have devoured him."

26 Let them blush and be in awe together, those who congratulate at my misfortunes. Let them be clothed with confusion and awe, who speak great things against me.

27 Let them exult and rejoice, who wish my justice, and let them ever say, "The Lord be magnified," who will the peace of his servant.

28 And so my tongue will express your justice: your praise all day long.

Psalms 35

1 Unto the end. To the servant of the Lord, David himself.

2 The unjust one has said within himself that he would commit offenses. There is no fear of God before his eyes.

3 For he has acted deceitfully in his sight, such that his iniquity will be found to be hatred.

4 The words of his mouth are iniquity and deceit. He is unwilling to understand, so that he may act well.

5 He has been considering iniquity on his bed. He has set himself on every way that is not good; moreover, he has not hated evil.

6 Lord, your mercy is in heaven, and your truth is even to the clouds.

7 Your justice is like the mountains of God. Your judgments are a great abyss. Men and beasts, you will save, O Lord.

8 How you have multiplied your mercy, O God! And so the sons of men will hope under the cover of your wings.

9 They will be inebriated with the fruitfulness of your house, and you will give them to drink from the torrent of your enjoyment.

10 For with you is the fountain of life; and within your light, we will see the light.

11 Extend your mercy before those who know you, and your justice to these, who are upright in heart.

12 May arrogant feet not approach me, and may the hand of the sinner not disturb me.

13 In that place, those who work iniquity have fallen. They have been expelled; they were not able to stand.

Psalms 36

1 A Psalm of David himself. Do not choose to imitate the malicious; neither should you envy those who work iniquity.

2 For they will quickly wither away like dry grass, and in like manner to kitchen herbs, they will soon droop.

3 Hope in the Lord and do good, and dwell in the land, and so you shall be pastured with its riches.

4 Delight in the Lord, and he will grant to you the petitions of your heart.

5 Reveal your way to the Lord, and hope in him, and he will accomplish it.

6 And he will bring forth your justice like the light, and your judgment like the midday.

7 Be subject to the Lord and pray to him. Do not choose to compete with him who prospers in his way, with the man who does injustice.

8 Cease from wrath and leave behind rage. Do not choose to imitate the malicious.

9 For those who are malicious will be exterminated. But those who remain with the Lord, these will inherit the land.

10 Yet still a little while, and the sinner will not be. And you will search his place and find nothing.

11 But the meek shall inherit the earth, and they will delight in the multitude of peace.

12 The sinner will observe the just, and he will gnash his teeth over him.

13 But the Lord will laugh at him: for he knows in advance that his day will come.

14 The sinners have drawn the sword, they have bent their bow, so as to cast down the poor and the needy, so as to massacre the upright of heart.

15 Let their sword enter into their own hearts, and let their bow be broken.

16 A little is better to the just than the many riches of sinners.

17 For the arms of sinners will be crushed, but the Lord confirms the just.

18 The Lord knows the days of the immaculate, and their inheritance will be in eternity.

19 They will not be confounded in an evil time; and in days of famine, they will be satisfied:

20 for sinners will perish. Truly, the adversaries of the Lord, soon after they have been honored and exalted, will fade away, in the same way that smoke fades away.

21 The sinner will lend and not release, but the just one shows compassion and donates.

22 For those who bless him will inherit the earth, but those who curse him will perish.

23 The steps of a man will be directed by the Lord, and he will choose his way.

24 When he falls, he will not be harmed, because the Lord places his hand under him.

25 I have been young, and now I am old; and I have not seen the just forsaken, nor his offspring seeking bread.

26 He shows compassion and lends, all day long, and his offspring will be in blessing.

27 Turn away from evil and do good, and dwell forever and ever.

28 For the Lord loves judgment, and he will not abandon his saints. They will be kept safe in eternity. The unjust will be punished, and the offspring of the impious will perish.

29 But the just will inherit the earth, and they will dwell upon it forever and ever.

30 The mouth of the just one will express wisdom, and his tongue will speak judgment.

31 The law of his God is in his heart, and his steps shall not be supplanted.

32 The sinner considers the just one and seeks to put him to death.

33 But the Lord will not abandon him into his hands, nor condemn him, when he will be judged.

34 Wait for the Lord, and keep to his way. And he will exalt you, so as to inherit the land that you may seize. When the sinners will have passed away, then you shall see.

35 I have seen the impious over-exalted, and lifted up like the cedars of Lebanon.

36 And I passed by, and behold, he was not. And I sought him, and his place was not found.

37 Keep to innocence, and gaze upon fairness: because there are allotments for the peaceful man.

38 But the unjust will be destroyed together: the allotments of the impious will pass away.

39 But the salvation of the just is from the Lord, and he is their protector in time of tribulation.

40 And the Lord will help them and free them. And he will rescue them from sinners and save them, because they have hoped in him.

Psalms 37

1 A Psalm of David, in commemoration of the Sabbath.

2 O Lord, do not rebuke me in your fury, nor chastise me in your wrath.

3 For your arrows have been driven into me, and your hand has been confirmed over me.

4 There is no health in my flesh before the face of your wrath. There is no peace for my bones before the face of my sins.

5 For my iniquities have walked over my head, and they have been like a heavy burden weighing upon me.

6 My sores have putrefied and been corrupted before the face of my foolishness.

7 I have become miserable, and I have been bent down, even to the end. I have walked with contrition all day long.

8 For my loins have been filled with illusions, and there is no health in my flesh.

9 I have been afflicted and greatly humbled. I bellowed from the groaning of my heart.

10 O Lord, all my desire is before you, and my groaning before you has not been hidden.

11 My heart has been disturbed. My strength has abandoned me, and the light of my eyes has abandoned me, and it is not with me.

12 My friends and my neighbors have drawn near and stood against me. And those who were next to me stood far apart. And those who sought my soul used violence.

13 And those who sought evil accusations against me were speaking emptiness. And they practiced deceitfulness all day long.

14 But, like someone deaf, I did not hear. And I was like someone mute, not opening his mouth.

15 And I became like a man who does not hear, and who has no reproofs in his mouth.

16 For in you, Lord, I have hoped. You will listen to me, O Lord my God.

17 For I said, "Lest at any time, my enemies might rejoice over me," and, "While my feet are being shaken, they have spoken great things against me."

18 For I have been prepared for scourges, and my sorrow is ever before me.

19 For I will announce my iniquity, and I will think about my sin.

20 But my enemies live, and they have been stronger than me. And those who have wrongfully hated me have been multiplied.

21 Those who render evil for good have dragged me down, because I followed goodness.

22 Do not forsake me, O Lord my God. Do not depart from me.

23 Be attentive to my help, O Lord, the God of my salvation.

Psalms 38

1 Unto the end. For Jeduthun himself. A Canticle of David.

2 I said, "I will keep to my ways, so that I will not offend with my tongue." I posted a guard at my mouth, when a sinner took up a position against me.

3 I was silenced and humbled, and I was quiet before good things, and my sorrow was renewed.

4 My heart grew hot within me, and, during my meditation, a fire would flare up.

5 I spoke with my tongue, "O Lord, make me know my end, and what the number of my days will be, so that I may know what is lacking to me."

6 Behold, you have made my days measurable, and, before you, my substance is as nothing. Yet truly, all things are vanity: every living man.

7 So then, truly man passes by like an image; even so, he is disquieted in vain. He stores up, and he knows not for whom he will gather these things.

8 And now, what is it that awaits me? Is it not the Lord? And my substance is with you.

9 Rescue me from all my iniquities. You have handed me over as reproach to the foolish.

10 I was silenced, and I did not open my mouth, because it was you who acted.

11 Remove your scourges from me.

12 I fall short at corrections from the strength of your hand. For you have chastised man for iniquity. And you have made his soul shrink away like a spider. Nevertheless, it is in vain that any man be disquieted.

13 O Lord, heed my prayer and my supplication. Pay attention to my tears. Do not be silent. For I am a newcomer with you, and a sojourner, just as all my fathers were.

14 Forgive me, so that I may be refreshed, before I will go forth and be no more.

Psalms 39

1 Unto the end. A Psalm of David himself.

2 I have waited expectantly for the Lord, and he was attentive to me.

3 And he heard my prayers and he led me out of the pit of misery and the quagmire. And he stationed my feet upon a rock, and he directed my steps.

4 And he sent a new canticle into my mouth, a song to our God. Many will see, and they will fear; and they will hope in the Lord.

5 Blessed is the man whose hope is in the name of the Lord, and who has no respect for vanities and absurd falsehoods.

6 You have accomplished your many wonders, O Lord my God, and there is no one similar to you in your thoughts. I have announced and I have spoken: they are multiplied beyond number.

7 Sacrifice and oblation, you did not want. But you have perfected ears for me. Holocaust and sin offering, you did not require.

8 Then I said, "Behold, I draw near." At the head of the book, it has been written of me:

9 that I should do your will. My God, I have willed it. And your law is in the midst of my heart.

10 I have announced your justice in a great Church: behold, I will not restrain my lips. O Lord, you have known it.

11 I have not concealed your justice within my heart. I have spoken your truth and your salvation. I have not concealed your mercy and your truth from a great assembly.

12 O Lord, do not take your tender mercies far from me. Your mercy and your truth ever sustain me.

13 For evils without number have surrounded me. My iniquities have taken hold of me, and I was not able to see. They have been multiplied beyond the hairs of my head. And my heart has forsaken me.

14 Be pleased, O Lord, to rescue me. Look down, O Lord, to help me.

15 Let them together be confounded and awed, who seek after my soul to steal it away. Let them be turned back and be in awe, who wish evils upon me.

16 Let them bear their confusion all at once, who say to me, "Well, well."

17 Let all who seek you exult and rejoice over you. And let those who love your salvation always say, "May the Lord be magnified."

18 But I am a beggar and poor. The Lord has been concerned about me. You are my helper and my protector. My God, do not delay.

Psalms 40

1 Unto the end. A Psalm of David himself.

2 Blessed is he who shows understanding toward the needy and the poor. The Lord will deliver him in the evil day.

3 May the Lord preserve him and give him life, and make him blessed upon the earth. And may he not hand him over to the will of his adversaries.

4 May the Lord bring him help on his bed of sorrow. In his infirmity, you have changed his entire covering.

5 I said, "O Lord, be merciful to me. Heal my soul, because I have sinned against you."

6 My enemies have spoken evils against me. When will he die and his name perish?

7 And when he came in to see me, he was speaking emptiness. His heart gathered iniquity to itself. He went outside, and he was speaking in the same way.

8 All my enemies were whispering against me. They were thinking up evils against me.

9 They established an unjust word against me. Will he that sleeps no longer rise again?

10 For even the man of my peace, in whom I hoped, who ate my bread, has greatly supplanted me.

11 But you, O Lord, have mercy on me, and raise me up again. And I will requite them.

12 By this, I knew that you preferred me: because my adversary will not rejoice over me.

13 But you have sustained me, because of my innocence, and you have confirmed me in your sight in eternity.

14 Blessed is the Lord God of Israel, for all generations and even forever. Amen. Amen.

Psalms 41

1 Unto the end. The understanding of the sons of Korah.

2 As the deer longs for fountains of water, so my soul longs for you, O God.

3 My soul has thirsted for the strong living God. When will I draw close and appear before the face of God?

4 My tears have been my bread, day and night. Meanwhile, it is said to me daily: "Where is your God?"

5 These things I have remembered; and my soul within me, I have poured out. For I will cross into the place of the wonderful tabernacle, all the way to the house of God, with a voice of exultation and confession, the sound of feasting.

6 Why are you sad, my soul? And why do you disquiet me? Hope in God, for I will still confess to him: the salvation of my countenance,

7 and my God. My soul has been troubled within myself. Because of this, I will remember you from the land of the Jordan and from Hermon, from the little mountain.

8 Abyss calls upon abyss, with the voice of your floodgate. All your heights and your waves have passed over me.

9 In the daylight, the Lord has ordered his mercy; and in the night, a canticle to him. With me is a prayer to the God of my life.

10 I will say to God, "You are my supporter. Why have you forgotten me? And why do I walk in mourning, while my adversary afflicts me?"

11 While my bones are being broken, my enemies, who trouble me, have reproached me. Meanwhile, they say to me every single day, "Where is your God?"

12 My soul, why are you saddened? And why do you disquiet me? Hope in God, for I will still confess to him: the salvation of my countenance and my God.

Psalms 43

1 Unto the end. To the sons of Korah, toward understanding.

2 We have heard, O God, with our own ears. Our fathers have announced to us the work that you wrought in their days and in the days of antiquity.

3 Your hand dispersed the Gentiles, and you transplanted them. You afflicted a people, and you expelled them.

4 For they did not take possession of the land by their sword, and their own arm did not save them. But your right hand and your arm, and the light of your countenance did so, because you were pleased with them.

5 You yourself are my king and my God, who commands the salvation of Jacob.

6 With you, we will brandish a horn before our enemies; and in your name, we will spurn those rising up against us.

7 For I will not hope in my bow, and my sword will not save me.

8 For you have saved us from those who afflict us, and you have bewildered those who hate us.

9 In God, we will give praise all day long; and in your name, we will confess forever.

10 But now, you have rejected and bewildered us, and you will not go forth with our armies, O God.

11 You have turned our back to our enemies, and those who hated us have plundered for themselves.

12 You have given us over like sheep for food. You have scattered us among the Gentiles.

13 You have sold your people without a price, and no great number was exchanged for them.

14 You have set us as a disgrace to our neighbors, a scoff and a derision to those who are around us.

15 You have set us as a parable among the Gentiles, a shaking of the head among the peoples.

16 All day long my shame is before me, and the confusion of my face has covered me,

17 before the voice of the reproacher and the commentator, before the face of the adversary and the pursuer.

18 All these things have come upon us, yet we have not forgotten you, and we have not acted unjustly in your covenant.

19 And our heart has not turned back. And you have not diverted our steps from your way.

20 For you humbled us in a place of affliction, and the shadow of death has covered us.

21 If we have forgotten the name of our God, and if we have extended our hands to a foreign god,

22 will not God find this out? For he knows the secrets of the heart. For, because of you, we are being killed all day long. We are considered as sheep for the slaughter.

23 Rise up. Why do you fall asleep, O Lord? Rise up, and do not reject us in the end.

24 Why do you turn your face away, and why do you forget our needfulness and our tribulation?

25 For our soul has been humbled into the dust. Our belly has been bound to the earth.

26 Rise up, O Lord. Help us and redeem us, because of your name.

Psalms 44

1 Unto the end. For those who will be changed. To the sons of Korah, toward understanding. A Canticle for the Beloved.

2 My heart has uttered a good word. I speak of my works to the king. My tongue is like the pen of a scribe who writes quickly.

3 You are a brilliant form before the sons of men. Grace has been poured freely into your lips. Because of this, God has blessed you in eternity.

4 Fasten your sword to your thigh, O most powerful one.

5 With your splendor and your excellence extended, proceed prosperously, and reign for the sake of truth and meekness and justice, and so will your right hand lead you wondrously.

6 Your arrows are sharp; the people will fall under you, with the hearts of the enemies of the king.

7 Your throne, O God, is forever and ever. The scepter of your kingdom is a scepter of true aim.

8 You have loved justice and hated iniquity. Because of this, God, your God, has anointed you, before your co-heirs, with the oil of gladness.

9 Myrrh and balsam and cinnamon perfume your garments, from the houses of ivory. From these, they have delighted you:

10 the daughters of kings in your honor. The queen assisted at your right hand, in clothing of gold, encircled with diversity.

11 Listen, daughter, and see, and incline your ear. And forget your people and your father's house.

12 And the king will desire your beauty. For he is the Lord your God, and they will adore him.

13 And the daughters of Tyre will entreat your countenance with gifts: all the rich men of the people.

14 All the glory of the daughter of its king is inside, in golden fringes,

15 clothed all around with diversities. After her, virgins will be led to the king. Her neighbors will be brought to you.

16 They will be brought with gladness and exultation. They will be led into the temple of the king.

17 For your fathers, sons have been born to you. You will establish them as leaders over all the earth.

18 They will remember your name always, for generation after generation. Because of this, people will confess to you in eternity, even forever and ever.

Psalms 45

1 Unto the end. To the sons of Korah, for confidants. A Psalm.

2 Our God is our refuge and strength, a helper in the tribulations that have greatly overwhelmed us.

3 Because of this, we will not be afraid when the earth will be turbulent and the mountains will be transferred into the heart of the sea.

4 They thundered, and the waters were stirred up among them; the mountains have been disturbed by his strength.

5 The frenzy of the river rejoices the city of God. The Most High has sanctified his tabernacle.

6 God is in its midst; it will not be shaken. God will assist it in the early morning.

7 The peoples have been disturbed, and the kingdoms have been bowed down. He uttered his voice: the earth has been moved.

8 The Lord of hosts is with us. The God of Jacob is our supporter.

9 Draw near and behold the works of the Lord: what portents he has set upon the earth,

10 carrying away wars even to the end of the earth. He will crush the bow and break the weapons, and he will burn the shield with fire.

11 Be empty, and see that I am God. I will be exalted among the peoples, and I will be exalted upon the earth.

12 The Lord of hosts is with us. The God of Jacob is our supporter.

Psalms 47

1 A Canticle Psalm. To the sons of Korah, on the second Sabbath.

2 The Lord is great and exceedingly praiseworthy, in the city of our God, on his holy mountain.

3 Mount Zion is being founded with the exultation of the whole earth, on the north side, the city of the great king.

4 In her houses, God will be known, since he will support her.

5 For behold, the kings of the earth have been gathered together; they have convened as one.

6 Such did they see, and they were astonished: they were disturbed, they were moved.

7 Trembling took hold of them. In that place, their pains were that of a woman in labor.

8 With a vehement spirit, you will crush the ships of Tarshish.

9 As we have heard, so we have seen, in the city of the Lord of hosts, in the city of our God. God has founded it in eternity.

10 We have received your mercy, O God, in the midst of your temple.

11 According to your name, O God, so does your praise reach to the ends of the earth. Your right hand is full of justice.

12 Let mount Zion rejoice, and let the daughters of Judah exult, because of your judgments, O Lord.

13 Encircle Zion and embrace her. Discourse in her towers.

14 Set your hearts on her virtue. And distribute her houses, so that you may discourse of it in another generation.

15 For this is God, our God, in eternity and forever and ever. He will rule us forever.

Psalms 48

1 Unto the end. A Psalm to the sons of Korah.

2 Hear these things, all nations. Pay attention, all inhabitants of the world:

3 whoever is earth-born, you sons of men, together as one, the rich and the poor.

4 My mouth will speak wisdom, and the meditation of my heart will speak prudence.

5 I will incline my ear to a parable. I will open my case with the psaltery.

6 Why should I fear in the evil day? The iniquity at my heel will surround me.

7 Those who trust in their own strength and who glory in the multitude of their riches,

8 no brother redeems, nor will man buy back. He will not give to God his appeasement,

9 nor the price for the redemption of his soul. And he will labor continuously,

10 and he will still live, until the end.

11 He will not see death, when he sees the wise dying: the foolish and the senseless will perish together. And they will leave their riches to strangers.

12 And their sepulchers will be their houses forever, their tabernacles from generation to generation. They have called their names in their own lands.

13 And man, when he was held in honor, did not understand. He has been compared to the senseless beasts, and he has become like them.

14 This way of theirs is a scandal to them. And afterwards, they will delight in their mouth.

15 They have been placed in Hell like sheep. Death will feed on them. And the just will have dominion over them in the morning. And their help will grow old in Hell for their glory.

16 Even so, truly God will redeem my soul from the hand of Hell, when he will receive me.

17 Do not be afraid, when a man will have been made rich, and when the glory of his house will have been multiplied.

18 For when he dies, he will take nothing away, and his glory will not descend with him.

19 For his soul will be blessed in his lifetime, and he will admit to you when you do good to him.

20 He will even enter with the progeny of his fathers, but, even in eternity, he will not see the light.

21 Man, when he was in honor, did not understand. He has been compared to the senseless beasts, and he has become like them.

Psalms 49

1 A Psalm of Asaph. The God of gods, the Lord has spoken, and he has called the earth, from the rising of the sun even to its setting,

2 from Zion, the brilliance of his beauty.

3 God will arrive manifestly. Our God also will not keep silence. A fire will flare up in his sight, and a mighty tempest will surround him.

4 He will call to heaven from above, and to the earth, to discern his people.

5 Gather his holy ones to him, you who order his covenant above sacrifices.

6 And the heavens will announce his justice. For God is the judge.

7 Listen, my people, and I will speak. Listen, Israel, and I will testify for you. I am God, your God.

8 I will not reprove you for your sacrifices. Moreover, your holocausts are ever in my sight.

9 I will not accept calves from your house, nor he-goats from your flocks.

10 For all the wild beasts of the forest are mine: the cattle on the hills and the oxen.

11 I know all the flying things of the air, and the beauty of the field is with me.

12 If I should be hungry, I would not tell you: for the whole world is mine, and all its plentitude.

13 Shall I gnaw on the flesh of bulls? Or would I drink the blood of goats?

14 Offer to God the sacrifice of praise, and pay your vows to the Most High.

15 And call upon me in the day of tribulation. I will rescue you, and you will honor me.

16 But to the sinner, God has said: Why do you discourse on my justices, and take up my covenant through your mouth?

17 Truly, you have hated discipline, and you have cast my sermons behind you.

18 If you saw a thief, you ran with him, and you have placed your portion with adulterers.

19 Your mouth has abounded with malice, and your tongue has concocted deceits.

20 Sitting, you spoke against your brother, and you set up a scandal against your mother's son.

21 These things you have done, and I was silent. You thought, unjustly, that I ought to be like you. But I will reprove you, and I will set myself against your face.

22 Understand these things, you who forget God; lest at any time, he might quickly take you away, and there would be no one to rescue you.

23 The sacrifice of praise will honor me. And in that place is the journey by which I will reveal to him the salvation of God.

Psalms 50

1 Unto the end. A Psalm of David,

2 when Nathan the prophet came to him, after he went to Bathsheba.

3 Be merciful to me, O God, according to your great mercy. And, according to the plentitude of your compassion, wipe out my iniquity.

4 Wash me once again from my iniquity, and cleanse me from my sin.

5 For I know my iniquity, and my sin is ever before me.

6 Against you only have I sinned, and I have done evil before your eyes. And so, you are justified in your words, and you will prevail when you give judgment.

7 For behold, I was conceived in iniquities, and in sinfulness did my mother conceive me.

8 For behold, you have loved truth. The obscure and hidden things of your wisdom, you have manifested to me.

9 You will sprinkle me with hyssop, and I will be cleansed. You will wash me, and I will be made whiter than snow.

10 In my hearing, you will grant gladness and rejoicing. And the bones that have been humbled will exult.

11 Turn your face away from my sins, and erase all my iniquities.

12 Create a clean heart in me, O God. And renew an upright spirit within my inmost being.

13 Do not cast me away from your face; and do not take your Holy Spirit from me.

14 Restore to me the joy of your salvation, and confirm me with an unsurpassed spirit.

15 I will teach the unjust your ways, and the impious will be converted to you.

16 Free me from blood, O God, the God of my salvation, and my tongue will extol your justice.

17 O Lord, you will open my lips, and my mouth will announce your praise.

18 For if you had desired sacrifice, I would certainly have given it, but with holocausts, you will not be delighted.

19 A crushed spirit is a sacrifice to God. A contrite and humbled heart, O God, you will not spurn.

20 Act kindly, Lord, in your good will toward Zion, so that the walls of Jerusalem may be built up.

21 Then you will accept the sacrifice of justice, oblations, and holocausts. Then they will lay calves upon your altar.

Psalms 51

1 Unto the end. The understanding of David.

2 When Doeg the Edomite came and reported to Saul, David went to the house of Ahimelech.

3 Why do you glory in malice, you who are powerful in iniquity?

4 All day long your tongue thinks up injustice. Like a sharp razor, you have wrought deceit.

5 You have loved malice above goodness, and iniquity more than speaking righteousness.

6 You have loved all precipitous words, you deceitful tongue.

7 Because of this, God will destroy you in the end. He will pull you up, and he will remove you from your tabernacle and your root from the land of the living.

8 The just will see and be afraid, and they will laugh over him, and say:

9 "Behold the man who did not set God as his helper. But he hoped in the multitude of his riches, and so he prevailed in his emptiness."

10 But I, like a fruitful olive tree in the house of God, have hoped in the mercy of God unto eternity, and forever and ever.

11 I will confess to you forever, because you have accomplished it. And I will wait on your name, for it is good in the sight of your saints.

Psalms 54

1 Unto the end. In verses, the understanding of David.

2 Listen to my prayer, O God, and despise not my supplication.

3 Be attentive to me, and heed me. I have been grieved in my training, and I have been disturbed

4 at the voice of the adversary and at the tribulation of the sinner. For they have diverted iniquities toward me, and they have been harassing me with rage.

5 My heart has become disturbed within me, and the dread of death has fallen over me.

6 Fear and trembling have overwhelmed me, and darkness has buried me.

7 And I said, "Who will give me wings like the dove, so that I may fly away and take rest?"

8 Behold, I have fled far away, and I linger in solitude.

9 I waited for him who saved me from a weak-minded spirit and from a tempest.

10 Cast them down, O Lord, and divide their tongues. For I have seen iniquity and contradiction in the city.

11 Day and night, iniquity will surround it upon its walls, and hardship is in its midst,

12 with injustice. And usury and deceit have not fallen away from its streets.

13 For if my enemy had spoken evil about me, certainly, I would have sustained it. And if he who hated me had been speaking great things against me, I would perhaps have hidden myself from him.

14 Truly, you are a man of one mind: my leader and my acquaintance,

15 who took sweet food together with me. In the house of God, we walked side-by-side.

16 Let death come upon them, and let them descend alive into Hellfire. For there is wickedness in their dwellings, in their midst.

17 But I have cried out to God, and the Lord will save me.

18 Evening and morning and midday, I will discourse and announce, and he will heed my voice.

19 He will redeem my soul in peace from those who draw near to me. For, among the many, they were with me.

20 God will hear, and He who is before time will humble them. For there is no change with them, and they have not feared God.

21 He has stretched forth his hand in retribution. They have contaminated his covenant.

22 They were divided by the wrath of his countenance, and his heart has drawn near. His words are smoother than oil, and they are arrows.

23 Cast your cares upon the Lord, and he will nurture you. He will not allow the just to be tossed about forever.

24 Truly, O God, you will lead them away into the well of death. Bloody and deceitful men will not divide their days in half. But I will hope in you, O Lord.

Psalms 55

1 Unto the end. For the people who have become far removed from the Sacred. Of David, with the inscription of a title, when the Philistines held him in Gath.

2 Have mercy on me, O God, because man has trampled over me. All day long, he has afflicted me by fighting against me.

3 My enemies have trampled over me all day long. For those who make war against me are many.

4 From the height of the day, I will be afraid. But truly, I will hope in you.

5 In God, I will praise my words. In God, I have put my trust. I will not fear what flesh can do to me.

6 All day long, they curse my words. All their intentions are for evil against me.

7 They will dwell and hide themselves. They will watch my heel, just as they waited for my soul;

8 because of this, nothing will save them. In your anger, you will crush the people.

9 O God, I have announced my life to you. You have placed my tears in your sight, and even in your promise.

10 Then my enemies will be turned back. On whatever day that I call upon you, behold, I know that you are my God.

11 In God, I will praise the word. In the Lord, I will praise his speech. In God, I have hoped. I will not fear what man can do to me.

12 My vows to you, O God, are in me. I will repay them. Praises be to you.

13 For you have rescued my soul from death and my feet from slipping, so that I may be pleasing in the sight of God, in the light of the living.

Psalms 56

1 Unto the end. May you not destroy. Of David, with the inscription of a title, when he fled from Saul into a cave.

2 Be merciful to me, O God, be merciful to me. For my soul trusts in you. And I will hope in the shadow of your wings, until iniquity passes away.

3 I will cry out to God Most High, to God who has been kind to me.

4 He sent from heaven and freed me. He has surrendered into disgrace those who trampled me. God has sent his mercy and his truth.

5 And he has rescued my soul from the midst of the young lions. I slept troubled. The sons of men: their teeth are weapons and arrows, and their tongue is a sharp sword.

6 Be exalted above the heavens, O God, and your glory above all the earth.

7 They prepared a snare for my feet, and they bowed down my soul. They dug a pit before my face, yet they have fallen into it.

8 My heart is prepared, O God, my heart is prepared. I will sing, and I will compose a psalm.

9 Rise up, my glory. Rise up, psaltery and harp. I will arise in early morning.

10 I will confess to you, O Lord, among the peoples. I will compose a psalm to you among the nations.

11 For your mercy has been magnified, even to the heavens, and your truth, even to the clouds.

12 Be exalted above the heavens, O God, and your glory above all the earth.

Psalms 57

1 Unto the end. May you not destroy. Of David, with the inscription of a title.

2 If, truly and certainly, you speak justice, then judge what is right, you sons of men.

3 For, even in your heart, you work iniquity. Your hands construct injustice on the earth.

4 Sinners have become foreigners from the womb; they have gone astray from conception. They have been speaking falsehoods.

5 Their fury is similar to that of a serpent; it is like a deaf asp, who even blocks her ears,

6 who will not listen to the voice of charmers, nor even to the enchanter who chants wisely.

7 God will crush their teeth within their own mouth. The Lord will break the molars of the lions.

8 They will come to nothing, like water flowing away. He has aimed his bow, while they are being weakened.

9 Like wax that flows, they will be carried away. Fire has fallen upon them, and they will not see the sun.

10 Before your thorns could know the brier, he consumes them alive, as if in rage.

11 The just one will rejoice when he sees vindication. He will wash his hands in the blood of the sinner.

12 And man will say, "If the just one is fruitful, then, truly, there is a God judging them on earth."

Psalms 58

1 Unto the end. May you not destroy. Of David, with the inscription of a title, when Saul sent and watched his house, in order to execute him.

2 Rescue me from my enemies, my God, and free me from those who rise up against me.

3 Rescue me from those who work iniquity, and save me from men of blood.

4 For behold, they have seized my soul. The strong have rushed upon me.

5 And it is neither my iniquity, nor my sin, O Lord. I have run and gone directly, without iniquity.

6 Rise up to meet me, and see: even you, O Lord, the God of hosts, the God of Israel. Reach out to visit all nations. Do not take pity on all those who work iniquity.

7 They will return toward evening, and they will suffer hunger like dogs, and they will wander around the city.

8 Behold, they will speak with their mouth, and a sword is in their lips: "For who has heard us?"

9 And you, O Lord, will laugh at them. You will lead all the Gentiles to nothing.

10 I will guard my strength toward you, for you are God, my supporter.

11 My God, his mercy will precede me.

12 God will oversee my enemies for me. Do not slay them, lest at times my people may forget them. Scatter them by your virtue. And depose them, O Lord, my protector,

13 by the offense of their mouth and by the speech of their lips. And may they be caught in their arrogance. And, for their cursing and lying, they will be made known

14 at the consummation, in the fury of the consummation, and so they will be no more. And they will know that God will rule over Jacob, even to the ends of the earth.

15 They will return toward evening, and they will suffer hunger like dogs, and they will wander around the city.

16 They will be dispersed in order to gnaw, and truly, when they will not have been satisfied, they will murmur.

17 But I will sing your strength, and I will extol your mercy, in the morning. For you have been my supporter and my refuge in the day of my tribulation.

18 To you, my helper, I will sing psalms. For you are God, my supporter. My God is my mercy.

Psalms 59

1 Unto the end. For those who will be changed, with the inscription of a title, of David himself, for instruction:

2 when he set fire to Mesopotamia of Syria and Sobal, and Joab turned back and struck Idumea, in the valley of the salt pits, twelve thousand men.

3 O God, you have rejected us, and you have ruined us. You became angry, and yet you have been merciful to us.

4 You have moved the earth, and you have disturbed it. Heal its breaches, for it has been moved.

5 You have revealed to your people difficulties. You have made us drink the wine of remorse.

6 You have given a warning sign to those who fear you, so that they may flee from before the face of the bow, so that your beloved may be delivered.

7 Save me with your right hand, and hear me.

8 God has spoken in his holy place: I will rejoice, and I will divide Shechem, and I will measure the steep valley of the tabernacles.

9 Gilead is mine, and Manasseh is mine. And Ephraim is the strength of my head. Judah is my king.

10 Moab is the cooking pot of my hope. Into Idumea, I will extend my shoe. To me, the foreigners have been made subject.

11 Who will lead me into the fortified city? Who will lead me all the way to Idumea?

12 Will not you, O God, who has rejected us? And will not you, O God, go out with our armies?

13 Grant us help from tribulation. For salvation from man is empty.

14 In God, we will act virtuously. And those who trouble us, he will lead to nothing.

Psalms 61

1 Unto the end. For Jeduthun. A Psalm of David.

2 Will my soul not be subject to God? For from him is my salvation.

3 Yes, he himself is my God and my salvation. He is my supporter; I will be moved no more.

4 How is it that you rush against a man? Every one of you puts to death, as if you were pulling down a ruined wall, leaning over and falling apart.

5 So, truly, they intended to reject my price. I ran in thirst. They blessed with their mouth and cursed with their heart.

6 Yet, truly, my soul will be subject to God. For from him is my patience.

7 For he is my God and my Savior. He is my helper; I will not be expelled.

8 In God is my salvation and my glory. He is the God of my help, and my hope is in God.

9 All peoples gathered together: trust in him. Pour out your hearts in his sight. God is our helper for eternity.

10 So, truly, the sons of men are untrustworthy. The sons of men are liars in the scales, so that, by emptiness, they may deceive among themselves.

11 Do not trust in iniquity, and do not desire plunder. If riches flow toward you, do not be willing to set your heart on them.

12 God has spoken once. I have heard two things: that power belongs to God,

13 and that mercy belongs to you, O Lord. For you will repay each one according to his works.

Psalms 62

1 A Psalm of David, when he was in the desert of Idumea.

2 O God, my God: to you, I keep vigil until first light. For you, my soul has thirsted, to you my body, in so many ways.

3 By a deserted land, both inaccessible and waterless, so I have appeared in the sanctuary before you, in order to behold your virtue and your glory.

4 For your mercy is better than life itself. It is you my lips will praise.

5 So will I bless you in my life, and I will lift up my hands in your name.

6 Let my soul be filled, as if with marrow and fatness; and my mouth will give praise with exultant lips.

7 When I have remembered you on my bed in the morning, I will meditate on you.

8 For you have been my helper. And I will exult under the cover of your wings.

9 My soul has clung close to you. Your right hand has supported me.

10 Truly, these ones have sought my soul in vain. They will enter into the lower parts of the earth.

11 They will be delivered into the hand of the sword. They will be the portions of foxes.

12 Truly, the king will rejoice in God: all those who swear by him will be praised, because the mouth of those who speak iniquity has been blocked.

Psalms 63

1 Unto the end. A Psalm of David.

2 Hear, O God, my prayer of supplication. Rescue my soul from the fear of the enemy.

3 You have protected me from the assembly of the malignant, from a multitude of workers of iniquity.

4 For they have sharpened their tongues like a sword; they have formed their bow into a bitter thing,

5 so that they may shoot arrows from hiding at the immaculate.

6 They will suddenly shoot arrows at him, and they will not be afraid. They are resolute in their wicked talk. They have discussed hidden snares. They have said, "Who will see them?"

7 They have been searching carefully for iniquities. Their exhaustive search has failed. Man will approach with a deep heart,

8 and God will be exalted. The arrows of the little ones have become their wounds,

9 and their tongues have been weakened against them. All those who saw them have been troubled;

10 and every man was afraid. And they announced the works of God, and they understood his acts.

11 The just will rejoice in the Lord, and they will hope in him. And all the upright of heart will be praised.

Psalms 64

1 Unto the end. A Psalm of David. A Canticle of Jeremiah and Ezekiel to the people of the captivity, when they began to go into exile.

2 O God, a hymn adorns you in Zion, and a vow will be repaid to you in Jerusalem.

3 Hear my prayer: all flesh will come to you.

4 Words of iniquity have prevailed over us. And you will pardon our impieties.

5 Blessed is he whom you have chosen and taken up. He will dwell in your courts. We will be filled with the good things of your house. Holy is your temple:

6 wonderful in equity. Hear us, O God our Savior, the hope of all the ends of the earth and of a sea far away.

7 You prepare the mountains in your virtue, wrapped with power.

8 You stir up the depths of the sea, the noise of its waves. The nations will be troubled,

9 and those who dwell at the limits will be afraid, before your signs. You will make the passing of morning and evening enjoyable.

10 You have visited the earth, and you have saturated it. You have enriched it in so many ways. The river of God has been filled with water. You have prepared their food. For thus is its preparation.

11 Drench its streams, multiply its fruits; it will spring up and rejoice in its showers.

12 You will bless the crown of the year with your kindness, and your fields will be filled with abundance.

13 The beauty of the desert will fatten, and the hills will be wrapped with exultation.

14 The rams of the sheep have been clothed, and the valleys will abound with grain. They will cry out; yes, they will even utter a hymn.

Psalms 65

1 Unto the end. A Canticle Psalm of the Resurrection. Shout joyfully to God, all the earth.

2 Proclaim a psalm to his name. Give glory to his praise.

3 Exclaim to God, "How terrible are your works, O Lord!" According to the fullness of your virtue, your enemies will speak lies about you.

4 Let all the earth adore you and sing psalms to you. May it sing a psalm to your name.

5 Draw near and see the works of God, who is terrible in his counsels over the sons of men.

6 He converts the sea into dry land. They will cross the river on foot. There, we will rejoice in him.

7 He rules by his virtue for eternity. His eyes gaze upon the nations. May those who exasperate him, not be exalted in themselves.

8 Bless our God, you Gentiles, and make the voice of his praise be heard.

9 He has set my soul toward life, and he has granted that my feet may not be shaken.

10 For you, O God, have tested us. You have examined us by fire, just as silver is examined.

11 You have led us into a snare. You have placed tribulations on our back.

12 You have set men over our heads. We have crossed through fire and water. And you have led us out to refreshment.

13 I will enter your house with holocausts. I will repay my vows to you,

14 which my lips discerned and my mouth spoke, in my tribulation.

15 I will offer to you holocausts full of marrow, with the burnt offerings of rams. I will offer to you bulls as well as goats.

16 Draw near and listen, all you who fear God, and I will describe to you how much he has done for my soul.

17 I cried out to him with my mouth, and I extolled him under my breath.

18 If I have seen iniquity in my heart, the Lord would not heed me.

19 And yet, God has heeded me and he has attended to the voice of my supplication.

20 Blessed is God, who has not removed my prayer, nor his mercy, from me.

Psalms 67

1 Unto the end. A Canticle Psalm of David himself.

2 May God rise up, and may his enemies be scattered, and may those who hate him flee from before his face.

3 Just as smoke vanishes, so may they vanish. Just as wax flows away before the face of fire, so may sinners pass away before the face of God.

4 And so, let the just feast, and let them exult in the sight of God and be delighted in gladness.

5 Sing to God, sing a psalm to his name. Make a path for him, who ascends over the west. The Lord is his name. Exult in his sight; they will be stirred up before his face,

6 the father of orphans and the judge of widows. God is in his holy place.

7 It is God who makes men dwell in a house under one custom. He leads out those who are strongly bound, and similarly, those who exasperate, who dwell in sepulchers.

8 O God, when you departed in the sight of your people, when you passed through the desert,

9 the earth was moved, for the heavens rained down before the face of the God of Sinai, before the face of the God of Israel.

10 You will set aside for your inheritance, O God, a willing rain. And though it was weak, truly, you have made it perfect.

11 Your animals will dwell in it. O God, in your sweetness, you have provided for the poor.

12 The Lord will give the word to evangelizers, along with great virtue.

13 The King of virtue is beloved among the beloved. And the beauty of the house will divide spoils.

14 If you take your rest in the midst of the clergy, you will be like a dove whose wings are covered with fine silver and edged with pale gold.

15 When heaven discerns kings to be over her, they will be whitened with the snows of Zalmon.

16 The mountain of God is a fat mountain, a dense mountain, a thick mountain.

17 So then, why are you distrustful of dense mountains? The mountain on which God is well pleased to dwell, even there, the Lord will dwell until the end.

18 The chariot of God is ten thousand fold: thousands rejoice. The Lord is with them in Sinai, in the holy place.

19 You have ascended on high; you have taken captivity captive. You have accepted gifts among men. For even those who do not believe dwell with the Lord God.

20 Blessed is the Lord, day after day. The God of our salvation will make our journey prosper for us.

21 Our God is the God who will bring about our salvation, and our Lord is the Lord who has brought an end to death.

22 So then, truly, God will break the heads of his enemies, the hairy skull of those who wander around in their offenses.

23 The Lord said: I will turn them away from Bashan, I will turn them into the depths of the sea,

24 so that your feet may be soaked in the blood of your enemies, so that the tongue of your dogs may be soaked with the same.

25 O God, they have seen your arrival, the arrival of my God, of my king who is in a holy place.

26 The leaders went ahead, united with the singers of psalms, in the midst of girls playing on timbrels.

27 In the churches, bless the Lord God from the fountains of Israel.

28 In that place, Benjamin is a youth in ecstasy of mind. The leaders of Judah are their governors: the leaders of Zebulun, the leaders of Naphtali.

29 Command by your virtue, O God. Confirm in this place, O God, what you have wrought in us.

30 Before your temple in Jerusalem, kings will offer gifts to you.

31 Rebuke the wild beasts of the reeds, a congregation of bulls with the cows of the people, for they seek to exclude those who have been tested like silver. Scatter the nations that are pleased by wars.

32 Ambassadors will come out of Egypt. Ethiopia will offer in advance her hands to God.

33 Sing to God, O kingdoms of the earth. Sing psalms to the Lord. Sing psalms to God.

34 He ascends, up to the heaven of the heavens, toward the east. Behold, he will utter his voice, the voice of virtue.

35 Give glory to God beyond Israel. His magnificence and his virtue is in the clouds.

36 God is wonderful in his saints. The God of Israel himself will give virtue and strength to his people. Blessed is God.

Psalms 68

1 Unto the end. For those who will be changed: of David.

2 Save me, O God, for the waters have entered, even to my soul.

3 I have become stuck in a deep quagmire, and there is no firm footing. I have arrived at the height of the sea, and a tempest has overwhelmed me.

4 I have endured hardships, while crying out. My jaws have become hoarse; my eyes have failed. Meanwhile, I hope in my God.

5 Those who hate me without cause have been multiplied beyond the hairs of my head. My enemies, who persecuted me unjustly, have been strengthened. Then I was required to pay for what I did not take.

6 O God, you know my foolishness, and my offenses have not been hidden from you.

7 Let those who wait for you, O Lord, the Lord of hosts, not be shamed in me. Let those who seek you, O God of Israel, not be confounded over me.

8 For because of you, I have endured reproach; confusion has covered my face.

9 I have become a stranger to my brothers and a sojourner to the sons of my mother.

10 For zeal for your house has consumed me, and the reproaches of those who reproached you have fallen upon me.

11 And I covered my soul with fasting, and it has become a reproach to me.

12 And I put on a haircloth as my garment, and I became a parable to them.

13 Those who sat at the gate spoke against me, and those who drank wine made me their song.

14 But as for me, truly, my prayer is to you, O Lord. This time has pleased you well, O God. In the multitude of your mercy, in the truth of your salvation, hear me.

15 Rescue me from the quagmire, so that I may not become trapped. Free me from those who hate me and from deep waters.

16 Do not allow the tempest of water to submerge me, nor the deep to absorb me. And do not allow the well to close in on me.

17 Hear me, O Lord, for your mercy is kind. Look upon me, according to the fullness of your compassion.

18 And do not turn your face away from your servant, for I am in trouble: heed me quickly.

19 Attend to my soul, and free it. Rescue me, because of my enemies.

20 You know my reproach, and my confusion, and my reverence.

21 All those who trouble me are in your sight; my heart has anticipated reproach and misery. And I sought for one who might grieve together with me, but there was no one, and for one who might console me, and I found no one.

22 And they gave me gall for my food. And in my thirst, they gave me vinegar to drink.

23 Let their table be a snare before them, and a retribution, and a scandal.

24 Let their eyes be darkened, so that they may not see, and may their back always be crooked.

25 Pour out your indignation upon them, and may the fury of your anger take hold of them.

26 May their dwelling place be deserted, and may there be no one who dwells in their tabernacles.

27 For they persecuted whomever you struck. And they have added to the grief of my wounds.

28 Assign an iniquity upon their iniquity, and may they not enter into your justice.

29 Delete them from the Book of the Living, and let them not be written down with the just.

30 I am poor and sorrowful, but your salvation, O God, has taken me up.

31 I will praise the name of God with a canticle, and I will magnify him with praise.

32 And it will please God more than a new calf producing horns and hoofs.

33 Let the poor see and rejoice. Seek God, and your soul will live.

34 For the Lord has heard the poor, and he has not despised his prisoners.

35 Let the heavens and the earth praise him: the sea, and everything that crawls in it.

36 For God will save Zion, and the cities of Judah will be built up. And they will dwell there, and they will acquire it by inheritance.

37 And the offspring of his servants will possess it; and those who love his name will dwell in it.

Psalms 70

1 A Psalm of David. Of the sons of Jonadab and the former captives. In you, O Lord, I have hoped; do not let me be brought to ruin forever.

2 Free me by your justice, and rescue me. Incline your ear to me, and save me.

3 Be a God of protection and a place of strength for me, so that you may accomplish my salvation. For you are my firmament and my refuge.

4 Rescue me, O my God, from the hand of the sinner, and from the hand of the unjust and those who act against the law.

5 For you, O Lord, are my patience: my hope from my youth, O Lord.

6 In you, I have been confirmed from conception. From my mother's womb, you are my protector. In you, I will sing forever.

7 I have become to many as if I were a portent, but you are a strong helper.

8 Let my mouth be filled with praise, so that I may sing your glory, your greatness all day long.

9 Do not cast me off in the time of old age. Do not abandon me when my strength will fail.

10 For my enemies have spoken against me. And those who watched for my soul have taken counsel as one,

11 saying: "God has abandoned him. Pursue and overtake him. For there is no one to rescue him."

12 O God, do not be far from me. O my God, provide for my assistance.

13 May they be confounded, and may they fail, who drag down my soul. Let them be covered with confusion and shame, who seek evils for me.

14 But I will always have hope. And I will add more to all your praise.

15 My mouth will announce your justice, your salvation all day long. For I have not known letters.

16 I will enter into the powers of the Lord. I will be mindful of your justice alone, O Lord.

17 You have taught me from my youth, O God. And so I will declare your wonders continuously,

18 even in old age and with grey hairs. Do not abandon me, O God, while I announce your arm to every future generation: your power

19 and your justice, O God, even to the highest great things that you have done. O God, who is like you?

20 How great is the tribulation that you have revealed to me: very great and evil. And so, turning back, you have brought me to life, and you have led me back again from the abyss of the earth.

21 You have multiplied your magnificence. And so, turning back to me, you have consoled me.

22 Therefore, I will confess your truth to you, with the instruments of the Psalter. O God, I will sing psalms to you with stringed instruments, O Holy One of Israel.

23 My lips will exult, when I sing to you, and also my soul, which you have redeemed.

24 And even my tongue will meditate on your justice all day long, when those who seek evils for me have been confounded and set in awe.

Psalms 71

1 A Psalm according to Solomon.

2 Give your judgment, O God, to the king, and your justice to the king's son, to judge your people with justice and your poor with judgment.

3 Let the mountains take up peace for the people, and the hills, justice.

4 He will judge the poor of the people, and he will bring salvation to the sons of the poor. And he will humble the false accuser.

5 And he will remain, with the sun and before the moon, from generation to generation.

6 He will descend like rain upon fleece, and like showers showering upon the earth.

7 In his days, justice will rise like the sun, with abundance of peace, until the moon is taken away.

8 And he will rule from sea to sea and from the river to the limits of the whole world.

9 In his sight, the Ethiopians will fall prostrate, and his enemies will lick the ground.

10 The kings of Tarshish and the islands will offer gifts. The kings of Arabia and of Seba will bring gifts.

11 And all the kings of the earth shall adore him. All nations will serve him.

12 For he will free the poor from the powerful, and the poor one who has no helper.

13 He will spare the poor and the indigent, and he will bring salvation to the souls of the poor.

14 He will redeem their souls from usuries and from iniquity, and their names shall be honorable in his sight.

15 And he will live, and to him will be given from the gold of Arabia, and by him they will always adore. They will bless him all day long.

16 And there will be a firmament on earth, at the summits of mountains: its fruits will be extolled above Lebanon, and those of the city will flourish like the grass of the earth.

17 May his name be blessed forever; may his name remain before the sun. And all the tribes of the earth will be blessed in him. All nations will magnify him.

18 Blessed is the Lord, God of Israel, who alone does wondrous things.

19 And blessed is the name of his majesty in eternity. And all the earth will be filled with his majesty. Amen. Amen.

20 The praises of David, the son of Jesse, have reached an end.

Psalms 72

1 A Psalm of Asaph. How good is God to Israel, to those who are upright in heart.

2 But my feet were nearly moved; my steps had nearly slipped.

3 For I was zealous over the iniquitous, seeing the peacefulness of sinners.

4 For they have no respect for their death, nor do they have support in their wounds.

5 They are not with the hardships of men, nor will they be scourged with men.

6 Therefore, arrogance has held on to them. They have been covered with their iniquity and impiety.

7 Their iniquity has proceeded, as if from fat. They have parted from the affection of the heart.

8 They have thought and spoken wickedness. They have spoken iniquity in high places.

9 They have set their mouth against heaven, and their tongue has traversed the earth.

10 Therefore, my people will be converted here, and fullness of days will be found in them.

11 And they said, "How would God know?" and, "Isn't there knowledge in high places?"

12 Behold, these are sinners, and, abounding in this age, they have obtained riches.

13 And I said: So then, it is without purpose that I have justified my heart and washed my hands among the innocent.

14 And I have been scourged all day long, and I have received my chastisement in the mornings.

15 If I were to say that I would explain this: Behold, I would condemn this nation of your sons.

16 I considered, so that I might know this. It is a hardship before me,

17 until I may enter into the Sanctuary of God, and understand it to its last part.

18 So, because of deceitfulness, truly, you have placed it before them. While they were being lifted up, you were casting them down.

19 How have they been brought to desolation? They have suddenly failed. They have perished because of their iniquity.

20 As a dream is to those who awaken, O Lord, so will you reduce their image to nothing in your city.

21 For my heart has been inflamed, and my temperament has been changed.

22 And so, I have been reduced to nothing, and I did not know it.

23 I have become like a beast of burden to you, and I am always with you.

24 You have held my right hand. And in your will, you have conducted me, and with your glory, you have taken me up.

25 For what is there for me in heaven? And what do I wish for on earth before you?

26 My body has failed, and my heart: O God of my heart, and God my portion, into eternity.

27 For behold, those who put themselves far from you will perish. You have perished all those who fornicate away from you.

28 But it is good for me to adhere to God, to put my hope in the Lord God, so that I may announce all your prophecies, at the gates of the daughter of Zion.

Psalms 73

1 The understanding of Asaph. O God, why have you rejected us to the end. Why has your fury become enraged over the sheep of your pasture?

2 Be mindful of your congregation, which you have possessed from the beginning. You redeemed the scepter of your inheritance, mount Zion, in which you have dwelt.

3 Lift up your hands against their arrogance in the end. How great the malice of the enemy has been in the sanctuary!

4 And those who hate you have been glorified, in the midst of your solemnity. They have set up their own signs as a proof,

5 as if it had been issued from on high; yet they did not understand. As in a forest of chopped wood,

6 they have cut down the entrances themselves. With axe and hatchet, they have brought it down.

7 They have set fire to your Sanctuary. They have polluted the tabernacle of your name on earth.

8 They have said in their heart, the whole group of them together: "Let us cause all the feast days of God to cease from the land.

9 We have not seen our proof; there is now no prophet. And he will no longer know us."

10 How long, O God, will the enemy place blame? Is the adversary to provoke your name until the end?

11 Why do you turn your hand away, even your right hand, from the midst of your sinews, until the end?

12 But God is our king before all ages. He has wrought salvation in the midst of the earth.

13 In your virtue, you confirmed the sea. You crushed the heads of the serpents in the waters.

14 You have broken the heads of the serpent. You have given him as food for the people of the Ethiopians.

15 You have disrupted the fountains and the torrents. You have dried up the rivers of Ethan.

16 Yours is the day, and yours is the night. You have made the morning light and the sun.

17 You have made all the limits of the earth. The summer and the spring were formed by you.

18 Be mindful of this: the enemy placed blame against the Lord, and a foolish people has incited against your name.

19 Do not hand over to beasts the souls that confess to you; and do not forget the souls of your poor until the end.

20 Consider your covenant. For those who have been darkened upon the earth have been filled by the iniquity of the houses.

21 Do not allow the humble to be turned away in confusion. The poor and the needy will praise your name.

22 Rise up, O God, judge your own case. Call to mind the accusations against you, which are made by the foolish all day long.

23 Do not forget the voices of your adversaries. The arrogance of those who hate you rises up continually.

Psalms 75

1 Unto the end. With Praises. A Psalm of Asaph. A Canticle to the Assyrians.

2 In Judea, God is known. In Israel, his name is great.

3 And his place has been formed with peace. And his dwelling place is in Zion.

4 In that place, he has broken the powers of the bows, the shield, the sword, and the battle.

5 You illuminate wondrously from the mountains of eternity.

6 All the foolish of heart have been disturbed. They have slept their sleep, and all the men of riches have found nothing in their hands.

7 At your rebuke, O God of Jacob, those who were mounted on horseback have fallen asleep.

8 You are terrible, and so, who can withstand you? From thence is your wrath.

9 You have caused judgment to be heard from heaven. The earth trembled and was quieted,

10 when God rose up in judgment in order to bring salvation to all the meek of the earth.

11 For the thinking of man will confess to you, and the legacy of his thinking will keep a feast day to you.

12 Make vows and pay them to the Lord, your God. All you who surround him bring gifts: to him who is terrible,

13 even to him who takes away the spirit of leaders, to him who is terrible with the kings of the earth.

Psalms 76

1 Unto the end. For Jeduthun. A Psalm of Asaph.

2 I cried out to the Lord with my voice, to God with my voice, and he attended to me.

3 In the days of my tribulation, I sought God, with my hands opposite him in the night, and I was not deceived. My soul refused to be consoled.

4 I was mindful of God, and I was delighted, and I was distressed, and my spirit fell away.

5 My eyes anticipated the vigils. I was disturbed, and I did not speak.

6 I considered the days of antiquity, and I held the years of eternity in my mind.

7 And I meditated in the night with my heart, and I was distressed, and I examined my spirit.

8 So then, will God reject for eternity? Will he not continue to allow himself to show favor?

9 Or, will he cut off his mercy in the end, from generation to generation?

10 And would God ever forget to be merciful? Or, would he, in his wrath, restrict his mercies?

11 And I said, "Now I have begun. This change is from the right hand of the Most High."

12 I was mindful of the works of the Lord. For I will be mindful from the beginning of your wonders,

13 and I will meditate on all your works. And I will take part in your intentions.

14 Your way, O God, is in what is holy. Which God is great like our God?

15 You are the God who performs miracles. You have made your virtue known among the peoples.

16 With your arm, you have redeemed your people, the sons of Jacob and of Joseph.

17 The waters saw you, O God, the waters saw you, and they were afraid, and the depths were stirred up.

18 Great was the sound of the waters. The clouds uttered a voice. For your arrows also pass by.

19 The voice of your thunder is like a wheel. Your flashes have illuminated the whole world. The earth has quaked and trembled.

20 Your way is through the sea, and your paths are through many waters. And your traces will not be known.

21 You have conducted your people like sheep, by the hand of Moses and Aaron.

Psalms 77

1 The understanding of Asaph. O my people, attend to my law. Incline your ears to the words of my mouth.

2 I will open my mouth in parables. I will speak about concepts that are from the beginning.

3 We have heard and known such great things, as our fathers have described to us.

4 These things have not been hidden from their sons in any generation: declaring the praises of the Lord, and his virtues, and the wonders that he has done.

5 And he has received testimony with Jacob, and he has set a law within Israel. Such great things, he has commanded our fathers, so as to make these things known to their sons,

6 so that another generation might know them, and so that the sons, who will be born and who will grow up, shall describe them to their sons.

7 So then, may they put their hope in God, and may they not forget the works of God, and may they seek his commandments.

8 May they not become like their fathers, a perverse and exasperating generation: a generation that does not straighten their heart and whose spirit is not trustworthy with God.

9 The sons of Ephraim, who bend and shoot the bow, have been turned back in the day of battle.

10 They have not kept the covenant of God. And they were not willing to walk in his law.

11 And they have been forgetful of his benefits, and of his miracle, which he revealed to them.

12 He performed miracles in the sight of their fathers, in the land of Egypt, in the field of Tanis.

13 He broke the sea and he led them through. And he stationed the waters, as if in a vessel.

14 And he led them with a cloud by day, and with illumination by fire throughout the night.

15 He broke through the rock in the wasteland, and he gave them to drink, as if from the great abyss.

16 He brought forth water from the rock, and he conducted the waters, as if they were rivers.

17 And yet, they continued to sin against him. In a waterless place, they provoked the Most High with resentment.

18 And they tempted God in their hearts, by asking for food according to their desires.

19 And they spoke badly about God. They said, "Would God be able to prepare a table in the desert?

20 He struck the rock, and so waters flowed and the torrents flooded, but would even he be able to provide bread, or provide a table, for his people?"

21 Therefore, the Lord heard, and he was dismayed, and a fire was kindled within Jacob, and an anger ascended into Israel.

22 For they neither put their trust in God, nor did they hope in his salvation.

23 And he commanded the clouds from above, and he opened the doors of heaven.

24 And he rained down manna upon them to eat, and he gave them the bread of heaven.

25 Man ate the bread of Angels. He sent them provisions in abundance.

26 He transferred the south wind from heaven, and, in his virtue, he brought in the Southwest wind.

27 And he rained down flesh upon them, as if it were dust, and feathered birds, as if they were the sand of the sea.

28 And they fell down in the midst of their camp, encircling their tabernacles.

29 And they ate until they were greatly satisfied, and he brought to them according to their desires.

30 They were not cheated out of what they wanted. Their food was still in their mouth,

31 and then the wrath of God came upon them. And he slew the fat ones among them, and he impeded the elect of Israel.

32 In all these things, they continued to sin, and they were not trustworthy with his miracles.

33 And their days faded away into vanity, and their years with haste.

34 When he slew them, then they sought him. And they returned, and they drew near to him in the early morning.

35 And they were mindful that God is their helper and that the Most High God is their redeemer.

36 And they chose him with their mouth, and then they lied to him with their tongue.

37 For their heart was not upright with him, nor have they been living faithfully in his covenant.

38 Yet he is merciful, and he will pardon their sins. And he will not destroy them. And he has abundantly turned aside his own wrath. And he did not enflame his wrath entirely.

39 And he remembered that they are flesh: with a spirit that goes forth and does not return.

40 How often did they provoke him in the desert and stir him to wrath in a waterless place?

41 And they turned back and tempted God, and they exasperated the Holy One of Israel.

42 They did not remember his hand, in the day that he redeemed them from the hand of the one troubling them.

43 Thus, he positioned his signs in Egypt and his wonders in the field of Tanis.

44 And he turned their rivers into blood, along with their rain showers, so that they could not drink.

45 He sent among them the common fly, and it devoured them, and the frog, and it scattered them.

46 And he gave up their fruits to mold and their labors to the locust.

47 And he slew their vineyards with hail and their mulberry trees with severe frost.

48 And he delivered their cattle to the hail and their possessions to fire.

49 And he sent the wrath of his indignation among them: indignation and wrath and tribulation, sent forth by evil angels.

50 He made way for the path of his anger. He did not spare their souls from death. And he enclosed their beasts of burden in death.

51 And he struck all the first-born in the land of Egypt: the first-fruits of all their labor in the tabernacles of Ham.

52 And he took away his own people like sheep, and he led them through the wilderness like a flock.

53 And he led them out in hope, and they did not fear. And the sea covered their enemies.

54 And he led them to the mountain of his sanctification: the mountain that his right hand had acquired. And he cast out the Gentiles before their face. And he divided their land by lot to them, with a line of distribution.

55 And he caused the tribes of Israel to dwell in their tabernacles.

56 Yet they tempted and aggravated God Most High, and they did not keep his testaments.

57 And they turned themselves aside, and they did not serve the covenant. In the same manner as their fathers, they were turned backwards, like a crooked bow.

58 They impelled him to anger on their hills, and they provoked him to rivalry with their graven images.

59 God listened, and he spurned them, and he reduced Israel greatly, almost to nothing.

60 And he rejected the tabernacle of Shiloh, his tabernacle where he had dwelt among men.

61 And he delivered their virtue into captivity, and their beauty into the hands of the enemy.

62 And he enclosed his people with the sword, and he spurned his inheritance.

63 Fire consumed their young men, and their virgins were not lamented.

64 Their priests fell by the sword, and their widows did not weep.

65 And the Lord was awaked, as if out of sleep, and like a powerful man impaired by wine.

66 And he struck his enemies on the back. He gave them over to everlasting disgrace.

67 And he rejected the tabernacle of Joseph, and he did not choose the tribe of Ephraim.

68 But he chose the tribe of Judah: mount Zion, which he loved.

69 And he built up his sanctuary, like a single-horned beast, in the land that he founded for all ages.

70 And he chose his servant David, and he took him from the flocks of the sheep: he received him from following the ewes with their young,

71 in order to pasture Jacob his servant and Israel his inheritance.

72 And he fed them with the innocence of his heart. And he led them with the understanding of his hands.

Psalms 78

1 A Psalm of Asaph. O God, the Gentiles have entered into your inheritance; they have polluted your holy temple. They have set Jerusalem as a place to tend fruit trees.

2 They have placed the dead bodies of your servants as food for the birds of the sky, the flesh of your saints for the beasts of the earth.

3 They have poured out their blood like water all around Jerusalem, and there was no one who would bury them.

4 We have become a disgrace to our neighbors, an object of ridicule and mockery to those who are around us.

5 How long, O Lord? Will you be angry until the end? Will your zeal be kindled like a fire?

6 Pour out your wrath among the Gentiles, who have not known you, and upon the kingdoms that have not invoked your name.

7 For they have devoured Jacob, and they have desolated his place.

8 Do not remember our iniquities of the past. May your mercies quickly intercept us, for we have become exceedingly poor.

9 Help us, O God, our Savior. And free us, Lord, for the glory of your name. And forgive us our sins for the sake of your name.

10 Let them not say among the Gentiles, "Where is their God?" And may your name become known among the nations before our eyes. For the retribution of your servants' blood, which has been poured out:

11 may the groans of the shackled enter before you. According to the greatness of your arm, take possession of the sons of those who have been killed.

12 And repay our neighbors sevenfold within their sinews. It is the reproach of the same ones who brought reproach against you, O Lord.

13 But we are your people and the sheep of your pasture: we will give thanks to you in all ages. From generation to generation, we will announce your praise.

Psalms 79

1 Unto the end. For those who will be changed. The testimony of Asaph. A Psalm.

2 The One who reigns over Israel: Be attentive. For you lead Joseph like a sheep. The One who sits upon the cherubim: Shine forth

3 in the presence of Ephraim, Benjamin, and Manasseh. Awaken your power and draw near, so as to accomplish our salvation.

4 Convert us, O God. And reveal your face, and we will be saved.

5 O Lord, God of hosts, how long will you be angry over the prayer of your servant?

6 How long will you feed us the bread of tears, and give us to drink a full measure of tears?

7 You have set us as a contradiction to our neighbors. And our enemies have ridiculed us.

8 O God of hosts, convert us. And reveal your face, and we will be saved.

9 You have transferred a vineyard from Egypt. You have cast out the Gentiles, and planted it.

10 You were the leader of the journey in its sight. You planted its roots, and it filled the earth.

11 Its shadow covered the hills, and its branches covered the cedars of God.

12 It extended its new branches even to the sea, and its new seedlings even to the river.

13 So then, why have you destroyed its walls, so that all those who pass by the way gather its grapes?

14 The wild boar of the forest has trampled it, and a single wild beast has laid waste to it.

15 Turn back, O God of hosts. Look down from heaven, and see, and visit this vineyard;

16 and complete what your right hand has planted, and look upon the son of man, whom you have confirmed for yourself.

17 Whatever has been set on fire and dug under will perish at the rebuke of your countenance.

18 Let your hand be over the man on your right, and over the son of man, whom you have confirmed for yourself.

19 For we do not depart from you, and you will revive us. And we will invoke your name.

20 O Lord, God of hosts, convert us. And reveal your face, and we will be saved.

Psalms 80

1 Unto the end. For the wine and oil presses. A Psalm of Asaph himself.

2 Exult before God our helper. Sing joyfully to the God of Jacob.

3 Take up a psalm, and bring forth the timbrel: a pleasing Psalter with stringed instruments.

4 Sound the trumpet at the new moon, on the noteworthy day of your solemnity,

5 for it is a precept in Israel and a judgment for the God of Jacob.

6 He set it as a testimony with Joseph, when he went out of the land of Egypt. He heard a tongue that he did not know.

7 He turned the burdens away from his back. His hands had been a slave to baskets.

8 You called upon me in tribulation, and I freed you. I heard you within the hidden tempest. I tested you with waters of contradiction.

9 My people, listen and I will call you to testify. If, O Israel, you will pay heed to me,

10 then there will be no new god among you, nor will you adore a foreign god.

11 For I am the Lord your God, who led you out of the land of Egypt. Widen your mouth, and I will fill it.

12 But my people did not hear my voice, and Israel was not attentive to me.

13 And so, I sent them away, according to the desires of their heart. They will go forth according to their own inventions.

14 If my people had heard me, if Israel had walked in my ways,

15 I would have humbled their enemies, as if it were nothing, and I would have sent my hand upon those who troubled them.

16 The enemies of the Lord have lied to him, and their time will come, in every age.

17 And he fed them from the fat of the grain, and he saturated them with honey from the rock.

Psalms 82

1 A Canticle Psalm of Asaph.

2 O God, who will ever be like you? Do not be silent, and do not be unmoved, O God.

3 For behold, your enemies have sounded off, and those who hate you have carried out a head.

4 They have acted with malice in counsel over your people, and they have plotted against your holy ones.

5 They have said, "Come, let us scatter them from the nations and not allow the name of Israel to be remembered any longer."

6 For they plotted unanimously. Joined together against you, they ordained a covenant:

7 the tabernacle of Edomites and Ishmaelites, and Moab and the Hagarites,

8 and Gebal, and Ammon, and Amalek, the foreigners among the inhabitants of Tyre.

9 For even Assur comes with them. They have become the helpers of the sons of Lot.

10 Do to them as you did to Midian and Sisera, just as to Jabin at the torrent of Kishon.

11 They perished at Endor, and they became like the dung of the earth.

12 Set their leaders to be like Oreb and Zeeb, and Zebah and Zalmunna: all their leaders

13 who said, "Let us possess the Sanctuary of God for an inheritance."

14 My God, set them like a wheel, and like stubble before the face of the wind.

15 Set them like a fire burning up the forest, and like a flame burning up the mountains.

16 So will you pursue them in your tempest, and disturb them in your wrath.

17 Fill their faces with shame, and they will seek your name, O Lord.

18 Let them be ashamed and troubled, from age to age, and let them be confounded and perish.

19 And let them know that the Lord is your name. You alone are the Most High in all the earth.

Psalms 83

1 Unto the end. For the wine and oil presses. A Psalm to the sons of Korah.

2 How beloved are your tabernacles, O Lord of hosts!

3 My soul longs and faints for the courts of the Lord. My heart and my flesh have exulted in the living God.

4 For even the sparrow has found a home for himself, and the turtle-dove a nest for herself, where she may lay her young: your altars, O Lord of hosts, my king and my God.

5 Blessed are those who dwell in your house, O Lord. They will praise you from age to age.

6 Blessed is the man whose help is from you. In his heart, he is disposed to ascend

7 from the valley of tears, from the place which he has determined.

8 For even the lawgiver will provide a blessing; they will go from virtue to virtue. The God of gods will be seen in Zion.

9 O Lord, God of hosts, hear my prayer. Pay attention, O God of Jacob.

10 O God, gaze upon our protector, and look upon the face of your Christ.

11 For one day in your courts is better than thousands elsewhere. I have chosen to be lowly in the house of my God, rather than to dwell in the tabernacles of sinners.

12 For God loves mercy and truth. The Lord will give grace and glory.

13 He will not withhold good things from those who walk in innocence. O Lord of hosts, blessed is the man who hopes in you.

Psalms 84

1 Unto the end. A Psalm to the sons of Korah.

2 O Lord, you have blessed your land. You have turned aside the captivity of Jacob.

3 You have released the iniquity of your people. You have covered all their sins.

4 You have mitigated all your wrath. You have turned aside from the wrath of your indignation.

5 Convert us, O God, our Savior, and turn your anger away from us.

6 Will you be angry with us forever? And will you extend your wrath from generation to generation?

7 O God, you will turn back and revive us. And your people will rejoice in you.

8 O Lord, reveal to us your mercy, and grant to us your salvation.

9 I will listen to what the Lord God may be saying to me. For he will speak peace to his people, and to his saints, and to those who are being converted to the heart.

10 So then, truly his salvation is near to those who fear him, so that glory may inhabit our land.

11 Mercy and truth have met each other. Justice and peace have kissed.

12 Truth has risen from the earth, and justice has gazed down from heaven.

13 For so will the Lord give goodness, and our earth will give her fruit.

14 Justice will walk before him, and he will set his steps upon the way.

Psalms 85

1 A Prayer of David himself. Incline your ear, O Lord, and hear me. For I am needy and poor.

2 Preserve my soul, for I am holy. My God, bring salvation to your servant who hopes in you.

3 O Lord, be merciful to me, for I have cried out to you all day long.

4 Give joy to the soul of your servant, for I have lifted up my soul to you, Lord.

5 For you are sweet and mild, Lord, and plentiful in mercy to all who call upon you.

6 Pay attention, Lord, to my prayer, and attend to the voice of my supplication.

7 In the day of my tribulation, I cried out to you, because you heeded me.

8 There is no one like you among the gods, O Lord, and there is no one like you in your works.

9 All the nations, which you have made, will draw near and adore in your presence, O Lord. And they will glorify your name.

10 For you are great, and you perform wonders. You alone are God.

11 Lead me, O Lord, in your way, and I will walk in your truth. May my heart rejoice, so that it will fear your name.

12 I will confess to you, O Lord my God, with my whole heart. And I will glorify your name in eternity.

13 For your mercy toward me is great, and you have rescued my soul from the lower part of Hell.

14 O God, the iniquitous have risen up against me, and the synagogue of the powerful have sought my soul, and they have not placed you in their sight.

15 And you, Lord God, are compassionate and merciful, being patient and full of mercy and truthful.

16 Look down upon me and have mercy on me. Grant your authority to your servant, and bring salvation to the son of your handmaid.

17 Make me a sign of what is good, so that those who hate me, may look and be confounded. For you, O Lord, have helped me and consoled me.

Psalms 87

1 A Canticle Psalm to the sons of Korah. Unto the end. For Mahalath, to answer the understanding of Heman the Ezrahite.

2 O Lord, God of my salvation: I have cried out, day and night, in your presence.

3 Let my prayer enter in your sight. Incline your ear to my petition.

4 For my soul has been filled with evils, and my life has drawn near to Hell.

5 I am considered to be among those who will descend into the pit. I have become like a man without assistance,

6 idle among the dead. I am like the wounded sleeping in sepulchers, whom you no longer remember, and who have been repelled by your hand.

7 They have lain me in the lower pit: in dark places and in the shadow of death.

8 Your fury has been confirmed over me. And you have brought all your waves upon me.

9 You have sent my acquaintances far from me. They have set me as an abomination to themselves. I was handed over, yet I did not depart.

10 My eyes languished before destitution. All day long, I cried out to you, O Lord. I stretched out my hands to you.

11 Will you perform wonders for the dead? Or will physicians raise to life, and so confess to you?

12 Could anyone declare your mercy in the sepulcher, or your truth from within perdition?

13 Will your wonders be known in the darkness, or your justice in the land of oblivion?

14 And I have cried out to you, O Lord, and in early morning, my prayer will come before you.

15 Lord, why do you reject my prayer? Why do you turn your face away from me?

16 I am poor, and I have been amid hardships from my youth. And, though I have been exalted, I am humbled and disturbed.

17 Your wrath has crossed into me, and your terrors have disturbed me.

18 They have surrounded me like water, all day long. They have surrounded me, all at once.

19 Friend and neighbor, and my acquaintances, you have sent far away from me, away from misery.

Psalms 88

1 The understanding of Ethan the Ezrahite.

2 I will sing the mercies of the Lord in eternity. I will announce your truth with my mouth, from generation to generation.

3 For you have said: Mercy will be built in the heavens, unto eternity. Your truth will be prepared there.

4 I have set up a covenant with my elect. I have sworn to David my servant:

5 I will prepare your offspring, even in eternity. And I will build up your throne, from generation to generation.

6 The heavens will confess your miracles, Lord, and also your truth, in the Church of the saints.

7 For who among the clouds is equal to the Lord? Who among the sons of God is like God?

8 God is glorified by the counsel of the saints. He is great and terrible above all those who are around him.

9 O Lord, God of hosts, who is like you? You are powerful, Lord, and your truth is all around you.

10 You rule over the power of the sea, and you even mitigate the movement of its waves.

11 You have humbled the arrogant one, like one who has been wounded. You have scattered your enemies with the arm of your strength.

12 Yours are the heavens, and yours is the earth. You founded the whole world in all its fullness.

13 You created the north and the sea. Tabor and Hermon will exult in your name.

14 Your arm acts with power. Let your hand be strengthened, and let your right hand be exalted.

15 Justice and judgment are the preparation of your throne. Mercy and truth will precede your face.

16 Blessed is the people that knows jubilation. They will walk in the light of your countenance, O Lord,

17 and they will exult in your name all day long, and they will be exalted in your justice.

18 For you are the glory of their virtue, and in your goodness, our horn will be exalted.

19 For our assumption is of the Lord, and it is of our king, the holy one of Israel.

20 Then you spoke in a vision to your holy ones, and you said: I have stationed help with the powerful one, and I have exalted the elect one from my people.

21 I have found my servant David. I have anointed him with my holy oil.

22 For my hand will assist him, and my arm will fortify him.

23 The enemy will have no advantage over him, nor will the son of iniquity be positioned to harm him.

24 And I will cut down his enemies before his face. And those who hate him, I will turn to flight.

25 And my truth and my mercy will be with him. And his horn will be exalted in my name.

26 And I will place his hand on the sea and his right hand on the rivers.

27 He will invoke me: "You are my father, my God, and the support of my salvation."

28 And I will make him the first-born, preeminent before the kings of the earth.

29 I will preserve my mercy for him eternally, and my covenant for him faithfully.

30 And I will set his offspring from generation to generation, and his throne like the days of heaven.

31 But if his sons abandon my law, and if they do not walk in my judgments,

32 if they profane my justices, and if they do not keep my commandments:

33 I will visit their iniquities with a rod, and their sins with a beating.

34 But I will not scatter my mercy from him, and I will not do harm to my truth.

35 And I will not profane my covenant, and I will not make void that which proceeds from my lips.

36 I have sworn by my holiness one time: I will not lie to David,

37 his offspring will remain for eternity. And his throne will be like the sun in my sight,

38 and, like the moon, it is perfected in eternity, and it is a faithful witness in heaven.

39 Yet, truly, you have rejected and despised, you have pushed away, my Christ.

40 You have overthrown the covenant of your servant. You have profaned his sanctuary on earth.

41 You have destroyed all his fences. You have made his territory dreadful.

42 All who pass by the way have plundered him. He has become a disgrace to his neighbors.

43 You have exalted the right hand of those who oppress him. You have brought joy to all his enemies.

44 You have diverted the help of his sword, and you have not assisted him in battle.

45 You have torn him away from cleansing, and you have smashed his throne down to the ground.

46 You have reduced the days of his time. You have flooded him with confusion.

47 How long, O Lord? Will you turn away unto the end? Will your wrath flare up like a fire?

48 Remember what my substance is. For could you really have appointed all the sons of men in vain?

49 Who is the man that will live, and yet not see death? Who will rescue his own soul from the hand of the underworld?

50 O Lord, where are your mercies of antiquity, just as you swore to David in your truth?

51 Be mindful, O Lord, of the disgrace of your servants (which I have sustained in my sinews) among many nations.

52 With these, your enemies have reproached you, O Lord; with these, they have reproached the commutation of your Christ.

53 Blessed is the Lord for all eternity. Amen. Amen.

Psalms 89

1 A prayer of Moses, the man of God. O Lord, you have been our refuge from generation to generation.

2 Before the mountains became, or the land was formed along with the world: from ages past, even to all ages, you are God.

3 And, lest man be turned aside in humiliation, you have said: Be converted, O sons of men.

4 For a thousand years before your eyes are like the days of yesterday, which have passed by, and they are like a watch of the night,

5 which was held for nothing: so their years shall be.

6 In the morning, he may pass away like grass; in the morning, he may flower and pass away. In the evening, he will fall, and harden, and become dry.

7 For, at your wrath, we have withered away, and we have been disturbed by your fury.

8 You have placed our iniquities in your sight, our age in the illumination of your countenance.

9 For all our days have faded away, and at your wrath, we have fainted. Our years will be considered to be like a spider's web.

10 The days of our years in them are seventy years. But in the powerful, they are eighty years, and more of these are with hardship and sorrow. For mildness has overwhelmed us, and we shall be corrected.

11 Who knows the power of your wrath? And, before fear, can your wrath

12 be numbered? So make known your right hand, along with men learned in heart, in wisdom.

13 Return, O Lord, how long? And may you be persuaded on behalf of your servants.

14 We were filled in the morning with your mercy, and we exulted and delighted all our days.

15 We have been rejoicing, because of the days in which you humbled us, because of the years in which we saw evils.

16 Look down upon your servants and upon their works, and direct their sons.

17 And may the splendor of the Lord our God be upon us. And so, direct the works of our hands over us; direct even the work of our hands.

Psalms 90

1 The Praise of a Canticle, of David. Whoever dwells with the assistance of the Most High will abide in the protection of the God of heaven.

2 He will say to the Lord, "You are my supporter and my refuge." My God, I will hope in him.

3 For he has freed me from the snare of those who go hunting, and from the harsh word.

4 He will overshadow you with his shoulders, and you will hope under his wings.

5 His truth will surround you with a shield. You will not be afraid: before the terror of the night,

6 before the arrow flying in the day, before the troubles that wander in the darkness, nor of invasion and the midday demon.

7 A thousand will fall before your side and ten thousand before your right hand. Yet it will not draw near you.

8 So then, truly, you will consider with your eyes, and you will see the retribution of sinners.

9 For you, O Lord, are my hope. You have set the Most High as your refuge.

10 Disaster will not draw near to you, and the scourge will not approach your tabernacle.

11 For he has given his Angels charge over you, so as to preserve you in all your ways.

12 With their hands, they will carry you, lest you hurt your foot against a stone.

13 You will walk over the asp and the king serpent, and you will trample the lion and the dragon.

14 Because he has hoped in me, I will free him. I will protect him because he has known my name.

15 He will cry out to me, and I will heed him. I am with him in tribulation. I will rescue him, and I will glorify him.

16 I will fill him with length of days. And I will reveal to him my salvation.

Psalms 91

1 A Canticle Psalm. On the day of the Sabbath.

2 It is good to confess to the Lord and to sing psalms to your name, O Most High:

3 to announce your mercy in the morning, and your truth throughout the night,

4 upon the ten strings, upon the psaltery, with a canticle, upon stringed instruments.

5 For you, O Lord, have delighted me with your doings, and I will exult in the works of your hands.

6 How great are your works, O Lord! Your thoughts have been made exceedingly deep.

7 A foolish man will not know these things, and a senseless one will not understand:

8 when sinners will have risen up like grass, and when all those who work iniquity will have appeared, that they shall pass away, age after age.

9 But you, O Lord, are the Most High for all eternity.

10 For behold your enemies, O Lord, for behold your enemies will perish, and all those who work iniquity will be dispersed.

11 And my horn will be exalted like that of the single-horned beast, and my old age will be exalted in fruitful mercy.

12 And my eye has looked down upon my enemies, and my ear will hear of the malignant rising up against me.

13 The just one will flourish like the palm tree. He will be multiplied like the cedar of Lebanon.

14 Those planted in the house of the Lord will flourish in the courts of the house of our God.

15 They will still be multiplied in a fruitful old age, and they will endure well,

16 so that they may announce that the Lord our God is righteous and that there is no iniquity in him.

Psalms 93

1 A Psalm of David himself. The Fourth Sabbath. The Lord is the God of retribution. The God of retribution acts in order to deliver.

2 Lift yourself up, for you judge the earth. Repay the arrogant with retribution.

3 How long will sinners, O Lord, how long will sinners glory?

4 How long will they utter and speak iniquity? How long will all who work injustice speak out?

5 They have humiliated your people, O Lord, and they have harassed your inheritance.

6 They have executed the widow and the new arrival, and they have slaughtered the orphan.

7 And they have said, "The Lord will not see, nor will the God of Jacob understand."

8 Understand, you senseless ones among the people. And be wise at last, you foolish ones.

9 He who formed the ear, will he not hear? And he who forged the eye, does he not look closely?

10 He who chastises nations, he who teaches man knowledge, will he not rebuke?

11 The Lord knows the thoughts of men: that these are in vain.

12 Blessed is the man whom you will instruct, O Lord. And you will teach him from your law.

13 So may you soothe him from the evil days, until a pit may be dug for sinners.

14 For the Lord will not drive away his people, and he will not abandon his inheritance,

15 even until the time when justice is being converted into judgment, and when those who are close to justice are all those who are upright of heart.

16 Who will rise up with me against the malignant? Or who will stand with me against the workers of iniquity?

17 Except that the Lord assisted me, my soul almost would have dwelt in Hell.

18 If ever I said, "My foot is slipping," then your mercy, O Lord, assisted me.

19 According to the multitude of my sorrows in my heart, your consolations have given joy to my soul.

20 Does the seat of iniquity adhere to you, you who contrive hardship within a commandment?

21 They will hunt down the soul of the just, and they will condemn innocent blood.

22 And the Lord has been made into a refuge for me, and my God into the assistance of my hope.

23 And he will repay them their iniquity, and he will destroy them in their malice. The Lord our God will utterly destroy them.

Psalms 95

1 A Canticle of David himself, when the house was built after the captivity. Sing to the Lord a new song. Sing to the Lord, all the earth.

2 Sing to the Lord and bless his name. Announce his salvation from day to day.

3 Announce his glory among the Gentiles, his miracles among all peoples.

4 For the Lord is great and greatly to be praised. He is terrible, beyond all gods.

5 For all the gods of the Gentiles are demons, but the Lord made the heavens.

6 Confession and beauty are in his sight. Sanctity and magnificence are in his sanctuary.

7 Bring to the Lord, you natives of the nations, bring to the Lord glory and honor.

8 Bring to the Lord glory for his name. Lift up sacrifices, and enter into his courts.

9 Adore the Lord in his holy court. Let the entire earth be shaken before his face.

10 Say among the Gentiles: The Lord has reigned. For he has even corrected the whole world, which will not be shaken. He will judge the peoples with fairness.

11 Let the heavens rejoice, and let the earth exult; let the sea and all its fullness be moved.

12 The fields and all the things that are in them will be glad. Then all the trees of the forest will rejoice

13 before the face of the Lord: for he arrives. For he arrives to judge the earth. He will judge the whole world with fairness and the peoples with his truth.

Psalms 96

1 This is to David, when his land was restored to him. The Lord has reigned, let the earth exult. Let the many islands rejoice.

2 Clouds and mist are all around him. Justice and judgment are corrections from his throne.

3 A fire will precede him, and it will enflame his enemies all around.

4 His lightnings have enlightened the whole world. The earth saw, and it was shaken.

5 The mountains flowed like wax before the face of the Lord, before the face of the Lord of all the earth.

6 The heavens announced his justice, and all peoples saw his glory.

7 May all those who adore graven images be confounded, along with those who glory in their false images. All you his Angels: Adore him.

8 Zion heard, and was glad. And the daughters of Judah exulted because of your judgments, O Lord.

9 For you are the Most High Lord over all the earth. You are greatly exalted above all gods.

10 You who love the Lord: hate evil. The Lord watches over the souls of his holy ones. He will free them from the hand of the sinner.

11 The light has risen for the just, and joy for the upright of heart.

12 Rejoice in the Lord, you just ones, and confess to the memory of his sanctuary.

Psalms 100

1 A Psalm of David himself. I will sing mercy and judgment to you, O Lord. I will sing psalms.

2 And I will have understanding within the immaculate way, when you will draw near to me. I wandered about in the innocence of my heart, in the midst of my house.

3 I will not display any unjust thing before my eyes. I have hated those carrying out betrayals.

4 The perverse heart did not adhere to me. And the malignant, who turned away before me, I would not recognize.

5 The one who secretly detracted his neighbor, this one I pursued. The one with an arrogant eye and an insatiable heart, with that one I would not eat.

6 My eyes looked toward the faithful of the earth, to sit with me. The one walking in the immaculate way, this one ministered to me.

7 He who has acted arrogantly will not dwell in the midst of my house. He who has spoken iniquity was not guided with the sight of my eyes.

8 In the morning, I executed all the sinners of the earth, so that I might scatter all the workers of iniquity from the city of the Lord.

Psalms 101

1 The prayer of the pauper, when he was anxious, and so he poured out his petition in the sight of the Lord.

2 O Lord, hear my prayer, and let my outcry reach you.

3 Do not turn your face away from me. In whatever day that I am in trouble, incline your ear to me. In whatever day that I will call upon you, heed me quickly.

4 For my days have faded away like smoke, and my bones have dried out like firewood.

5 I have been cut down like hay, and my heart has withered, for I had forgotten to eat my bread.

6 Before the voice of my groaning, my bone has adhered to my flesh.

7 I have become like a pelican in solitude. I have become like a night raven in a house.

8 I have kept vigil, and I have become like a solitary sparrow on a roof.

9 All day long my enemies reproached me, and those who praised me swore oaths against me.

10 For I chewed on ashes like bread, and I mixed weeping into my drink.

11 By the face of your anger and indignation, you lifted me up and threw me down.

12 My days have declined like a shadow, and I have dried out like hay.

13 But you, O Lord, endure for eternity, and your memorial is from generation to generation.

14 You will rise up and take pity on Zion, for it is time for its mercy, for the time has come.

15 For its stones have pleased your servants, and they will take pity on its land.

16 And the Gentiles will fear your name, O Lord, and all the kings of the earth your glory.

17 For the Lord has built up Zion, and he will be seen in his glory.

18 He has noticed of the prayer of the humble, and he has not despised their petition.

19 Let these things be written in another generation, and the people who will be created will praise the Lord.

20 For he has gazed from his high sanctuary. From heaven, the Lord has beheld the earth.

21 So may he hear the groans of those in shackles, in order that he may release the sons of the slain.

22 So may they announce the name of the Lord in Zion and his praise in Jerusalem:

23 while the people convene, along with kings, in order that they may serve the Lord.

24 He responded to him in the way of his virtue: Declare to me the brevity of my days.

25 Do not call me back in the middle of my days: your years are from generation to generation.

26 In the beginning, O Lord, you founded the earth. And the heavens are the work of your hands.

27 They will perish, but you remain. And all will grow old like a garment. And, like a blanket, you will change them, and they will be changed.

28 Yet you are ever yourself, and your years will not decline.

29 The sons of your servants will live, and their offspring will be guided aright in every age.

Psalms 102

1 To David himself. Bless the Lord, O my soul, and bless his holy name, all that is within me.

2 Bless the Lord, O my soul, and do not forget all his recompenses.

3 He forgives all your iniquities. He heals all your infirmities.

4 He redeems your life from destruction. He crowns you with mercy and compassion.

5 He satisfies your desire with good things. Your youth will be renewed like that of the eagle.

6 The Lord accomplishes mercies, and his judgment is for all who patiently endure injuries.

7 He has made his ways known to Moses, his will to the sons of Israel.

8 The Lord is compassionate and merciful, patient and full of mercy.

9 He will not be angry forever, and he will not threaten for eternity.

10 He has not dealt with us according to our sins, and he has not repaid us according to our iniquities.

11 For according to the height of the heavens above the earth, so has he reinforced his mercy toward those who fear him.

12 As far as the east is from the west, so far has he removed our iniquities from us.

13 As a father is compassionate to his sons, so has the Lord been compassionate to those who fear him.

14 For he knows our form. He has called to mind that we are dust.

15 Man: his days are like hay. Like the flower of the field, so will he flourish.

16 For the spirit in him will pass away, and it will not remain, and he will know his place no longer.

17 But the mercy of the Lord is from eternity, and even unto eternity, upon those who fear him. And his justice is with the sons of the sons,

18 with those who serve his covenant and have been mindful of his commandments by doing them.

19 The Lord has prepared his throne in heaven, and his kingdom will rule over all.

20 Bless the Lord, all you his Angels: powerful in virtue, doing his word, in order to heed the voice of his discourse.

21 Bless the Lord, all his hosts: his ministers who do his will.

22 Bless the Lord, all his works: in every place of his dominion. Bless the Lord, O my soul.

Psalms 103

1 To David himself. Bless the Lord, O my soul. O Lord my God, you are exceedingly great. You have clothed yourself with confession and beauty;

2 you are dressed with light like a garment, while you stretch out heaven like a tent.

3 You cover its heights with water. You set the clouds as your stairs. You walk upon the wings of the winds.

4 You make your Angels a breath of life, and your ministers a burning fire.

5 You founded the earth upon its stable base. It will not be bent from age to age.

6 The abyss, like a garment, is its clothing. The waters will remain standing above the mountains.

7 At your rebuke, they will flee. At the voice of your thunder, they will dread.

8 The mountains ascend, and the plains descend, to the place which you have founded for them.

9 You have set a limit that they will not cross. And they will not return to cover the earth.

10 You spring forth fountains in steep valleys. The waters will cross through the midst of the mountains.

11 All the wild beasts of the field will drink. The wild donkeys will anticipate in their thirst.

12 Above them, the flying things of the air will dwell. From the midst of the rocks, they will utter voices.

13 You irrigate the mountains from your heights. The earth will be satiated from the fruit of your works,

14 producing grass for cattle and herbs for the service of men. So may you draw bread from the earth,

15 and wine, in order to cheer the heart of man. Then he may gladden his face with oil, and bread will confirm the heart of man.

16 The trees of the field will be saturated, along with the cedars of Lebanon, which he planted.

17 There, the sparrows will make their nests. The leader of them is the house of the heron.

18 The heights of the hills are for the deer; the rock is a refuge for the hedgehog.

19 He has made the moon for seasons; the sun knows its setting.

20 You appointed darkness, and it has become night; all the beasts of the forest will cross through it.

21 The young lions will roar, while searching for and seizing their meal from God.

22 The sun arose, and they were gathered together; and in their dens, they will lie down together.

23 Man will go forth to his work and to his activities, until the evening.

24 How great are your works, O Lord! You have made all things in wisdom. The earth has been filled with your possessions.

25 This sea is great and its hands are spacious. There are creeping things without number: the small animals with the great.

26 There, the ships will pass by this sea-serpent that you have formed to mock them.

27 All these expect you to give them food in due time.

28 What you give to them, they will gather. When you open your hand, they will all be filled with goodness.

29 But if you turn your face away, they will be disturbed. You will take away their breath, and they will fail, and they will return to their dust.

30 You will send forth your Spirit, and they will be created. And you will renew the face of the earth.

31 May the glory of the Lord be for all ages. The Lord will rejoice in his works.

32 He considers the earth, and he makes it tremble. He touches the mountains, and they smoke.

33 I will sing to the Lord with my life. I will sing psalms to my God, as long as I am.

34 May my speech be pleasing to him. Truly, I will take delight in the Lord.

35 Let sinners fade away from the earth, along with the unjust, so that they may not be. Bless the Lord, O my soul.

Psalms 104

1 Alleluia. Confess to the Lord, and invoke his name. Announce his works among the nations.

2 Sing to him, and sing psalms to him. Describe all his wonders.

3 Be praised in his holy name. Let the heart of those who seek the Lord rejoice.

4 Seek the Lord, and be confirmed. Seek his face always.

5 Remember his miracles, which he has done, his portents and the judgments of his mouth:

6 you offspring of Abraham his servant, you sons of Jacob his elect.

7 He is the Lord our God. His judgments are throughout the entire earth.

8 He has remembered his covenant for all ages: the word that he entrusted to a thousand generations,

9 which he assigned to Abraham, and his oath to Isaac.

10 And he stationed the same for Jacob with a precept, and for Israel with an eternal testament,

11 saying: To you, I will give the land of Canaan, the allotment of your inheritance.

12 Though they may have been but a small number, very few and foreigners there,

13 and though they passed from nation to nation, and from one kingdom to another people,

14 he allowed no man to harm them, and he reproved kings on their behalf.

15 Do not be willing to touch my Christ, and do not be willing to malign my prophets.

16 And he called a famine upon the land, and he crushed every foundation of the bread.

17 He sent a man before them: Joseph, who had been sold as a slave.

18 They humbled his feet in shackles; the iron pierced his soul,

19 until his word arrived. The eloquence of the Lord inflamed him.

20 The king sent and released him; he was the ruler of the people, and he dismissed him.

21 He established him as master of his house and ruler of all his possessions,

22 so that he might instruct his princes as himself, and teach his elders prudence.

23 And Israel entered into Egypt, and Jacob became a sojourner in the land of Ham.

24 And he helped his people greatly, and he strengthened them over their enemies.

25 He turned their heart to hate his people, and to deal deceitfully with his servants.

26 He sent Moses, his servant, and Aaron, the one whom he chose.

27 He placed with them signs of his word, and portents in the land of Ham.

28 He sent darkness and made it conceal, and he did not afflict them with his speech.

29 He turned their waters into blood, and he slaughtered their fish.

30 Their land brought forth frogs, even in the inner chambers of their kings.

31 He spoke, and there came forth common flies and gnats, in every region.

32 He gave them a shower of hail and a burning fire, in the same land.

33 And he struck their vineyards and their fig trees, and he crushed the trees of their region.

34 He spoke, and the locust came forth, and the caterpillar, of which there was no number.

35 And it devoured all the grass in their land, and it consumed all the fruit of their land.

36 And he struck all the first-born in their land, the first-fruits of all their labor.

37 And he led them out with silver and gold, and there was not an infirm one among their tribes.

38 Egypt was joyful at their departure, for the fear of them lay heavy upon them.

39 He spread a cloud for their protection, and a fire, to give them light through the night.

40 They petitioned, and the quail came; and he satisfied them with the bread of heaven.

41 He ruptured the rock and the waters flowed: rivers gushed in the dry land.

42 For he had called to mind his holy word, which he kept near to his servant Abraham.

43 And he led forth his people in exultation, and his elect in rejoicing.

44 And he gave them the regions of the Gentiles, and they possessed the labors of the peoples,

45 so that they might observe his justifications, and inquire about his law.

Psalms 105

1 Alleluia. Confess to the Lord, for he is good, for his mercy is with every generation.

2 Who will declare the powers of the Lord? Who make a hearing for all his praises?

3 Blessed are those who keep judgment and who do justice at all times.

4 Remember us, O Lord, with good will for your people. Visit us with your salvation,

5 so that we may see the goodness of your elect, so that we may rejoice in the joy of your nation, so that you may be praised along with your inheritance.

6 We have sinned, as have our fathers. We have acted unjustly; we have wrought iniquity.

7 Our fathers did not understand your miracles in Egypt. They did not remember the multitude of your mercies. And they provoked you, while going up to the sea, even the Red Sea.

8 And he saved them for the sake of his name, so that he might make known his power.

9 And he rebuked the Red Sea, and it dried up. And he led them into the abyss, as if into a desert.

10 And he saved them from the hand of those who hated them. And he redeemed them from the hand of the enemy.

11 And the water covered those who troubled them. Not one of them remained.

12 And they believed his words, and they sang his praises.

13 As soon as they had finished, they forgot his works, and they would not endure his counsel.

14 And they coveted their desire in the desert, and they tempted God in a waterless place.

15 And he granted to them their request, and he sent abundance into their souls.

16 And they provoked Moses in the camp, and Aaron, the holy one of the Lord.

17 The earth opened and swallowed Dathan, and it covered the congregation of Abiram.

18 And a fire broke out in their congregation. A flame burned up the sinners.

19 And they fashioned a calf at Horeb, and they adored a graven image.

20 And they exchanged their glory for the likeness of a calf that eats hay.

21 They forgot God, who saved them, who did great things in Egypt:

22 miracles in the land of Ham, terrible things at the Red Sea.

23 And he said that he would destroy them, yet Moses, his elect, stood firm before him in the breach, in order to avert his wrath, lest he destroy them.

24 And they held the desirable land to be nothing. They did not trust in his word.

25 And they murmured in their tabernacles. They did not heed the voice of the Lord.

26 And he lifted up his hand over them, in order to prostrate them in the desert,

27 and in order to cast their offspring among the nations, and to scatter them among the regions.

28 And they were initiated into Baal of Peor, and they ate the sacrifices of the dead.

29 And they provoked him with their inventions, and ruination was multiplied in them.

30 Then Phinehas stood up and placated him: and so the violent disturbance ceased.

31 And it was reputed to him unto justice, from generation to generation, even forever.

32 And they provoked him at the Waters of Contradiction, and Moses was afflicted because of them,

33 for they exasperated his spirit. And so he divided them with his lips.

34 They did not destroy the nations, about which the Lord had spoken to them.

35 And they were mixed among the Gentiles. And they learned their works,

36 and they served their graven images, and it became a scandal to them.

37 And they sacrificed their sons and their daughters to demons.

38 And they shed innocent blood: the blood of their sons and of their daughters, which they sacrificed to the graven images of Canaan. And the land was infected with bloodshed,

39 and was contaminated with their works. And they fornicated according to their own inventions.

40 And the Lord became furiously angry with his people, and he abhorred his inheritance.

41 And he delivered them into the hands of the nations. And those who hated them became rulers over them.

42 And their enemies afflicted them, and they were humbled under their hands.

43 Many times, he delivered them. Yet they provoked him with their counsel, and they were brought low by their iniquities.

44 And he saw that they were in tribulation, and he heard their prayer.

45 And he was mindful of his covenant, and he repented according to the multitude of his mercies.

46 And he provided for them with mercies, in the sight of all those who had seized them.

47 Save us, O Lord our God, and gather us from the nations, so that we may confess your holy name and glory in your praise.

48 Blessed is the Lord God of Israel, from ages past, even to all ages. And let all the people say: Amen. Amen.

Psalms 106

1 Alleluia. Confess to the Lord, for he is good, for his mercy is with every generation.

2 Let those who have been redeemed by the Lord say so: those whom he redeemed from the hand of the enemy and gathered from the regions,

3 from the rising of the sun and its setting, from the north and from the sea.

4 They wandered into solitude in a waterless place. They did not find the way of the city to be their dwelling place.

5 They were hungry, and they were thirsty. Their soul fainted within them.

6 And they cried out to the Lord in tribulation, and he rescued them in their necessity.

7 And he led them in the right way, so that they might go forth to a city of habitation.

8 Let his mercies confess to the Lord, and let his miracles confess to the sons of men.

9 For he has satisfied the empty soul, and he has satisfied the hungry soul with good things:

10 those sitting in darkness and in the shadow of death, shackled by extreme poverty and by iron.

11 For they exasperated the eloquence of God, and they irritated the deliberation of the Most High.

12 And their heart was brought low with hardships. They were weakened, and there was no one to help them.

13 And they cried out to the Lord in their tribulation, and he freed them from their distress.

14 And he led them out of darkness and the shadow of death, and he broke apart their chains.

15 Let his mercies confess to the Lord, and let his miracles confess to the sons of men.

16 For he has crushed the gates of brass and broken the iron bars.

17 He has taken them up, from the way of their iniquity. For they were brought low, because of their injustices.

18 Their soul abhorred all food, and they drew near even to the gates of death.

19 And they cried out to the Lord in their tribulation, and he delivered them in their necessity.

20 He sent his word, and he healed them, and he rescued them from their utter destruction.

21 Let his mercies confess to the Lord, and let his miracles confess to the sons of men.

22 And let them offer sacrifice with the sacrifice of praise, and let them announce his works in exultation.

23 Those who descend to the sea in ships, making their livelihood in the great waters:

24 these have seen the works of the Lord and his wonders in the deep.

25 He spoke: and a windstorm stood up, and its waves were exalted.

26 They ascend even to the heavens, and they descend even to the abyss. Their soul will waste away in distress.

27 They were troubled, and they moved like a drunkard, and all their wisdom was consumed.

28 And they cried out to the Lord in their tribulation, and he led them out of their distress.

29 And he replaced the storm with a breeze, and its waves were stilled.

30 And they were joyful that it was stilled, and he led them into the haven that they desired.

31 Let his mercies confess to the Lord, and let his miracles confess to the sons of men.

32 And let them exalt him in the Church of the people, and praise him in the chair of the elders.

33 He has placed rivers in the desert and sources of water in dry places,

34 a fruit-bearing land in the midst of brine, before the malice of those who dwell in it.

35 He has placed a desert in the midst of pools of waters, and a land without water in the midst of sources of water.

36 And he has gathered the hungry together there, and they constructed a city of habitation.

37 And they sowed fields and planted vineyards, and they produced the fruit of nativity.

38 And he blessed them, and they were multiplied exceedingly. And he did not diminish their beasts of burden.

39 And they became few, and they were afflicted by the tribulation of evils and of sorrow.

40 Contempt was poured over their leaders, and he caused them to wander in an impassable place, and not on the way.

41 And he helped the poor out of destitution, and he stationed families like sheep.

42 The upright will see, and they will rejoice. And every iniquity will block its mouth.

43 Who is wise and will keep these things? And who will understand the mercies of the Lord?

Psalms 107

1 A Canticle Psalm, of David himself.

2 My heart is prepared, O God, my heart is prepared. I will sing songs, and I will sing psalms in my glory.

3 Rise up, my glory. Rise up, Psalter and harp. I will arise in early morning.

4 I will confess to you, O Lord, among the peoples. And I will sing psalms to you among the nations.

5 For your mercy is great, beyond the heavens, and your truth, even to the clouds.

6 Be exalted, O God, beyond the heavens, and your glory, beyond all the earth,

7 so that your beloved may be freed. Save with your right hand, and heed me.

8 God has spoken in his holiness. I will exult, and I will divide Shechem, and I will divide by measure the steep valley of tabernacles.

9 Gilead is mine, and Manasseh is mine, and Ephraim is the supporter of my head. Judah is my king.

10 Moab is the cooking pot of my hope. I will extend my shoe in Idumea; the foreigners have become my friends.

11 Who will lead me into the fortified city? Who will lead me, even into Idumea?

12 Will not you, O God, who had rejected us? And will not you, O God, go out with our armies?

13 Grant us help from tribulation, for vain is the help of man.

14 In God, we will act virtuously, and he will bring our enemies to nothing.

Psalms 108

1 Unto the end. A Psalm of David.

2 O God, do not be silent toward my praise, for the mouth of the sinner and the mouth of the deceitful one have been opened against me.

3 They have spoken against me with deceitful tongues, and they have surrounded me with hateful words, and they fought against me over nothing.

4 Instead of choosing to act on my behalf, they detracted me. But I gave myself to prayer.

5 And they set evil against me, instead of good, and hatred, in return for my love.

6 Establish the sinner over him, and let the devil stand at his right hand.

7 When he is judged, may he go forth in condemnation, and may his prayer be counted as sin.

8 May his days be few, and let another take his episcopate.

9 May his sons be orphans, and his wife a widow.

10 May his sons be carried by those who walk unsteadily, and may they go begging. And may they be cast out of their dwelling places.

11 May the money lenders scrutinize all his belongings, and let foreigners plunder his labors.

12 May there be no one to assist him, nor anyone to be compassionate to his orphaned children.

13 May his posterity be in utter ruin. In one generation, may his name be wiped away.

14 May the iniquity of his fathers return in memory before the sight of the Lord, and do not let the sin of his mother be wiped away.

15 May these be opposite the Lord always, but let their memory perish from the earth.

16 For certain things are not remembered about them, in order to be merciful.

17 And so the destitute man was pursued, with the beggar and the remorseful in heart, so as to be put to death.

18 And he loved a curse, and it came to him. And he was unwilling to have a blessing, and it went far from him. And he clothed himself with curses like a garment, and it entered his inner self like water, and it entered his bones like oil.

19 May it be to him like a garment that covers him, and like a belt that always cinches him.

20 This is the work of those who detract me with the Lord and who speak evils against my soul.

21 But as for you, Lord, O Lord: act on my behalf for your name's sake. For your mercy is sweet.

22 Free me, for I am destitute and poor, and my heart has been disquieted within me.

23 I have been taken away like a shadow when it declines, and I have been shaken off like locusts.

24 My knees have been weakened by fasting, and my flesh has been replaced by oil.

25 And I have become a disgrace to them. They saw me, and they shook their heads.

26 Help me, O Lord, my God. Save me according to your mercy.

27 And let them know that this is your hand, and that you, O Lord, have done this.

28 They will curse, and you will bless. May those who rise up against me be confounded. But your servant will rejoice.

29 May those who detract me be clothed with shame, and may they be covered with their confusion, as if with a double cloak.

30 I will confess exceedingly to the Lord with my mouth. And I will praise him in the midst of the multitude.

31 For he stands at the right hand of the poor, in order to save my soul from persecutors.

Psalms 113

1 Alleluia. At the departure of Israel from Egypt, the house of Jacob from a barbarous people:

2 Judea was made his sanctuary; Israel was made his power.

3 The sea looked, and it fled. The Jordan was turned back again.

4 The mountains exulted like rams, and the hills like lambs among the sheep.

5 What happened to you, O sea, so that you fled, and to you, O Jordan, so that you were turned back again?

6 What happened to you, O mountains, so that you exulted like rams, and to you, O hills, so that you exulted like lambs among the sheep?

7 Before the face of the Lord, the earth was moved, before the face of the God of Jacob.

8 He converted the rock into pools of water, and the cliff into fountains of waters.

9 Not to us, O Lord, not to us, but to your name give glory.

10 Give glory to your mercy and your truth, lest the Gentiles should say, "Where is their God?"

11 But our God is in heaven. All things whatsoever that he has willed, he has done.

12 The idols of the nations are silver and gold, the works of the hands of men.

13 They have mouths, and do not speak; they have eyes, and do not see.

14 They have ears, and do not hear; they have noses, and do not smell.

15 They have hands, and do not feel; they have feet, and do not walk. Neither will they cry out with their throat.

16 Let those who make them become like them, along with all who trust in them.

17 The house of Israel has hoped in the Lord. He is their helper and their protector.

18 The house of Aaron has hoped in the Lord. He is their helper and their protector.

19 Those who fear the Lord have hoped in the Lord. He is their helper and their protector.

20 The Lord has been mindful of us, and he has blessed us. He has blessed the house of Israel. He has blessed the house of Aaron.

21 He has blessed all who fear the Lord, the small with the great.

22 May the Lord add blessings upon you: upon you, and upon your sons.

23 Blessed are you by the Lord, who made heaven and earth.

24 The heaven of heaven is for the Lord, but the earth he has given to the sons of men.

25 The dead will not praise you, Lord, and neither will all those who descend into Hell.

26 But we who live will bless the Lord, from this time forward, and even forever.

Psalms 117

1 Alleluia. Confess to the Lord, for he is good, for his mercy is forever.

2 Let Israel now say: For he is good, for his mercy is forever.

3 Let the house of Aaron now say: For his mercy is forever.

4 Let those who fear the Lord now say: For his mercy is forever.

5 In my tribulation, I called upon the Lord. And the Lord heeded me with generosity.

6 The Lord is my helper. I will not fear what man can do to me.

7 The Lord is my helper. And I will look down upon my enemies.

8 It is good to trust in the Lord, rather than to trust in man.

9 It is good to hope in the Lord, rather than to hope in leaders.

10 All the nations have surrounded me. And, in the name of the Lord, I have been avenged over them.

11 Surrounding me, they closed in on me. And, in the name of the Lord, I have been avenged over them.

12 They surrounded me like a swarm, and they burned like fire among the thorns. And, in the name of the Lord, I have been avenged over them.

13 Having been pushed, I was overturned so as to fall. But the Lord took me up.

14 The Lord is my strength and my praise. And he has become my salvation.

15 A voice of exultation and salvation is in the tabernacles of the just.

16 The right hand of the Lord has wrought virtue. The right hand of the Lord has exalted me. The right hand of the Lord has wrought virtue.

17 I will not die, but I will live. And I will declare the works of the Lord.

18 When chastising, the Lord chastised me. But he has not delivered me over to death.

19 Open the gates of justice to me. I will enter them, and I will confess to the Lord.

20 This is the gate of the Lord. The just will enter by it.

21 I will confess to you because you have heard me. And you have become my salvation.

22 The stone which the builders have rejected, this has become the head of the corner.

23 By the Lord has this been done, and it is a wonder before our eyes.

24 This is the day that the Lord has made. Let us exult and rejoice in it.

25 O Lord, grant salvation to me. O Lord, grant good prosperity.

26 Blessed is he who arrives in the name of the Lord. We have blessed you from the house of the Lord.

27 The Lord is God, and he has enlightened us. Establish a solemn day amid a dense crowd, even to the horn of the altar.

28 You are my God, and I will confess to you. You are my God, and I will exalt you. I will confess to you, for you have heeded me. And you have become my salvation.

29 Confess to the Lord, for he is good, for his mercy is forever.

Psalms 118

1 Alleluia. ALEPH. Blessed are the immaculate in the way, who walk in the law of the Lord.

2 Blessed are those who examine his testimonies. They seek him with their whole heart.

3 For those who work iniquity have not walked in his ways.

4 You have ordered your commandments to be kept most diligently.

5 I wish that my ways may be directed so as to keep your justifications.

6 Then I will not be confounded, when I will look into all your commandments.

7 I will confess to you with honesty of heart. In this way, I have learned the judgments of your justice.

8 I will keep your justifications. Do not utterly abandon me.

9 BETH. By what does an adolescent correct his way? By keeping to your words.

10 With my whole heart, I have sought you. Do not let me be driven away from your commandments.

11 I have hidden your eloquence in my heart, so that I may not sin against you.

12 Blessed are you, O Lord. Teach me your justifications.

13 With my lips, I have pronounced all the judgments of your mouth.

14 I have been delighted in the way of your testimonies, as if in all riches.

15 I will be trained in your commandments, and I will consider your ways.

16 I will meditate on your justifications. I will not forget your words.

17 GHIMEL. Repay your servant, revive me; and I will keep your words.

18 Reveal to my eyes, and I will consider the wonders of your law.

19 I am a sojourner on the earth. Do not hide your commandments from me.

20 My soul has longed to desire your justifications at all times.

21 You have rebuked the arrogant. Those who decline from your commandments are accursed.

22 Take me away from disgrace and contempt, for I have sought your testimonies.

23 For even the leaders sat and spoke against me. But your servant has been trained in your justifications.

24 For your testimonies are also my meditation, and your justifications are my counsel.

25 DALETH. My soul has adhered to the pavement. Revive me according to your word.

26 I have declared my ways, and you have heeded me. Teach me your justifications.

27 Instruct me in the way of your justifications, and I will be trained in your wonders.

28 My soul has slumbered because of weariness. Confirm me in your words.

29 Remove the way of iniquity from me, and have mercy on me by your law.

30 I have chosen the way of truth. I have not forgotten your judgments.

31 I have adhered to your testimonies, O Lord. Do not be willing to confound me.

32 I have run by way of your commandments, when you enlarged my heart.

33 HE. O Lord, place the law before me, the way of your justifications, and I will always inquire into it.

34 Give me understanding, and I will examine your law. And I will keep it with my whole heart.

35 Lead me according to the path of your commandments, for I have desired this.

36 Bend my heart with your testimonies, and not with avarice.

37 Turn my eyes away, lest they see what is vain. Revive me in your way.

38 Station your eloquence with your servant, along with your fear.

39 Cut off my disgrace, which I have taken up, for your judgments are delightful.

40 Behold, I have longed for your commandments. Revive me in your fairness.

41 VAU. And let your mercy overwhelm me, O Lord: your salvation according to your eloquence.

42 And I will respond to those who reproach me by word, for I have hoped in your words.

43 And do not utterly take away the word of truth from my mouth. For in your judgments, I have hoped beyond hope.

44 And I will always keep your law, in this age and forever and ever.

45 And I have wandered far and wide, because I was seeking your commandments.

46 And I spoke of your testimonies in the sight of kings, and I was not confounded.

47 And I meditated on your commandments, which I loved.

48 And I lifted up my hands to your commandments, which I loved. And I was trained in your justifications.

49 ZAIN. Be mindful of your word to your servant, by which you have given me hope.

50 This has consoled me in my humiliation, for your word has revived me.

51 The arrogant act altogether iniquitously, but I have not turned aside from your law.

52 I called to mind your judgments of antiquity, O Lord, and I was consoled.

53 Faintness has taken hold of me, because of the sinners, those who abandon your law.

54 Your justifications were the subject of my worthy singing, in the place of my pilgrimage.

55 During the night, I remembered your name, O Lord, and I kept your law.

56 This has happened to me because I sought your justifications.

57 HETH. O Lord, my portion, I have said that I would keep your law.

58 I have beseeched your face with my whole heart. Be merciful to me according to your word.

59 I have considered my ways, and I have turned my feet toward your testimonies.

60 I have been prepared, and I have not been disturbed, so that I may keep your commandments.

61 The ropes of the impious have encircled me, and I have not forgotten your law.

62 I arose in the middle of the night to confess to you, over the judgments of your justification.

63 I am a partaker with all those who fear you and who keep your commandments.

64 The earth, O Lord, is full of your mercy. Teach me your justifications.

65 TETH. You have done well with your servant, O Lord, according to your word.

66 Teach me goodness and discipline and knowledge, for I have trusted your commandments.

67 Before I was humbled, I committed offenses; because of this, I have kept to your word.

68 You are good, so in your goodness teach me your justifications.

69 The iniquity of the arrogant has been multiplied over me. Yet I will examine your commandments with all my heart.

70 Their heart has been curdled like milk. Truly, I have meditated on your law.

71 It is good for me that you humbled me, so that I may learn your justifications.

72 The law of your mouth is good for me, beyond thousands of gold and silver pieces.

73 IOD. Your hands have created me and formed me. Give me understanding, and I will learn your commandments.

74 Those who fear you will see me, and they will rejoice. For I have greatly hoped in your words.

75 I know, O Lord, that your judgments are fairness. And in your truth, you have humbled me.

76 Let it be your mercy that consoles me, according to your eloquence to your servant.

77 Let your compassion draw near to me, and I will live. For your law is my meditation.

78 Let the arrogant be confounded, for unjustly they have done iniquity to me. But I will be trained in your commandments.

79 Let those who fear you turn to me, along with those who know your testimonies.

80 Let my heart be immaculate in your justifications, so that I may not be confounded.

81 CAPH. My soul has faltered in your salvation, yet in your word, I have hoped beyond hope.

82 My eyes have failed in your eloquence, saying, "When will you console me?"

83 For I have become like a wineskin in the frost. I have not forgotten your justifications.

84 How many are the days of your servant? When will you bring judgment against those who persecute me?

85 The iniquitous have spoken fables to me. But these are unlike your law.

86 All your commandments are truth. They have been persecuting me unjustly: assist me.

87 They have nearly consumed me on earth. Yet I have not forsaken your commandments.

88 Revive me according to your mercy. And I will keep the testimonies of your mouth.

89 LAMED. O Lord, your word remains firm in heaven, for all eternity.

90 Your truth is from generation to generation. You have founded the earth, and it remains firm.

91 By your ordinance, the day perseveres. For all things are in service to you.

92 If your law had not been my meditation, then perhaps I would have perished in my humiliation.

93 I will not forget your justifications, for eternity. For by them, you have enlivened me.

94 I am yours. Accomplish my salvation. For I have inquired into your justifications.

95 The sinners have waited for me, in order to destroy me. I have understood your testimonies.

96 I have seen the end of the consummation of all things. Your commandment is exceedingly broad.

97 MEM. How have I loved your law, O Lord? It is my meditation all day long.

98 By your commandment, you have made me able to see far, beyond my enemies. For it is with me for eternity.

99 I have understood beyond all my teachers. For your testimonies are my meditation.

100 I have understood beyond the elders. For I have searched your commandments.

101 I have prohibited my feet from every evil way, so that I may keep your words.

102 I have not declined from your judgments, because you have stationed a law for me.

103 How sweet is your eloquence to my palate, more so than honey to my mouth!

104 I obtained understanding by your commandments. Because of this, I have hated every way of iniquity.

105 NUN. Your word is a lamp to my feet and a light to my paths.

106 I have sworn it, and so I am determined to keep the judgments of your justice.

107 I have been altogether humbled, Lord. Revive me according to your word.

108 Make the willing offerings of my mouth well pleasing, Lord, and teach me your judgments.

109 My soul is always in my hands, and I have not forgotten your law.

110 Sinners have set a snare for me, yet I have not strayed from your commandments.

111 I have acquired your testimonies as an inheritance unto eternity, because they are the exultation of my heart.

112 I have inclined my heart to do your justifications for eternity, as a recompense.

113 SAMECH. I have hated the iniquitous, and I have loved your law.

114 You are my helper and my supporter. And in your word, I have greatly hoped.

115 Turn away from me, you malignant ones. And I will examine the commandments of my God.

116 Uphold me according to your eloquence, and I will live. And let me not be confounded in my expectation.

117 Help me, and I will be saved. And I will meditate always on your justifications.

118 You have despised all those who fell away from your judgments. For their intention is unjust.

119 I have considered all the sinners of the earth to be transgressors. Therefore, I have loved your testimonies.

120 Pierce my flesh with your fear, for I am afraid of your judgments.

121 AIN. I have accomplished judgment and justice. Do not hand me over to those who slander me.

122 Uphold your servant in what is good. And do not allow the arrogant to slander me.

123 My eyes have failed in your salvation and in the eloquence of your justice.

124 Deal with your servant according to your mercy, and teach me your justifications.

125 I am your servant. Give me understanding, so that I may know your testimonies.

126 It is time to act, O Lord. They have dissipated your law.

127 Therefore, I have loved your commandments beyond gold and topaz.

128 Because of this, I was directed toward all your commandments. I held hatred for every iniquitous way.

129 PHE. Your testimonies are wonderful. Therefore, my soul has been examined by them.

130 The declaration of your words illuminates, and it gives understanding to little ones.

131 I opened my mouth and drew breath, for I desired your commandments.

132 Gaze upon me and be merciful to me, according to the judgment of those who love your name.

133 Direct my steps according to your eloquence, and let no injustice rule over me.

134 Redeem me from the slanders of men, so that I may keep your commandments.

135 Make your face shine upon your servant, and teach me your justifications.

136 My eyes have gushed like springs of water, because they have not kept your law.

137 SADE. You are just, O Lord, and your judgment is right.

138 You have commanded justice: your testimonies and your truth even more so.

139 My zeal has caused me to pine away, because my enemies have forgotten your words.

140 Your eloquence has been greatly enflamed, and your servant has loved it.

141 I am young and treated with contempt. But I have not forgotten your justifications.

142 Your justice is justice for all eternity, and your law is truth.

143 Tribulation and anguish have found me. Your commandments are my meditation.

144 Your testimonies are fairness unto eternity. Give me understanding, and I will live.

145 COPH. I cried out with my whole heart. Heed me, O Lord. I will ask for your justifications.

146 I cried out to you. Save me, so that I may keep your commandments.

147 I arrived first in maturity, and so I cried out. For in your words, I have hoped beyond hope.

148 My eyes preceded the dawn for you, so that I might meditate on your eloquence.

149 Hear my voice according to your mercy, O Lord. And revive me according to your judgment.

150 Those who persecute me have drawn near to iniquity, but they been brought far from your law.

151 You are near, O Lord, and all your ways are truth.

152 I have known from the beginning about your testimonies. For you founded them in eternity.

153 RES. See my humiliation and rescue me, for I have not forgotten your law.

154 Judge my judgment and redeem me. Revive me because of your eloquence.

155 Salvation is far from sinners, because they have not inquired about your justifications.

156 Many are your mercies, O Lord. Enliven me according to your judgment.

157 Many are those who persecute me and who trouble me. I have not turned away from your testimonies.

158 I saw the prevaricators, and I pine away. For they have not kept your word.

159 O Lord, see how I have loved your commandments. Revive me in your mercy.

160 The beginning of your words is truth. All the judgments of your justice are for eternity.

161 SIN. The leaders have persecuted me without cause. And my heart has been awed by your words.

162 I will rejoice over your eloquence, like one who has found many spoils.

163 I have held hatred for iniquity, and I have abhorred it. Yet I have loved your law.

164 Seven times a day, I uttered praise to you about the judgments of your justice.

165 Those who love your law have great peace, and there is no scandal for them.

166 I have waited for your salvation, O Lord. And I have loved your commandments.

167 My soul has kept to your testimonies and has loved them exceedingly.

168 I have served your commandments and your testimonies. For all my ways are before your sight.

169 TAU. O Lord, let my supplication draw near in your sight. Grant understanding to me according to your eloquence.

170 Let my petition enter before you. Rescue me according to your word.

171 A hymn will burst forth from my lips, when you will teach me your justifications.

172 My tongue will pronounce your eloquence. For all your commandments are fairness.

173 Let it be your hand that saves me. For I have chosen your commandments.

174 O Lord, I have longed for your salvation, and your law is my meditation.

175 My soul will live and will praise you, and your judgments will assist me.

176 I have gone astray like a sheep that is lost. Seek out your servant, for I have not forgotten your commandments.

Psalms 131

1 A Canticle in steps. O Lord, remember David and all his meekness,

2 how he swore to the Lord, how he made a vow to the God of Jacob:

3 I shall not enter into the tabernacle of my house, nor climb into the bed where I lie down;

4 I shall not give sleep to my eyes, nor slumber to my eyelids

5 and rest to my temples, until I find a place for the Lord, a tabernacle for the God of Jacob.

6 Behold, we heard of it in Ephrathah. We discovered it in the fields of the forest.

7 We will enter into his tabernacle. We will adore in the place where his feet stood.

8 Rise up, O Lord, into your resting place. You and the ark of your sanctification.

9 Let your priests be clothed with justice, and let your saints exult.

10 For the sake of your servant David, do not turn away the face of your Christ.

11 The Lord has sworn the truth to David, and he will not disappoint: I will set upon your throne from the fruit of your lineage.

12 If your sons will keep my covenant and these, my testimonies, which I will teach to them, then their sons will sit upon your throne even forever.

13 For the Lord has chosen Zion. He has chosen it as his dwelling place.

14 This is my resting place, forever and ever. Here I will dwell, for I have chosen it.

15 When blessing, I will bless her widow. I will satisfy her poor with bread.

16 I will clothe her priests with salvation, and her saints will rejoice with great joy.

17 There, I will produce a horn to David. There, I have prepared a lamp for my Christ.

18 I will clothe his enemies with confusion. But my sanctification will flourish over him.

Psalms 134

1 Alleluia. Praise the name of the Lord. You servants, praise the Lord.

2 You who stand in the house of the Lord, in the courts of the house of our God:

3 praise the Lord, for the Lord is good. Sing psalms to his name, for it is sweet.

4 For the Lord has chosen Jacob for himself, Israel for his own possession.

5 For I have known that the Lord is great, and our God is before all gods.

6 All things whatsoever that he willed, the Lord did: in heaven, on earth, in the sea, and in all the deep places.

7 He leads clouds from the ends of the earth. He has created lightnings in the rain. He has produced winds from his storehouses.

8 He struck the first-born of Egypt, from man even to cattle.

9 He sent signs and wonders into your midst, O Egypt: upon Pharaoh and upon all his servants.

10 He has struck many nations, and he has slaughtered strong kings:

11 Sihon, king of the Amorites, and Og, king of Bashan, and all the kingdoms of Canaan.

12 And he gave their land as an inheritance, as an inheritance for his people Israel.

13 Your name, O Lord, is in eternity. Your memorial, O Lord, is from generation to generation.

14 For the Lord will judge his people, and he will be petitioned by his servants.

15 The idols of the Gentiles are silver and gold, the works of the hands of men.

16 They have a mouth, and do not speak. They have eyes, and do not see.

17 They have ears, and do not hear. For neither is there any breath in their mouths.

18 Let those who make them become like them, along with all who trust in them.

19 Bless the Lord, O house of Israel. Bless the Lord, O house of Aaron.

20 Bless the Lord, O house of Levi. You who fear the Lord, bless the Lord.

21 The Lord is blessed from Zion, by those who dwell in Jerusalem.

Psalms 135

1 Alleluia. Confess to the Lord, for he is good: for his mercy is eternal.

2 Confess to the God of gods, for his mercy is eternal.

3 Confess to the Lord of lords, for his mercy is eternal.

4 He alone performs great miracles, for his mercy is eternal.

5 He made the heavens with understanding, for his mercy is eternal.

6 He established the earth above the waters, for his mercy is eternal.

7 He made the great lights, for his mercy is eternal:

8 the sun to rule the day, for his mercy is eternal:

9 the moon and the stars to rule the night, for his mercy is eternal.

10 He struck Egypt along with their first-born, for his mercy is eternal.

11 He led Israel away from their midst, for his mercy is eternal:

12 with a powerful hand and an outstretched arm, for his mercy is eternal.

13 He divided the Red Sea into separate parts, for his mercy is eternal.

14 And he led out Israel through the middle of it, for his mercy is eternal.

15 And he shook off Pharaoh and his army in the Red Sea, for his mercy is eternal.

16 He led his people through the desert, for his mercy is eternal.

17 He has struck great kings, for his mercy is eternal.

18 And he has slaughtered strong kings, for his mercy is eternal:

19 Sihon, king of the Amorites, for his mercy is eternal:

20 and Og, king of Bashan, for his mercy is eternal.

21 And he granted their land as an inheritance, for his mercy is eternal:

22 as an inheritance for his servant Israel, for his mercy is eternal.

23 For he was mindful of us in our humiliation, for his mercy is eternal.

24 And he redeemed us from our enemies, for his mercy is eternal.

25 He gives food to all flesh, for his mercy is eternal.

26 Confess to the God of heaven, for his mercy is eternal.

27 Confess to the Lord of lords, for his mercy is eternal.

Psalms 138

1 Unto the end. A Psalm of David. O Lord, you have examined me, and you have known me.

2 You have known my sitting down and my rising up again.

3 You have understood my thoughts from afar. My path and my fate, you have investigated.

4 And you have foreseen all my ways. For there is no word in my tongue.

5 Behold, O Lord, you have known all things: the newest and the very old. You have formed me, and you have placed your hand over me.

6 Your knowledge has become a wonder to me. It has been reinforced, and I am not able to prevail against it.

7 Where will I go from your Spirit? And where will I flee from your face?

8 If I ascend into heaven, you are there. If I descend into Hell, you are near.

9 If I assume my feathers in early morning, and dwell in the utmost parts of the sea,

10 even there, your hand will lead me forth, and your right hand will hold me.

11 And I said: Perhaps darkness will overwhelm me, and the night will be my illumination, to my delight.

12 But darkness will not be impenetrable to you, and night will illuminate like the day: for just as its darkness is, so also is its light.

13 For you have possessed my temperament. You have supported me from the womb of my mother.

14 I will confess to you, for you have been magnified terribly. Your works are miraculous, as my soul knows exceedingly well.

15 My bone, which you have made in secret, has not been hidden from you, and my substance is in accord with the lower parts of the earth.

16 Your eyes saw my imperfection, and all this shall be written in your book. Days will be formed, and no one shall be in them.

17 But to me, O God, your friends have been greatly honored. Their first ruler has been exceedingly strengthened.

18 I will number them, and they will be more numerous than the sand. I rose up, and I am still with you.

19 O God, if only you would cut down sinners. You men of blood: depart from me.

20 For you say in thought: They will accept your cities in vain.

21 Have I not hated those who hated you, Lord, and wasted away because of your enemies?

22 I have hated them with a perfect hatred, and they have become enemies to me.

23 Examine me, O God, and know my heart. Question me, and know my paths.

24 And see if there might be in me the way of iniquity, and lead me in the way of eternity.

Psalms 139

1 Unto the end. A Psalm of David.

2 Rescue me, O Lord, from the evil man. Rescue me from the iniquitous leader.

3 Those who have devised iniquities in their hearts: all day long they constructed conflicts.

4 They have sharpened their tongues like a serpent. The venom of asps is under their lips.

5 Preserve me, O Lord, from the hand of the sinner, and rescue me from men of iniquity. They have decided to supplant my steps.

6 The arrogant have hidden a snare for me. And they have stretched out cords for a snare. They have placed a stumbling block for me near the road.

7 I said to the Lord: You are my God. O Lord, heed the voice of my supplication.

8 Lord, O Lord, the strength of my salvation: you have overshadowed my head in the day of war.

9 O Lord, do not hand me over to the sinner by my desire. They have plotted against me. Do not abandon me, lest they should triumph.

10 The head of those who encompass me, the labor of their lips, will overwhelm them.

11 Burning coals will fall upon them. You will cast them down into the fire, into miseries that they will not be able to withstand.

12 A talkative man will not be guided aright upon the earth. Evils will drag the unjust man unto utter ruin.

13 I know that the Lord will accomplish justice for the needy and vindication for the poor.

14 So then, truly, the just will confess your name, and the upright will dwell with your countenance.

Psalms 140

1 A Psalm of David. O Lord, I have cried out to you, hear me. Attend to my voice, when I cry out to you.

2 Let my prayer be guided like incense in your sight: the lifting up of my hands, like the evening sacrifice.

3 O Lord, station a guard over my mouth and a door enclosing my lips.

4 Do not turn aside my heart to words of malice, to making excuses for sins, with men who work iniquity; and I will not communicate, even with the best of them.

5 The just one will correct me with mercy, and he will rebuke me. But do not allow the oil of the sinner to fatten my head. For my prayer will still be toward their good will.

6 Their judges have been engulfed, joined to the rocks. They will hear my words, which have prevailed,

7 as when the lava of the earth has erupted above ground. Our bones have been scattered beside Hell.

8 For Lord, O Lord, my eyes look to you. In you, I have hoped. Do not take away my soul.

9 Protect me from the snare that they have set up for me and from the scandals of those who work iniquity.

10 The sinners will fall into his net. I am alone, until I pass over.

Psalms 142

1 A Psalm of David, when his son Absalom was pursuing him. O Lord, hear my prayer. Incline your ear to my supplication in your truth. Heed me according to your justice.

2 And do not enter into judgment with your servant. For all the living will not be justified in your sight.

3 For the enemy has pursued my soul. He has lowered my life to the earth. He has stationed me in darkness, like the dead of ages past.

4 And my spirit has been in anguish over me. My heart within me has been disturbed.

5 I have called to mind the days of antiquity. I have been meditating on all your works. I have meditated on the workings of your hands.

6 I have extended my hands to you. My soul is like a land without water before you.

7 O Lord, heed me quickly. My spirit has grown faint. Do not turn your face away from me, lest I become like those who descend into the pit.

8 Make me hear your mercy in the morning. For I have hoped in you. Make known to me the way that I should walk. For I have lifted up my soul to you.

9 O Lord, rescue me from my enemies. I have fled to you.

10 Teach me to do your will. For you are my God. Your good Spirit will lead me into the righteous land.

11 For the sake of your name, O Lord, you will revive me in your fairness. You will lead my soul out of tribulation.

12 And you will scatter my enemies in your mercy. And you will destroy all those who afflict my soul. For I am your servant.

Psalms 143

1 A Psalm of David versus Goliath. Blessed is the Lord, my God, who trains my hands for the battle and my fingers for the war.

2 My mercy and my refuge, my supporter and my deliverer, my protector and him in whom I have hoped: he subdues my people under me.

3 O Lord, what is man that you have become known to him? Or the son of man that you consider him?

4 Man has been made similar to vanity. His days pass by like a shadow.

5 O Lord, incline your heavens and descend. Touch the mountains, and they will smoke.

6 Send a flash of lightning, and you will scatter them. Shoot your arrows, and you will set them in disarray.

7 Send forth your hand from on high: rescue me, and free me from many waters, from the hand of the sons of foreigners.

8 Their mouth has been speaking vain things, and their right hand is the right hand of iniquity.

9 To you, O God, I will sing a new song. On the psaltery, with an instrument of ten strings, I will sing psalms to you.

10 He gives salvation to kings. He has redeemed your servant David from the malignant sword.

11 Rescue me, and deliver me from the hand of the sons of foreigners. Their mouth has been speaking vain things, and their right hand is the right hand of iniquity.

12 Their sons are like new plantings in their youth. Their daughters are dressed up: adorned all around like the idols of a temple.

13 Their cupboards are full: overflowing from one thing into another. Their sheep bear young, brought forth in abundance.

14 Their cattle are fat. There is no ruined wall or passage, nor anyone crying out in their streets.

15 They have called the people that has these things: blessed. But blessed is the people whose God is the Lord.

Psalms 144

1 The Praise of David himself. I will extol you, O God, my king. And I will bless your name, in this time and forever and ever.

2 Throughout every single day, I will bless you. And I will praise your name, in this time and forever and ever.

3 The Lord is great and exceedingly praiseworthy. And there is no end to his greatness.

4 Generation after generation will praise your works, and they will declare your power.

5 They will tell of the magnificent glory of your sanctity. And they will discourse of your wonders.

6 And they will talk about the virtue of your terrible acts. And they will describe your greatness.

7 They will shout about the memory of your abundant sweetness. And they will exult in your justice.

8 The Lord is compassionate and merciful, patient and full of mercy.

9 The Lord is sweet to all things, and his compassion is upon all his works.

10 O Lord, may all your works confess to you, and let your holy ones bless you.

11 They will speak of the glory of your kingdom, and they will declare your power,

12 so as to make known to the sons of men your power and the glory of your magnificent kingdom.

13 Your kingdom is a kingdom for all ages, and your dominion is with all, from generation to generation. The Lord is faithful in all his words and holy in all his works.

14 The Lord lifts up all who have fallen down, and he sets upright all who have been thrown down.

15 O Lord, all eyes hope in you, and you provide their food in due time.

16 You open your hand, and you fill every kind of animal with a blessing.

17 The Lord is just in all his ways and holy in all his works.

18 The Lord is near to all who call upon him, to all who call upon him in truth.

19 He will do the will of those who fear him, and he will heed their supplication and accomplish their salvation.

20 The Lord watches over all who love him. And he will destroy all sinners.

21 My mouth will speak the praise of the Lord, and may all flesh bless his holy name, in this time and forever and ever.

Psalms 148

1 Alleluia. Praise the Lord from the heavens. Praise him on the heights.

2 Praise him, all his Angels. Praise him, all his hosts.

3 Praise him, sun and moon. Praise him, all stars and light.

4 Praise him, heavens of the heavens. And let all the waters that are above the heavens

5 praise the name of the Lord. For he spoke, and they became. He commanded, and they were created.

6 He has stationed them in eternity, and for age after age. He has established a precept, and it will not pass away.

7 Praise the Lord from the earth: you dragons and all deep places,

8 fire, hail, snow, ice, windstorms, which do his word,

9 mountains and all hills, fruitful trees and all cedars,

10 wild beasts and all cattle, serpents and feathered flying things,

11 kings of the earth and all peoples, leaders and all judges of the earth,

12 young men and virgins. Let the older men with the younger men, praise the name of the Lord.

13 For his name alone is exalted.

14 Confession of him is beyond heaven and earth, and he has exalted the horn of his people. A hymn to all his holy ones, to the sons of Israel, to a people close to him. Alleluia.

Proverbs 1

1 The parables of Solomon, son of David, king of Israel,

2 in order to know wisdom and discipline,

3 to understand words of prudence, and to accept the instruction of doctrine, justice and judgment, and equity,

4 so as to give discernment to little ones, knowledge and understanding to adolescents.

5 By listening, the wise shall become wiser and the intelligent shall possess governments.

6 He shall turn his soul to a parable and to its interpretation, to the words of the wise and their enigmas.

7 The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom. The foolish despise wisdom as well as doctrine.

8 Listen, my son, to the discipline of your father, and forsake not the law of your mother,

9 so that grace may be added to your head and a collar to your neck.

10 My son, if sinners should entice you, do not consent to them.

11 If they should say: "Come with us. We will lie in wait for blood. We will lay traps against the innocent, without cause.

12 Let us swallow him alive, like Hell, and whole, like one descending into the pit.

13 We will discover every precious substance. We will fill our houses with spoils.

14 Cast your lot with us. One purse will be for us all."

15 My son, do not walk with them. Preclude your feet from their paths.

16 For their feet rush to evil, and they hurry to shed blood.

17 But a net is thrown in vain before the eyes of those who have wings.

18 Likewise, they lie in ambush against their own blood, and they undertake deceits against their own souls.

19 Thus, the ways of all those who are greedy seize the souls of those who possess.

20 Wisdom forewarns far and wide; she bestows her voice in the streets.

21 She cries out at the head of crowds; at the entrance of the gates of the city, she offers her words, saying:

22 "Little ones, how long will you choose to be childish, and how long will the foolish desire what is harmful to themselves, and how long will the imprudent hate knowledge?

23 Be converted by my correction. Lo, I will offer my spirit to you, and I will reveal my words to you.

24 For I called, and you refused. I extended my hand, and there was no one who watched.

25 You have despised all my counsels, and you have neglected my rebukes.

26 Similarly, I will ridicule you at your demise, and I will mock you, when that which you feared shall overcome you.

27 When sudden calamity rushes upon you, and your demise advances like a tempest, when tribulation and anguish overcome you,

28 then they will call to me, and I will not heed, they will arise in the morning, and not find me.

29 For they held hatred for discipline, and they would not accept the fear of the Lord;

30 they would not consent to my counsel, but they detracted from all of my corrections.

31 Therefore, they shall eat the fruit of their way, and they shall have their fill of their own counsels.

32 The loathing of the little ones shall destroy them, and the prosperity of the foolish shall perish them.

33 But whoever will listen to me shall rest without terror, and shall have full enjoyment of abundance, without fear of evils."

Proverbs 2

1 My son, if you would accept my words, and conceal my commandments within you,

2 so that your ears may listen to wisdom, then bend your heart in order to know prudence.

3 For if you would call upon wisdom and bend your heart to prudence,

4 if you will seek her like money, and dig for her as if for treasure,

5 then you will understand the fear of the Lord, and you will discover the knowledge of God.

6 For the Lord bestows wisdom, and out of his mouth, prudence and knowledge.

7 He will preserve the salvation of the righteous, and he will protect those who walk in simplicity:

8 serving the paths of justice, and guarding the ways of sanctity.

9 Then you shall understand justice and judgment, and equity, and every good path.

10 If wisdom is to enter into your heart, and if knowledge is to become pleasing to your soul,

11 then counsel must guard you, and prudence must serve you,

12 so that you may be rescued from the evil way, and from the man who speaks perversities,

13 from those who leave the straight path to walk in dark ways,

14 who rejoice when they have done evil, and who exult in the most wicked things.

15 Their ways are perverse, and their steps are infamous.

16 So may you be rescued from the foreign woman, and from the outsider, who softens her speech,

17 and who leaves behind the Guide of her youth,

18 and who has forgotten the covenant of her God. For her household inclines toward death, and her paths toward Hell.

19 All those who enter to her will not return again, nor will they take hold of the paths of life.

20 So may you walk in the good way, and keep to the difficult paths of the just.

21 For those who are upright shall live upon the earth, and the simple shall continue upon it.

22 Yet truly, the impious shall perish from the earth, and those who act unjustly shall be taken away from it.

Proverbs 3

1 My son, do not forget my law, but let your heart guard my precepts.

2 For they shall set before you length of days, and years of life, and peace.

3 Let not mercy and truth abandon you: encircle them around your throat, and inscribe them on the tablets of your heart.

4 And so shall you discover grace and good discipline, in the sight of God and men.

5 Have confidence in the Lord with all your heart, and do not depend upon your own prudence.

6 In all your ways, consider him, and he himself will direct your steps.

7 Do not seem wise to yourself. Fear God, and withdraw from evil.

8 Certainly, it shall be health to your navel, and refreshment to your bones.

9 Honor the Lord with your substance, and give to him from the first of all your fruits,

10 and then your storehouses will be filled with abundance, and your presses shall overflow with wine.

11 My son, do not discard the discipline of the Lord, and do not fall away when you are corrected by him.

12 For whomever the Lord loves, he corrects, and just as a father does with a son, he wins him over.

13 Blessed is the man who finds wisdom and who advances to prudence.

14 Her acquisition is better than trading in silver, and her fruit is better than the first and purest gold.

15 She is more precious than all riches, and all that can be desired cannot prevail in comparison to her.

16 Length of days is at her right hand, and at her left hand is wealth and glory.

17 Her ways are beautiful ways, and all her paths are peaceful.

18 She is a tree of life to those who overtake her, and he who shall take hold of her is blessed.

19 The Lord founded the earth on wisdom. He secured the heavens with prudence.

20 By his wisdom, the abyss erupted and the clouds increased with dew.

21 My son, let not these things move away from your eyes. Preserve law as well as counsel.

22 And so shall there be life in your soul and grace in your voice.

23 Then you shall walk confidently in your way, and your feet will not stumble.

24 When you slumber, you shall not fear. When you rest, your sleep also will be sweet.

25 Do not fear unexpected terror, nor the power of the impious falling upon you.

26 For the Lord will be at your side, and he will guard your feet, so that you may not be seized.

27 Do not prevent him who is able from doing good. When you are able, do good yourself too.

28 Do not say to your friend: "Go away, and then return. Tomorrow I will give to you." When you are able to do so, give in the present.

29 Do not undertake evil against your friend, even though he has trust in you.

30 Do not contend against a man without cause, even though he has done no evil to you.

31 Do not rival an unjust man, and do not imitate his ways.

32 For everyone who ridicules is an abomination to the Lord, and his communication is for the simple.

33 Destitution in the house of the impious is from the Lord. But the habitations of the just shall be blessed.

34 He will ridicule those who ridicule, but he will bestow grace upon the mild.

35 The wise will possess glory. The exaltation of the foolish is disgraceful.

Proverbs 4

1 Listen, sons, to the discipline of a father, and pay attention, so that you may know prudence.

2 I will bestow upon you a good gift. Do not relinquish my law.

3 For I, too, was the son of my father, tender and an only son in the sight of my mother.

4 And he taught me, and he also said: "Let your heart accept my words. Keep my precepts, and you shall live.

5 Obtain wisdom, obtain prudence. May you neither forget, nor turn away from, the words of my mouth.

6 Do not send her away, and she will guard you. Love her, and she will preserve you.

7 The beginning of wisdom is to obtain wisdom, and, with all that you possess, to acquire prudence.

8 Grasp her, and she will exalt you. You will be glorified by her, when you have embraced her.

9 She will bestow upon your head an increase in graces, and she will protect you with a noble crown.

10 Listen, my son, and accept my words, so that years of life may be multiplied for you.

11 I will demonstrate to you the way of wisdom. I will lead you along the paths of equity.

12 When you have entered by these, your steps will not be constrained, and when running, you will have no obstacle.

13 Take hold of discipline. Do not dismiss it. Guard it, for it is your life.

14 Do not delight in the paths of the impious, nor permit the way of evil-doers to please you.

15 Take flight from it. Do not pass close to it. Turn away and abandon it.

16 For they do not sleep, unless they have done evil. And their sleep is quickly taken away from them, unless they have overthrown.

17 They eat the bread of impiety, and they drink the wine of iniquity.

18 But the path of the just is like a shining light: it advances and increases, even to the day of completion.

19 The way of the impious is darkened. They do not know where they may fall.

20 My son, pay attention to my sermons, and incline your ear to my eloquent words.

21 Let them not recede from your eyes. Keep them in the midst of your heart.

22 For they are life to those who find them and health to all that is flesh.

23 Preserve your heart with all watchfulness, for life proceeds from this.

24 Remove from yourself a corrupt mouth, and let detracting lips be far from you.

25 Let your eyes look straight ahead, and let your eyelids precede your steps.

26 Direct the path of your feet, and all your ways shall be secure.

27 Turn aside, neither to the right, nor to the left; yet turn your foot away from evil. For the Lord knows the ways that are on the right, and truly, those that are on the left are perverse. But he himself will make your courses straight. Then your journey will advance in peace.

Proverbs 5

1 My son, pay attention to my wisdom, and incline your ear to my prudence,

2 so that you may guard your thinking, and so that your lips may preserve discipline. Do not pay attention to the deceit of a woman.

3 For the lips of a loose woman are like a dripping honeycomb, and her voice is smoother than oil.

4 But in the end, she is as bitter as wormwood, and as sharp as a two-edged sword.

5 Her feet descend into death, and her steps reach even to Hell.

6 They do not walk along the path of life; her steps are wandering and untraceable.

7 Therefore, my son, listen to me now, and do not withdraw from the words of my mouth.

8 Make your way at a distance from her, and do not approach the doors of her house.

9 Do not give your honor to foreigners, and your years to the cruel.

10 Otherwise, outsiders may be filled with your strength, and your labors may be in a foreign house,

11 and you may mourn in the end, when you will have consumed your flesh and your body. And so you may say:

12 "Why have I detested discipline, and why has my heart not been quieted by correction?

13 And why have I not listened to the voice of those who guided me? And why has my ear not inclined to my teachers?

14 I have almost been with all evil in the midst of the church and of the assembly."

15 Drink water from your own cistern and from the springs of your own well.

16 Let your fountains be diverted far and wide, and divide your waters in the streets.

17 Hold them for yourself alone, and do not let strangers be partakers with you.

18 Let your spring be blessed, and rejoice with the wife of your youth:

19 a beloved doe and most pleasing fawn. Let her breasts inebriate you at all times. Be delighted continually by her love.

20 Why are you seduced, my son, by a strange woman, and why are you kept warm by the bosom of another?

21 The Lord beholds the ways of man, and he considers all his steps.

22 His own iniquities take hold of the impious, and he is bound by the cords of his own sins.

23 He shall die, for he has not held to discipline. And by the multitude of his foolishness, he shall be deceived.

Proverbs 6

1 My son, if you have taken a pledge on behalf of your friend, then you have bound your hand to an outsider,

2 then you are ensnared by the words of your own mouth, and taken captive by your own words.

3 Therefore, my son, do what I say, and free yourself, for you have fallen into the hand of your neighbor. Run, hurry, awaken your friend.

4 Do not grant sleep to your eyes, nor let your eyelids slumber.

5 Rescue yourself like a gazelle from the hand, and like a bird from the hand of the fowler.

6 Go to the ant, you lazy one, and consider her ways, and so learn wisdom.

7 For though she has no ruler, nor instructor, nor leader,

8 she provides meals for herself in the summer, and she gathers at the harvest what she may eat.

9 How long will you slumber, you lazy one? When will you rise up from your sleep?

10 You will sleep a little, you will slumber a little, you will fold your hands a little to sleep,

11 and then destitution will meet with you, like a traveler, and poverty, like an armed man. Yet truly, if you would be diligent, then your harvest will arrive like a fountain, and destitution will flee far from you.

12 An apostate man, a harmful man, walks with a perverse mouth;

13 he winks with the eyes, touches with the foot, speaks with the finger.

14 With a depraved heart he devises evil, and at all times he sows conflict.

15 To this one, his perdition will arrive promptly, and he shall be crushed suddenly: he will no longer have any remedy.

16 Six things there are that the Lord hates, and the seventh, his soul detests:

17 haughty eyes, a lying tongue, hands that shed innocent blood,

18 a heart that devises the most wicked thoughts, feet running swiftly unto evil,

19 a deceitful witness bringing forth lies, and he who sows discord among brothers.

20 My son, preserve the precepts of your father, and do not dismiss the law of your mother.

21 Bind them to your heart unceasingly, and encircle them around your throat.

22 When you walk, let them keep step with you. When you sleep, let them guard you. And when you keep watch, speak with them.

23 For commandment is a lamp, and law is a light, and the reproofs of discipline are the way of life.

24 So may they guard you from an evil woman, and from the flattering tongue of the outsider.

25 Let not your heart desire her beauty; do not be captivated by her winks.

26 For the price of a prostitute is only one loaf. Yet the woman seizes the precious soul of a man.

27 Would a man be able to conceal fire in his bosom, so that his garments would not burn?

28 Or could he walk over burning coals, so that his feet would not be burned?

29 So also, he who enters to the wife of his neighbor shall not be clean when he touches her.

30 Not so great is the fault when someone has stolen. For he steals so as to satisfy a hungry soul.

31 Also, if he is apprehended, he shall repay sevenfold and hand over all the substance of his house.

32 But whoever is an adulterer, because of the emptiness of his heart, will destroy his own soul.

33 He gathers shame and dishonor to himself, and his disgrace will not be wiped away.

34 For the jealousy and fury of the husband will not spare him on the day of vindication,

35 nor will he agree to the pleadings of anyone, nor will he accept, as repayment, a multitude of gifts.

Proverbs 7

1 My son, guard my words and conceal my precepts within you.

2 Son, preserve my commandments, and you shall live. And keep my law as the pupil of your eye.

3 Bind it with your fingers; write it on the tablets of your heart.

4 Say to wisdom, "You are my sister," and call prudence your friend.

5 So may she guard you from the woman who is an outsider, and from the stranger who sweetens her words.

6 For I gaze from the window of my house, through the lattice,

7 and I see little ones. I consider a frenzied youth,

8 who crosses the street at the corner and close to the way of that house.

9 He steps into shadows, as day becomes evening, into the darkness and gloom of the night.

10 And behold, a woman meets him, dressed like a harlot, prepared to captivate souls: chattering and rambling,

11 unwilling to bear silence, unable to keep her feet at home,

12 now outside, now in the streets, now lying in ambush near the corners.

13 And overtaking the youth, she kisses him, and with a provocative face, she flatters him, saying:

14 "I vowed sacrifices for well-being. Today I have repaid my vows.

15 Because of this, I have gone out to meet you, desiring to see you, and I have found you.

16 I have woven my bed with cords. I have strewn it with embroidered tapestries from Egypt.

17 I have sprinkled my bed with myrrh, aloe, and cinnamon.

18 Come, let us be inebriated in abundance, and let us delight in the embraces of desire, until the day begins to dawn.

19 For my husband is not in his house. He has gone away on a very long journey.

20 He took with him a bag of money. He will return to his house on the day of the full moon."

21 She enmeshed him with many words, and she drew him forward with the flattery of her lips.

22 Immediately, he follows her, like an ox being led to the sacrifice, and like a lamb acting lasciviously, and not knowing that he is being drawn foolishly into chains,

23 until the arrow pierces his liver. It is just as if a bird were to hurry into the snare. And he does not know that his actions endanger his own soul.

24 Therefore, my son, hear me now, and attend to the words of my mouth.

25 Do not let your mind be pulled into her ways. And do not be deceived by her paths.

26 For she has tossed aside many wounded, and some of those who were very strong have been slain by her.

27 Her household is the way to Hell, reaching even to the inner places of death.

Proverbs 8

1 Does not wisdom call out, and prudence bestow her voice?

2 At the summits and the tops of exalted places, standing above the ways, in the midst of the paths,

3 beside the gates of the city, at the very doors, she speaks, saying:

4 "O men, to you I call out, and my voice is to the sons of men.

5 O little ones, understand discernment. And you who are unwise, turn your souls.

6 Listen, for I will speak about great things, and my lips will be opened, so as to foretell what is right.

7 My throat shall practice truth, and my lips shall detest the impious.

8 All my words are just. There is no depravity in them, and no perversity.

9 They are upright to those who understand, and equitable to those who discover knowledge.

10 Accept my discipline, and not money. Choose the doctrine that is greater than gold.

11 For wisdom is better than all that is most precious, and everything that is desirable cannot compare to her.

12 I, wisdom, dwell in counsel, and I am inside learned thoughts.

13 The fear of the Lord hates evil. I detest arrogance, and pride, and every wicked way, and a mouth with a double tongue.

14 Counsel is mine, and equity. Prudence is mine. Strength is mine.

15 Through me, kings reign and legislators decree just conditions.

16 Through me, princes rule and the powerful decree justice.

17 I love those who love me. And those who stand watch for me until morning shall discover me.

18 With me, are wealth and glory, superb riches and justice.

19 For my fruit is better than gold and precious stones, and my progeny better than choice silver.

20 I walk in the way of justice, in the midst of the paths of judgment,

21 so that I may enrich those who love me, and thus complete their treasures.

22 The Lord possessed me in the beginning of his ways, before he made anything, from the beginning.

23 I was ordained from eternity, and out of antiquity, before the earth was formed.

24 The abyss did not yet exist, and I was already conceived; neither had the fountains of waters yet erupted.

25 The mountains, with their great mass, had not yet been established. Before the hills, I was brought forth.

26 Still he had not made the earth, and the rivers, and the poles of the globe of the earth.

27 I was already present: when he prepared the heavens; when, with a certain law and a circuit, he fortified the abyss;

28 when he made firm the sky above, and set free the fountains of waters;

29 when he encompassed the sea within its limits, and laid down a law for the waters, lest they transgress their limits; when he weighed the foundations of the earth.

30 I was with him in composing all things. And I was delighted, throughout every day, by playing in his sight at all times,

31 playing in globe of the earth. And my delight was to be with the sons of men.

32 Therefore, sons, hear me now. Blessed are those who preserve my ways.

33 Listen to discipline, and become wise, and do not be willing to cast it aside.

34 Blessed is the man who listens to me, and who stands watch at my gates everyday, and who observes at the posts of my doors.

35 He who finds me, finds life, and he will draw salvation from the Lord.

36 But he who sins against me will wound his own soul. All who hate me love death."

Proverbs 9

1 Wisdom has built a house for herself. She has hewn seven columns.

2 She has immolated her victims. She has mixed her wine and set forth her table.

3 She has sent her maids to call out to the tower and to the fortified walls of the city,

4 "If anyone is little, let him come to me." And to the unwise, she has said:

5 "Approach. Eat my bread, and drink the wine that I have mixed for you.

6 Leave behind childishness. And live and walk by the ways of prudence."

7 Whoever teaches a mocker causes injury to himself. And whoever argues with the impious produces a blemish on himself.

8 Do not be willing to argue with a mocker, lest he hate you. Dispute with the wise, and he will love you.

9 Present an opportunity to the wise, and wisdom shall be added to him. Teach the just, and he will hurry to receive it.

10 The fear of the Lord is the beginning of wisdom, and knowledge of holiness is prudence.

11 For by me, your days will be multiplied and years of life will be added to you.

12 If you would be wise, you will be so for yourself. But if you would be one who ridicules, you alone shall carry the evil.

13 A foolish and loud woman, who is full of enticements and who knows nothing at all,

14 sat at the entrance of her house on a seat, in a high place of the city,

15 so as to call to those who were passing by the way and continuing on their journey:

16 "Whoever is little, let him turn aside to me." And to the frenzied, she said,

17 "Stolen waters are more soothing, and secret bread is more pleasant."

18 And he did not know that giants are there, and that her companions are in the depths of Hell.

Proverbs 10

1 A wise son gladdens the father. Yet truly, a foolish son is the grief of his mother.

2 Treasures of impiety will profit nothing. Truly, justice shall liberate from death.

3 The Lord will not afflict with famine the soul of the just, and he will overthrow the treacheries of the impious.

4 The neglectful hand has wrought destitution. But the hand of the steadfast prepares riches. He who advances by lies, this one feeds on the wind. For he is the same as one who runs after flying birds.

5 He who gathers the harvest is a wise son. But he who snores in warm weather is a son of confusion.

6 The blessing of the Lord is on the head of the just. But iniquity covers the mouth of the impious.

7 The remembrance of the just is with praises. And the name of the impious shall decay.

8 The wise of heart accept precepts. The foolish are cut down by the lips.

9 He who walks in simplicity walks in confidence. But he who corrupts his ways shall be discovered.

10 He who winks with the eye gives sorrow. And the foolish in lips shall be beaten.

11 The mouth of the just is a vein of life. And the mouth of the impious covers iniquity.

12 Hatred rises up from disputes. And charity covers all offenses.

13 In the lips of the wise, wisdom is discovered. And a rod is for the back of one who lacks heart.

14 The wise store away knowledge. But the mouth of the foolish is a neighbor to confusion.

15 The substance of the rich is the city of his strength. The fear of the poor is their destitution.

16 The work of the just is unto life. But the fruit of the impious is unto sin.

17 The way of life is for those who observe discipline. But whoever abandons correction wanders astray.

18 Lying lips conceal hatred; whoever brings forth contempt is unwise.

19 In a multitude of speaking, sin will not be lacking. But whoever tempers his lips is most prudent.

20 The tongue of the just is choice silver. But the heart of the impious is exchanged for nothing.

21 The lips of the just instruct many. But those who are unlearned shall die in destitution of heart.

22 The blessing of the Lord causes riches. Affliction will not be a companion to them.

23 The foolish work wickedness as if in jest. But wisdom is prudence to a man.

24 What the impious fear will overwhelm them. The just shall be given their desire.

25 Like a passing tempest, so the impious one will be no more. But the just one is like an everlasting foundation.

26 Like vinegar to the teeth, and smoke to the eyes, so is a lazy one to those who sent him.

27 The fear of the Lord adds days. And the years of the impious will be shortened.

28 The expectation of the just is rejoicing. But the hope of the impious will perish.

29 The strength of the simple is the way of the Lord, and it is fear to those who work evil.

30 The just in eternity shall not be moved. But the impious will not live upon the earth.

31 The mouth of the just shall bring forth wisdom. The tongue of the depraved will perish.

32 The lips of the just consider what is acceptable. And the mouth of the impious considers perversities.

Proverbs 11

1 A deceitful scale is an abomination with the Lord, and a fair weighing is his will.

2 Wherever arrogance may be, there too is insult. But wherever humility is, there too is wisdom.

3 The simplicity of the just shall direct them, and the rebellion of the perverse will devastate them.

4 Wealth will not profit in the day of vengeance. But justice shall liberate from death.

5 The justice of the simple shall direct his way. And the impious will fall in his impiety.

6 The justice of the upright shall free them. And the iniquitous will be seized by their own treachery.

7 When the impious man is dead, there will no longer be any hope. And the expectation of the anxious will perish.

8 The just one is freed from anguish. And the impious one will be handed over instead of him.

9 The pretender deceives his friend by mouth. But the just shall be freed by knowledge.

10 In the good of the just, the city shall exult. And in the perdition of the impious, there shall be praise.

11 By the blessing of the just, the city shall be exalted. And by the mouth of the impious, it will be subverted.

12 Whoever despises his friend is destitute in heart. But the prudent man will remain silent.

13 Whoever walks dishonestly reveals secrets. But whoever is of a faithful soul conceals what is confided by a friend.

14 Where there is no governor, the people shall fall. But where there is much counsel, well-being shall be.

15 He will be afflicted with evil, who provides a guarantee for an outsider. But whoever is wary of traps shall be secure.

16 A gracious woman shall discover glory. And the robust will have wealth.

17 A merciful man benefits his own soul. But whoever is cruel casts out even his close relatives.

18 The impious does work with inconstancy. But for the sower of justice, there is the reward of faithfulness.

19 Clemency prepares life. And the pursuit of evils prepares death.

20 A depraved heart is abominable to the Lord. And his will is with those who walk in simplicity.

21 Hand in hand, the evil shall not be innocent. But the offspring of the just shall be saved.

22 A beautiful and senseless woman is like a gold ring in the snout of a swine.

23 The desire of the just is entirely good. The anticipation of the impious is fury.

24 Some distribute their own goods, and they become wealthier. Others seize what is not their own, and they are always in need.

25 The soul that blesses shall be made fat. And whoever inebriates will likewise be inebriated himself.

26 Whoever hides away grain shall be cursed among the people. But a blessing is upon the head of those who sell it.

27 He does well to rise early, who seeks what is good. But whoever is a seeker of evils shall be oppressed by them.

28 Whoever trusts in his riches will fall. But the just shall spring up like a green leaf.

29 Whoever troubles his own house will possess the winds. And whoever is foolish will serve the wise.

30 The fruit of the just one is the tree of life. And whoever receives souls is wise.

31 If the just are repaid upon the earth, how much more the impious and the sinner!

Proverbs 12

1 Whoever loves discipline loves knowledge. But whoever hates correction is unwise.

2 Whoever is good shall draw grace from the Lord. But whoever trusts in his own thoughts acts impiously.

3 Man will not be made strong from impiety. And the root of the just shall not be moved.

4 A diligent woman is a crown to her husband. And she who acts with confusion as to which things are worthy is decay to his bones.

5 The thoughts of the just are judgments. And the counsels of the impious are dishonest.

6 The words of the impious lie in wait for blood. The mouth of the just shall free them.

7 Turn from the impious, and they will not be. But the house of the just shall stand firm.

8 A man will be known by his doctrine. But whoever is vain and heartless will suffer contempt.

9 Better is a pauper who has what he needs, than someone glorious and in need of bread.

10 The just one knows the lives of his beasts. But the inner most parts of the impious are cruel.

11 Whoever works his land shall be satisfied with bread. But whoever continually pursues leisure is most foolish. Whoever is soothed by lingering over wine leaves behind contempt in his strongholds.

12 The desire of the impious is the fortification of what is most wicked. But the root of the just shall prosper.

13 For the sins of the lips draw ruin to the evil. But the just shall escape from distress.

14 By the fruit of his own mouth, each one shall be filled with good things, and according to the works of his own hands, it will be distributed to him.

15 The way of the foolish is right in his own eyes. But whoever is wise listens to counsels.

16 The senseless immediately reveals his anger. But whoever ignores injuries is clever.

17 He is a sign of justice, who speaks what he knows. But whoever deceives is a dishonest witness.

18 He who makes promises is also jabbed, as if with a sword, in conscience. But the tongue of the wise is reasonable.

19 The lips of truth shall be steadfast forever. But a hasty witness readies a lying tongue.

20 Deceit is in the heart of those who devise evils. But gladness follows those who take up counsels of peace.

21 Whatever may befall the just, it will not discourage him. But the impious will be filled with disasters.

22 Lying lips are an abomination to the Lord. But whoever acts faithfully pleases him.

23 A resourceful man conceals knowledge. And the heart of the unwise provokes foolishness.

24 The hand of the strong will rule. But anyone who is neglectful will pay tribute.

25 Grief in the heart of a man humbles him. And with a good word he shall be made glad.

26 He who ignores a loss for the sake of a friend is just. But the way of the impious will deceive them.

27 The dishonest will not discover gain. But the substance of a man will be like precious gold.

28 In the path of justice, there is life. But the devious way leads to death.

Proverbs 13

1 A wise son is the doctrine of his father. But he who ridicules does not listen when he is reproved.

2 From the fruit of his own month, a man shall be satisfied with good things. But the soul of betrayers is iniquity.

3 Whoever guards his mouth guards his soul. But whoever gives no consideration to his speech shall experience misfortunes.

4 The lazy one is willing and then not willing. But the soul of he who labors shall be made fat.

5 The just shall detest a lying word. But the impious confound and will be confounded.

6 Justice guards the way of the innocent. But impiety undermines the sinner.

7 One is like the rich, though he has nothing. And another is like the poor, though he has many riches.

8 The redemption of a man's life is his riches. But he who is poor cannot tolerate correction.

9 The light of the just enriches. But the lamp of the impious will be extinguished.

10 Among the arrogant, there are always conflicts. But those who do everything with counsel are ruled by wisdom.

11 Substance obtained in haste will be diminished. But what is collected by hand, little by little, shall be multiplied.

12 Hope, when it is delayed, afflicts the soul. The arrival of the desired is a tree of life.

13 Whoever denounces something obligates himself for the future. But whoever fears a lesson shall turn away in peace. Deceitful souls wander into sins. The just are merciful and compassionate.

14 The law of the wise is a fountain of life, so that he may turn aside from the ruin of death.

15 Good doctrine bestows grace. In the way of the contemptuous, there is a chasm.

16 The discerning do everything with counsel. But whoever is senseless discloses his stupidity.

17 The messenger of the impious will fall into evil. But a faithful ambassador shall prosper.

18 Destitution and disgrace are for those who abandon discipline. But whoever agrees with a reproof shall be glorified.

19 The desired, when perfected, shall delight the soul. The foolish detest those who flee from evils.

20 Whoever keeps step with the wise shall be wise. A friend of the foolish will become like them.

21 Evil pursues sinners. And good things shall be distributed to the just.

22 The good leave behind heirs: children and grandchildren. And the substance of the sinner is preserved for the just.

23 Much nourishment is in the fallow land of the fathers. But for others, it is gathered without judgment.

24 He who spares the rod hates his son. But he who loves him urgently instructs him.

25 The just eats and fills his soul. But the belly of the impious is never satisfied.

Proverbs 14

1 A wise woman builds up her household. But a foolish one will pull down with her own hands what has been built up.

2 One who walks on a virtuous journey, and who fears God, is despised by him who advances along a disreputable way.

3 In the mouth of the foolish, there is a rod of arrogance. But the lips of the wise guard them.

4 Where there are no oxen, the feeding trough is empty. But where there are many crops, there the strength of the ox is manifest.

5 A faithful witness will not lie. But a deceitful witness offers a lie.

6 A mocker seeks wisdom and does not find it. The doctrine of the prudent is accessible.

7 Go against a foolish man, and he does not acknowledge lips of prudence.

8 The wisdom of a discerning man is to understand his way. And the imprudence of the foolish is to be wandering astray.

9 The foolish will speak mockingly of sin. But grace lingers among the just.

10 The heart that knows the bitterness of its own soul, in its gladness the outsider shall not meddle.

11 The house of the impious will be wiped away. Yet truly, the tabernacles of the just shall spring forth.

12 There is a way which seems just to a man, but its conclusion leads to death.

13 Laughter shall be mingled with sorrow, and mourning occupies the limits of joy.

14 The foolish will be filled up by his own ways. And the good man shall be above him.

15 The innocent trust every word. The astute one considers his own steps. Nothing good will be for the deceitful son. But the wise servant shall act prosperously and his way will be set in order.

16 The wise fear, and so turn away from evil. The foolish leap ahead with confidence.

17 The impatient will work foolishness. And a resourceful man is hated.

18 The childish will possess foolishness, and the discerning will anticipate knowledge.

19 The evil will fall down before the good. And the impious will fall down before the gates of the just.

20 The pauper will be hated, even by his own neighbor. Yet truly, the friends of the wealthy are many.

21 Whoever despises his neighbor, sins. But whoever pities the poor shall be blessed. Whoever trusts in the Lord loves mercy.

22 They wander astray who work evil. But mercy and truth prepare good things.

23 In every work, there shall be abundance. But where there are many words, there is often need.

24 The crown of the wise is their wealth. The senselessness of the foolish is imprudence.

25 A faithful witness frees souls. And the chameleon utters lies.

26 In the fear of the Lord is the faithfulness of strength, and there shall be hope for his sons.

27 The fear of the Lord is a fountain of life, so as to turn aside from the ruin of death.

28 In a multitude of people, there is dignity for the king. And in a paucity of people, there is disgrace for the prince.

29 Whoever is patient is governed by much prudence. But whoever is impatient exalts his foolishness.

30 The well-being of the heart is life for the flesh. But envy is decay for the bones.

31 Whoever slanders the indigent argues against his Maker. But he who has compassion on the poor honors his Maker.

32 The impious will be expelled in his malice. But the just finds hope even in his own death.

33 In the heart of the prudent, wisdom finds rest. And so shall he instruct all the uneducated.

34 Justice elevates a nation. But sin makes the peoples miserable.

35 An intelligent minister is acceptable to the king. Whoever is useless shall bear his wrath.

Proverbs 15

1 A mild response shatters anger. But a harsh word stirs up fury.

2 The tongue of the wise adorns knowledge. But the mouth of the senseless gushes with foolishness.

3 In every place, the eyes of the Lord consider good and evil.

4 A peaceful tongue is a tree of life. But that which is immoderate will crush the spirit.

5 A fool laughs at the discipline of his father. But whoever preserves rebukes will become astute. In abundant justice, there is very great virtue. But the intentions of the impious will be eradicated.

6 The house of the just has very great strength. And in the fruits of the impious, there is disorder.

7 The lips of the wise shall disseminate knowledge. The heart of the foolish will be dissimilar.

8 The sacrifices of the impious are abominable to the Lord. The vows of the just are appeasing.

9 The way of the impious is an abomination to the Lord. Whoever pursues justice is loved by him.

10 Doctrine is evil to those who abandon the way of life. Whoever hates correction shall die.

11 Hell and perdition are in the sight of the Lord. How much more the hearts of the sons of men!

12 He who corrupts himself does not love the one who afflicts him, nor will he step toward the wise.

13 A rejoicing heart gladdens the face. But by the grief of the soul, the spirit is cast down.

14 The heart of the wise seeks doctrine. And the mouth of the foolish feeds on ignorance.

15 All the days of the poor are evil. A secure mind is like a continual feast.

16 Better is a little with the fear of the Lord, than great treasures and dissatisfaction.

17 It is better to be called to vegetables with charity, than to a fatted calf with hatred.

18 A short-tempered man provokes conflicts. Whoever is patient tempers those who are stirred up.

19 The way of the slothful is like a hedge of thorns. The way of the just is without offense.

20 A wise son gladdens the father. But the foolish man despises his mother.

21 Folly is gladness to the foolish. And the prudent man sets his own steps in order.

22 Intentions dissipate where there is no counsel. Yet truly, they are confirmed where there are many counselors.

23 A man rejoices in the verdict of his own mouth. And a word at the right time is best.

24 The path of life is for the wise above, so that he may turn away from the end of Hell.

25 The Lord will demolish the house of the arrogant. And He will make firm the borders of the widow.

26 Evil intentions are an abomination to the Lord. And pure conversation, most beautiful, shall be confirmed by him.

27 Whoever pursues avarice disturbs his own house. But whoever hates bribes shall live. Through mercy and faith, sins are purged. But through the fear of the Lord, each one turns aside from evil.

28 The mind of the just meditates on obedience. The mouth of the impious overflows with evils.

29 The Lord is distant from the impious. And he will heed the prayers of the just.

30 The light of the eyes rejoices the soul. A good reputation fattens the bones.

31 The ear that listens to the reproofs of life shall abide in the midst of the wise.

32 Whoever rejects discipline despises his own soul. But whoever agrees to correction is a possessor of the heart.

33 The fear of the Lord is the discipline of wisdom. And humility precedes glory.

Proverbs 16

1 It is for man to prepare the soul, and for the Lord to govern the tongue.

2 All the ways of a man are open to his eyes; the Lord is the one who weighs spirits.

3 Open your works to the Lord, and your intentions will be set in order.

4 The Lord has wrought all things because of himself. Likewise the impious is for the evil day.

5 All the arrogant are an abomination to the Lord. Even if hand will be joined to hand, he is not innocent. The beginning of a good way is to do justice. And this is more acceptable with God than to immolate sacrifices.

6 By mercy and truth, iniquity is redeemed. And by the fear of the Lord, one turns away from evil.

7 When the ways of man will please the Lord, he will convert even his enemies to peace.

8 Better is a little with justice, than many fruits with iniquity.

9 The heart of man disposes his way. But it is for Lord to direct his steps.

10 Foreknowledge is in the lips of the king. His mouth shall not err in judgment.

11 Weights and scales are judgments of the Lord. And all the stones in the bag are his work.

12 Those who act impiously are abominable to the king. For the throne is made firm by justice.

13 Just lips are the will of kings. He who speaks honestly shall be loved.

14 The indignation of a king is a herald of death. And the wise man will appease it.

15 In the cheerfulness of the king's countenance, there is life. And his clemency is like belated rain.

16 Possess wisdom, for it is better than gold. And acquire prudence, for it is more precious than silver.

17 The path of the just turns away from evils. He who guards his soul preserves his way.

18 Arrogance precedes destruction. And the spirit is exalted before a fall.

19 It is better to be humbled with the meek, than to divide spoils with the arrogant.

20 The learned in word shall find good things. And whoever hopes in the Lord is blessed.

21 Whoever is wise in heart shall be called prudent. And whoever is sweet in eloquence shall attain to what is greater.

22 Learning is a fountain of life to one who possesses it. The doctrine of the foolish is senseless.

23 The heart of the wise shall instruct his mouth and add grace to his lips.

24 Careful words are a honeycomb: sweet to the soul and healthful to the bones.

25 There is a way which seems right to a man, and its end result leads to death.

26 The soul of the laborer labors for himself, because his mouth has driven him to it.

27 The impious man digs up evil, and in his lips is a burning fire.

28 A perverse man stirs up lawsuits. And one who is verbose divides leaders.

29 A man of iniquity entices his friend, and he leads him along a way that is not good.

30 Whoever, with astonished eyes, thinks up depravities, biting his lips, accomplishes evil.

31 Old age is a crown of dignity, when it is found in the ways of justice.

32 A patient man is better than a strong one. And whoever rules his soul is better than one who assaults cities.

33 Lots are cast into the lap, but they are tempered by the Lord.

Proverbs 17

1 A dry morsel with gladness is better than a house full of sacrifices along with conflict.

2 A wise servant shall rule over foolish sons, and he will divide the inheritance among brothers.

3 Just as silver is tested by fire, and gold is tested in the furnace, so also does the Lord test hearts.

4 The evil obey an unjust tongue. And the false are submissive to lying lips.

5 Whoever despises the poor rebukes his Maker. And whoever rejoices in the ruin of another will not go unpunished.

6 Sons of sons are the crown of old age. And the glory of sons is their fathers.

7 Well-chosen words are not fitting for the foolish, nor are lying lips fitting for a leader.

8 The expectation of those who stand ready is a most pleasing jewel. Whichever way he turns himself, he understands prudently.

9 Whoever conceals an offense seeks friendships. Whoever repeats the words of another separates allies.

10 A correction benefits more with a wise man, than a hundred stripes with a fool.

11 The evil one continually seeks conflicts. But a cruel Angel shall be sent against him.

12 It is more expedient to meet a bear robbed of her young, than the foolish trusting in his own folly.

13 Whoever repays evil for good, evil shall not withdraw from his house.

14 Whoever releases the water is the head of the conflict. And just before he suffers contempt, he abandons judgment.

15 Those who justify the impious, and those who condemn the just, both are abominable with God.

16 What does it profit the foolish to have riches, when he is not able to buy wisdom? Whoever makes his house high seeks ruin. And whoever shuns learning shall fall into evils.

17 Whoever is a friend loves at all times. And a brother is proved by distress.

18 A foolish man will clap his hands, when he makes a pledge for his friend.

19 Whoever dwells on discord loves disputes. And whoever exalts his door seeks ruin.

20 Whoever is of a perverse heart shall not find good. And whoever turns his tongue shall fall into evil.

21 A foolish one is born into his own disgrace. But his father will not rejoice in one who is senseless.

22 A joyful soul makes a lifetime flourish. A gloomy spirit dries out the bones.

23 The impious receives gifts from the bosom, so that he may pervert the paths of judgment.

24 Prudence shines from the face of the wise. The eyes of the foolish are on the ends of the earth.

25 A foolish son is the anger of the father and the grief of the mother who conceived him.

26 It is not good to inflict damage on the just, nor to strike the leader who judges uprightly.

27 Whoever moderates his words is learned and prudent. And a man of learning has a precious spirit.

28 If he would remain silent, even the foolish would be considered wise, and if he closes his lips, intelligent.

Proverbs 18

1 Whoever has a will to withdraw from a friend, seeks occasions; he shall be reproached at all times.

2 The foolish do not accept words of prudence, unless you say what is already turning in his heart.

3 The impious, when he has arrived within the depths of sin, thinks little of it. But ill repute and disgrace follow him.

4 Words from the mouth of a man are deep waters. And the fountain of wisdom is a torrent overflowing.

5 It is not good to accept the character of the impious, so as to turn away from true judgment.

6 The lips of the foolish meddle in disputes. And his mouth provokes conflicts.

7 The mouth of the foolish is his destruction, and his own lips are the ruin of his soul.

8 The words of the double-tongued seem simple. And they reach even to the interior of the gut. Fear casts down the lazy, but the souls of the effeminate shall go hungry.

9 Whoever is dissolute and slack in his work is the brother of him who wastes his own works.

10 The name of the Lord is very strong tower. The just one rushes to it, and he shall be exalted.

11 The substance of the wealthy is the city of his strength, and it is like a strong wall encircling him.

12 The heart of a man is exalted before it is crushed and humbled before it is glorified.

13 Whoever responds before he listens, demonstrates himself to be foolish and deserving of confusion.

14 The spirit of a man sustains his weakness. Yet who can sustain a spirit that is easily angered?

15 A prudent heart shall possess knowledge. And the ear of the wise seeks doctrine.

16 A man's gift expands his way and makes space for him before leaders.

17 The just is the first accuser of himself; his friend arrives and shall investigate him.

18 Casting a lot suppresses contentions and passes judgment, even among the powerful.

19 A brother who is helped by a brother is like a reinforced city, and judgments are like the bars of cities.

20 From the fruit of a man's mouth shall his belly be filled. And the harvest of his own lips shall satisfy him.

21 Death and life are in the power of the tongue. Whoever values it shall eat from its fruits.

22 He who has found a good wife has found goodness, and he shall draw contentment from the Lord. He who expels a good wife expels goodness. But he who holds on to an adulteress is foolish and impious.

23 The poor will speak with supplications. And the rich will express themselves roughly.

24 A man amiable to society shall be more friendly than a brother.

Proverbs 19

1 Better is the poor who walks in his simplicity, than the rich who twists his lips and is unwise.

2 Where there is no knowledge of the soul, there is no good. And whoever hurries with his feet will stumble.

3 The foolishness of a man undermines his steps. And then he seethes in his soul against God.

4 Riches adds many friends. But from the pauper, even those whom he had become separated.

5 A false witness shall not go unpunished. And whoever speaks lies will not escape.

6 Many honor the character of one who is powerful, and there are friends for a giver of gifts.

7 The brothers of the poor man hate him. Moreover, even his friends have withdrawn far from him. Whoever pursues only words shall have nothing.

8 But whoever possesses reason loves his own soul. And one who guards prudence shall discover good things.

9 A false witness shall not go unpunished. And whoever speaks lies will perish.

10 Fine things are not fitting for the foolish, nor is it fitting for a servant to rule over princes.

11 The doctrine of a man is known through patience. And his glory is to pass beyond iniquities.

12 Like the roaring of a lion, so also is the wrath of a king. And his cheerfulness is like the dew upon the grass.

13 A foolish son is the grief of his father. And an argumentative wife is like a roof that is continually leaking.

14 A house and its riches are given by parents. But a prudent wife is particularly from the Lord.

15 Laziness sends one into a deep sleep, and a dissolute soul will go hungry.

16 Whoever guards a commandment guards his own soul. But whoever neglects his own way will die.

17 Whoever is merciful to the poor lends to the Lord. And he will repay him for his efforts.

18 Teach your son; do not despair. But do not set your soul toward putting him to death.

19 Whoever is impatient will sustain damage. And when it has been taken away, he will set up another.

20 Listen to counsel and take up discipline, so that you may be wise in your latter days.

21 There are many intentions in the heart of a man. But the will of the Lord shall stand firm.

22 An indigent man is merciful. And a pauper is better than a deceitful man.

23 The fear of the Lord is unto life. And he shall linger in plentitude, without being visited by disaster.

24 The lazy conceals his hand under his arm, and he will not so much as bring it to his mouth.

25 When the pestilent are scourged, the foolish will become wiser. But if you chastise the wise, he will understand discipline.

26 Whoever afflicts his father and flees from his mother is disreputable and unhappy.

27 Son, do not cease listening to doctrine, and do not be ignorant of the sermons of knowledge.

28 An unjust witness ridicules judgment. And the mouth of the impious devours iniquity.

29 Judgments are prepared for those who ridicule. And striking hammers are prepared for the bodies of the foolish.

Proverbs 20

1 It is a luxurious thing, wine, and inebriation is tumultuous. Anyone who is delighted by this will not be wise.

2 Just like the roaring of a lion, so also is the dread of a king. Whoever provokes him sins in his own soul.

3 Honor is for the man who separates himself from contentions. But all the foolish meddle in altercations.

4 Because of the cold, the lazy one was not willing to plough. Therefore, in the summer, he will beg, and it will not be given to him.

5 Counsel in the heart of a man is like deep waters. But a wise man will draw it out.

6 Many men are called merciful. But who will find a faithful man?

7 The just who walks in his simplicity shall leave behind him blessed sons.

8 The king who sits on the throne of judgment scatters all evil with his gaze.

9 Who is able to say: "My heart is clean. I am pure from sin?"

10 Diverse weights, diverse measures: both are abominable with God.

11 A child may be understood by his interests: whether his works may be clean and upright.

12 The hearing ear and the seeing eye: the Lord has made them both.

13 Do not love sleep, lest deprivation oppress you. Open your eyes and be satisfied with bread.

14 "It is bad, it is bad," says every buyer; and when he has withdrawn, then he will boast.

15 There is gold, and there are a multitude of jewels. But lips of knowledge are a precious vessel.

16 Take away the vestments of him who stands up to vouch for a stranger, and take a pledge from him instead of from outsiders.

17 The bread of lies is sweet to a man. But afterwards, his mouth will be filled with pebbles.

18 Plans are strengthened by counsels. And wars are to be handled by governments.

19 Do not become involved with him who reveals mysteries, and who walks deceitfully, and who enlarges his lips.

20 Whoever curses his father and mother, his lamp will be extinguished in the midst of darkness.

21 When an inheritance is obtained hastily in the beginning, in the end it will be without a blessing.

22 Do not say, "I will repay evil." Wait for the Lord, and he will free you.

23 Diverse weights are an abomination with the Lord. A deceitful balance is not good.

24 The steps of men are directed by the Lord. But who is the man able to understand his own way?

25 It is ruin for a man to devour what is holy, or, after making vows, to retract them.

26 A wise king scatters the impious and bends an archway over them.

27 The spirit of a man is a lamp to the Lord, which investigates all the secrets of the inner self.

28 Mercy and truth guard the king, and his throne is strengthened by clemency.

29 The joy of youths is their strength. And the dignity of old men is their grey hairs.

30 The bruise of a wound, as well as scourges, shall wipe away evils in the more secret places of the inner self.

Proverbs 21

1 Just as with the dividing of the waters, so also is the heart of the king in the hand of the Lord. He shall bend it whichever way he wills.

2 Every way of a man seems right to himself. But the Lord weighs hearts.

3 To do mercy and judgment is more pleasing to the Lord than sacrifices.

4 To lift up the eyes is to enlarge the heart. The lamp of the impious is sin.

5 The intentions of the robust continually bring forth abundance. But all the lazy are continually in need.

6 Whoever gathers treasures by a lying tongue is vain and heartless. And he will stumble into the snares of death.

7 The robberies of the impious will drag them down, because they were not willing to do judgment.

8 The perverse way of a man is foreign. But whoever is pure: his work is upright.

9 It is better to sit in a corner of the attic, than with a contentious woman and in a shared house.

10 The soul of the impious desires evil; he will not take pity on his neighbor.

11 When the pestilent is punished, a little one will become wiser. And if he pursues what is wise, he will receive knowledge.

12 The just thinks carefully about the house of the impious, so that he may draw the impious away from evil.

13 Whoever blocks his ears to the outcry of the poor shall also cry out himself, and he will not be heeded.

14 A surprise gift extinguishes anger. And a gift concealed in the bosom extinguishes the greatest indignation.

15 It is gladness for the just to do judgment; and it is dread for those who work iniquity.

16 A man who wanders astray from the way of doctrine will linger in the company of the giants.

17 Whoever loves a feast will be in deprivation. Whoever loves wine and fatness will not be enriched.

18 The impious is given over instead of the just, and the iniquitous is given over in place of the upright.

19 It is better to live in a deserted land, than with a quarrelsome and emotional woman.

20 There is desirable treasure, as well as oil, in the habitations of the just. And the imprudent man will waste it.

21 Whoever follows justice and mercy shall discover life, justice, and glory.

22 The wise has ascended the city of the strong, and he has torn down the bulwark of its confidence.

23 Whoever guards his mouth and his tongue guards his soul from anguish.

24 A proud and arrogant one is also called ignorant, if he, in anger, acts according to pride.

25 Desires kill the lazy, for his hands are not willing to work at all.

26 He covets and desires all day long. But whoever is just shall distribute and shall not cease.

27 The sacrifices of the impious are abominable, because they are offered out of wickedness.

28 A lying witness will perish. An obedient man shall speak of victory.

29 The impious man insolently hardens his face. But whoever is upright corrects his own way.

30 There is no wisdom, there is no prudence, there is no counsel, which is against the Lord.

31 The horse is prepared for the day of battle. But the Lord bestows salvation.

Proverbs 22

1 A good name is better than many riches. And good esteem is above silver and gold.

2 The rich and poor have met one another. The Lord is the maker of them both.

3 The clever saw evil and hid himself. The innocent continued on and was afflicted with damage.

4 The end of moderation is the fear of the Lord, riches and glory and life.

5 Weapons and swords are on the way of the perverse. But he who guards his own soul withdraws far from them.

6 The proverb is: A youth is close to his way; even when he is old, he will not withdraw from it.

7 The rich rule over the poor. And the borrower is servant to the lender.

8 Whoever sows iniquity will reap evils, and by the rod of his own wrath he will be consumed.

9 Whoever is inclined to mercy shall be blessed, for from his bread he has given to the poor. Whoever gives gifts will acquire victory and honor. But he carries away the soul of the receiver.

10 Cast out the one who ridicules, and conflict will go out with him, and accusations and insults will cease.

11 Whoever loves cleanness of heart, because of the grace of his lips, will have the king as his friend.

12 The eyes of the Lord watch over knowledge. And the words of the iniquitous are supplanted.

13 The lazy one says: "There is a lion outside. I might be slain in the midst of the streets."

14 The mouth of a foreign woman is a deep pit; the Lord was angry with him who will fall into it.

15 Foolishness has been bound to the heart of a child, and a rod of discipline shall cause it to flee.

16 Whoever slanders the poor, so as to augment his own riches, will give it away to one who is richer, and will be in need.

17 Incline your ear, and listen to the words of the wise. Then apply your heart to my doctrine.

18 It shall be beautiful to you, if you preserve it in your inner self, and it shall overflow from your lips,

19 so that your confidence may be in the Lord. Therefore, I also have revealed it to you this day.

20 Behold, I have written it for you in three ways, and with meditations and knowledge,

21 so that I might reveal to you, firmly and with words of truth, in order to respond about these things to those who sent you.

22 Do not act with violence toward the pauper because he is poor. And do not weary the needy at the gate.

23 For the Lord will judge his case, and he will pierce those who have pierced his soul.

24 Do not be willing to be a friend to an angry man, and do not walk with a furious man,

25 lest perhaps you learn his ways, and take up a stumbling block to your soul.

26 Do not be willing to be with those who certify with their hands, and who offer themselves as a guarantee against debts.

27 For if you do not have the means to restore, what reason should there be for him to take the covering from your bed?

28 Do not cross beyond the ancient limits that your fathers have set.

29 Have you seen a man swift in his work? He shall stand in the sight of kings, and not before those who are disreputable.

Proverbs 23

1 When you sit down to eat with a leader, pay close attention to what has been set before your face,

2 and put a knife to your throat, if, in such a way, you could hold your soul in your own power.

3 Do not desire his foods, in which is the bread of deceit.

4 Do not be willing to labor so that you may be enriched. But set limits by your prudence.

5 Do not raise your eyes toward wealth that you are not able to have. For they will make themselves wings, like those of an eagle, and they will fly in the sky.

6 Do not eat with an envious man, and do not desire his foods.

7 For, like a seer and an interpreter of dreams, he presumes what he does not know. "Eat and drink," he will say to you; and his mind is not with you.

8 The foods that you had eaten, you will vomit up. And you will lose the beauty in your words.

9 Do not speak into the ears of the unwise. They will despise the doctrine of your eloquence.

10 Do not touch the boundaries of little ones, and do not enter into the field of the fatherless.

11 For their close relative is strong, and he will judge their case against you.

12 Let your heart enter into doctrine, and let your ears enter into words of knowledge.

13 Do not be willing to take away discipline from a child. For if you strike him with the rod, he will not die.

14 You will strike him with the rod, and so shall you deliver his soul from Hell.

15 My son, if your soul will become wise, my heart will be glad with you.

16 And my temperament will exult, when your lips will have spoken what is upright.

17 Let not your heart compete with sinners. But be in the fear of the Lord all day long.

18 For you will have hope in the end, and your expectation will not be taken away.

19 Listen, my son, and be wise, and direct your soul along the way.

20 Do not be willing to be in the feasts of great drinkers, nor in the carousings of those who gather to feed on flesh.

21 For those who waste time drinking, and who surrender themselves to symbols, will be consumed. And those who sleep will be clothed in rags.

22 Listen to your father, who conceived you. And do not despise your mother, when she is old.

23 Purchase truth, and do not sell wisdom, or doctrine, or understanding.

24 The father of the just exults in gladness; he who has conceived the wise will rejoice in him.

25 Let your father and your mother be joyful, and may she who conceived you exult.

26 My son, offer me your heart, and let your eyes keep to my ways.

27 For a loose woman is a deep pit, and a foreign woman is a constricted well.

28 She lies in wait along the way like a robber. And the incautious one whom she sees, she will put to death.

29 Who has woe? Whose father has woe? Who has quarrels? Who falls into pits? Who has wounds without cause? Who has watery eyes?

30 Is it not those who linger over wine, and who strive to be drinking from their cups?

31 Do not gaze into the wine when it turns gold, when its color shines in the glass. It enters pleasantly,

32 but in the end, it will bite like a snake, and it will spread poison like a king of snakes.

33 Your eyes will see women who are outsiders, and your heart will utter perversities.

34 And you will be like someone sleeping in the middle of the sea, and like a pilot, fast asleep, who has lost his hold on the helm.

35 And you will say: "They have beaten me, but I did not feel pain. They have dragged me, and I did not realize it. When will I awaken and find more wine?"

Proverbs 24

1 Do not imitate evil men, nor desire to be among them.

2 For their mind meditates on robberies, and their lips speak deceptions.

3 By wisdom shall a house be built, and by prudence shall it be strengthened.

4 By doctrine, the storerooms shall be filled with every substance that is precious and most beautiful.

5 A wise man is strong, and a well-taught man is robust and valiant.

6 For war is undertaken in an orderly manner, and safety shall be where there are many counsels.

7 Wisdom is beyond the foolish; at the gate he will not open his mouth.

8 Whoever intends to do evil shall be called foolish.

9 The intention of the foolish is sin. And the detractor is an abomination among men.

10 If you despair, being weary in the day of anguish, your strength will be diminished.

11 Rescue those who are led away to death. And do not cease from delivering those who are dragged away to a violent death.

12 If you would say: "I do not have sufficient strength." He who inspects the heart, the same one understands, and nothing slips past the one who preserves your soul. And he shall repay a man according to his works.

13 My son, eat honey, because it is good, and the honeycomb, because it is so sweet to your throat.

14 So, too, is the doctrine of wisdom to your soul. When you have found it, you will have hope in the end, and your hope shall not perish.

15 Do not lie in wait, and do not seek impiety in the house of the just, nor spoil his rest.

16 For the just one will fall seven times, and he shall rise again. But the impious will fall into evil.

17 When your enemy will fall, do not be glad, and do not let your heart exult in his ruin,

18 lest perhaps the Lord see, and it displease him, and he may take away his wrath from him.

19 Do not contend with the most wicked, and do not be a rival to the impious.

20 For the evil hold no hope in the future, and the lamp of the impious will be extinguished.

21 My son, fear the Lord, as well as the king. And do not mingle with detractors.

22 For their perdition shall up rise suddenly. And who knows what ruin will be for each of them?

23 Likewise, these things are for the wise. It is not good to base judgment on knowledge of character.

24 Those who say to the impious, "You are just," shall be cursed by the people, and the tribes shall detest them.

25 Those who argue against the impious shall be praised, and a blessing shall come upon them.

26 He shall kiss the lips, who responds with upright words.

27 Prepare your outdoor work, and diligently cultivate your field, so that afterward, you may build your house.

28 Do not be a witness without cause against your neighbor. And do not mislead anyone with your lips.

29 Do not say, "I will do to him as he has done to me." I will repay each one according to his work.

30 I passed by the field of a lazy man, and by the vineyard of a foolish man,

31 and behold, it was entirely filled with nettles, and thorns had covered its surface, and the stonewall was destroyed.

32 When I had seen this, I laid it up in my heart, and by this example, I received discipline.

33 You will sleep a little," I said. "You will slumber briefly. You will fold your hands a little, so as to rest.

34 And destitution will overtake you like a runner, and begging will overtake you like an armed man."

Proverbs 25

1 These, too, are parables of Solomon, which the men of Hezekiah, king of Judah, transferred.

2 It is to the glory of God to conceal a word, and it is to the glory of kings to investigate speech.

3 Heaven above, and earth below, and the heart of kings are each unsearchable.

4 Take away the tarnish from silver, and a most pure vessel will go forth.

5 Take away impiety from the face of the king, and his throne shall be made firm by justice.

6 Do not appear glorious before the king, and do not stand in the place of the great.

7 For it is better that it should be said to you, "Ascend to here," than that you should be humbled before the prince.

8 The things that your eyes have seen, do not offer hastily in a quarrel, lest afterward you may not be able to make amends, when you have dishonored your friend.

9 Argue your case with your friend, and do not reveal the secret to an outsider,

10 lest perhaps he may insult you, when he has heard it, and he might not cease to reproach you. Grace and friendship free a man; preserve these for yourself, lest you fall under reproach.

11 Whoever speaks a word at an opportune time is like apples of gold on beds of silver.

12 Whoever reproves the wise and obedient ear is like an earring of gold with a shining pearl.

13 Just like the cold of snow in a time of harvest, so also is a faithful messenger to him who sent him: he causes his soul to rest.

14 A man who boasts and does not fulfill his promises is like clouds and wind, when rain does not follow.

15 By patience, a leader shall be appeased, and a soft tongue shall break hardness.

16 You have discovered honey; eat what is sufficient for you, lest perhaps, being filled up, you may vomit it.

17 Withdraw your feet from the house of your neighbor, lest, when he has had his fill, he may hate you.

18 A man who speaks false testimony against his neighbor is like a dart and a sword and a sharp arrow.

19 Whoever sets his hopes on the unfaithful in a day of anguish is like a rotten tooth and weary foot,

20 and like one who loosens his garment in cold weather. Whoever sings verses to a wicked heart is like vinegar on baking soda. Just like a moth to a garment, and a worm to wood, so too does the sadness of a man do harm to the heart.

21 If your enemy is hungry, feed him. If he is thirsty, give him water to drink.

22 For you will gather hot coals upon his head, and the Lord will repay you.

23 The north wind brings forth the rain, and a sorrowful face brings forth a detracting tongue.

24 It is better to sit in a corner of the attic, than with an argumentative woman and in a shared house.

25 Like cold water to a thirsty soul, so too are good reports from a far away land.

26 The just falling down before the impious is like a fountain stirred up by feet and like a corrupted spring.

27 Just as whoever eats too much honey, it is not good for him, so also whoever is an investigator of what is majestic will be overwhelmed by glory.

28 Just like a city lying in the open and without surrounding walls, so also is a man who is unable to restrain his own spirit in speaking.

Proverbs 26

1 In the manner of snow in the summer, and rain at the harvest, so also is glory unfit for the foolish.

2 Like a bird flying away to another place, and like a sparrow that hurries away freely, so also a curse uttered against someone without cause will pass away.

3 A whip is for a horse, and a muzzle is for donkey, and a rod is for the back of the imprudent.

4 Do not respond to the foolish according to his folly, lest you become like him.

5 Respond to the foolish according to his folly, lest he imagine himself to be wise.

6 Whoever sends words by a foolish messenger has lame feet and drinks iniquity.

7 In the manner of a lame man who has beautiful legs to no purpose, so also is a parable unfit for the mouth of the foolish.

8 Just like one who casts a stone into the pile of Mercury, so also is he who gives honor to the foolish.

9 In the manner of a thorn, if it were to spring up from the hand of a drunkard, so also is a parable in the mouth of the foolish.

10 Judgment determines cases. And whoever imposes silence on the foolish mitigates anger.

11 Like a dog that returns to his vomit, so also is the imprudent who repeats his foolishness.

12 Have you seen a man who seems wise to himself? There will be greater hope held for the unwise than for him.

13 The lazy one says, "There is a lion along the way, and a lioness in the roads."

14 Just as a door turns upon its hinges, so also does the lazy one turn upon his bed.

15 The lazy one conceals his hand under his arms, and it is a labor for him to move it to his mouth.

16 The lazy one seems wiser to himself than seven men speaking judgments.

17 Just like one who takes hold of a dog by the ears, so also is he who crosses impatiently and meddles in the quarrels of another.

18 Just as he is guilty who let loose the arrows and the lances unto death,

19 so also is the man who harms his friend by deceitfulness. And when he has been apprehended, he says, "I did it jokingly."

20 When the wood fails, the fire will be extinguished. And when the gossiper is taken away, conflicts will be quelled.

21 Just as charcoals are to burning coals, and wood is to fire, so also is an angry man who stirs up quarrels.

22 The words of a whisperer seem simple, but they penetrate to the innermost parts of the self.

23 In the same manner as an earthen vessel, if it were adorned with impure silver, conceited lips are allied with a wicked heart.

24 An enemy is known by his lips, though it is from his heart that he draws out deceit.

25 When he will have lowered his voice, do not believe him, for there are seven vices in his heart.

26 Whoever covers hatred with deceit, his malice shall be revealed in the assembly.

27 Whoever digs a pit will fall into it. And whoever rolls a stone, it will roll back to him.

28 A false tongue does not love truth. And a slippery mouth works ruin.

Proverbs 27

1 Do not boast about tomorrow, for you do not know what the future day may bring.

2 Let another praise you, and not your own mouth: an outsider, and not your own lips.

3 A stone is weighty, and sand is burdensome; but the wrath of the foolish is heavier than both.

4 Anger holds no mercy, nor does fury when it erupts. And who can bear the assault of one who has been provoked?

5 An open rebuke is better than hidden love.

6 The wounds of a loved one are better than the deceitful kisses of a hateful one.

7 A sated soul will trample the honeycomb. And a hungry soul will accept even bitter in place of sweet.

8 Just like a bird migrating from her nest, so also is a man who abandons his place.

9 Ointment and various perfumes delight the heart. And the good advice of a friend is sweet to the soul.

10 Do not dismiss your friend or your father's friend. And do not enter your brother's house in the day of your affliction. A close neighbor is better than a distant brother.

11 My son, study wisdom, and rejoice my heart, so that you may be able to respond to the one who reproaches.

12 The discerning man, seeing evil, hides himself. The little ones, continuing on, sustain losses.

13 Take away the garment of him who has vouched for an outsider. And take a pledge from him on behalf of foreigners.

14 Whoever blesses his neighbor with a grand voice, rising in the night, shall be like one who curses.

15 A roof leaking on a cold day, and an argumentative woman, are comparable.

16 He who would restrain her, he is like one who would grasp the wind, or who would gather together oil with his right hand.

17 Iron sharpens iron, and a man sharpens the countenance of his friend.

18 Whoever maintains the fig tree shall eat its fruit. And whoever is the keeper of his master shall be glorified.

19 In the manner of faces looking into shining water, so are the hearts of men made manifest to the prudent.

20 Hell and perdition are never filled; similarly the eyes of men are insatiable.

21 In the manner of silver being tested in the refinery, and gold in the furnace, so also is a man tested by the mouth of one who praises. The heart of the iniquitous inquires after evils, but the heart of the righteous inquires after knowledge.

22 Even if you were to crush the foolish with a mortar, as when a pestle strikes over pearled barley, his foolishness would not be taken from him.

23 Be diligent to know the countenance of your cattle, and consider your own flocks,

24 for you will not always hold this power. But a crown shall be awarded from generation to generation.

25 The meadows are open, and the green plants have appeared, and the hay has been collected from the mountains.

26 Lambs are for your clothing, and goats are for the price of a field.

27 Let the milk of goats be sufficient for your food, and for the necessities of your household, and for the provisions of your handmaids.

Proverbs 28

1 The impious flees, though no one pursues. But the just, like a confident lion, shall be without dread.

2 Because of the sins of the land, it has many princes. And because of the wisdom of a man, and the knowledge of those things that are said, the life of the leader shall be prolonged.

3 A poor man slandering the poor is like a violent rainstorm in advance of a famine.

4 Those who abandon the law praise the impious. Those who guard it are inflamed against him.

5 Evil men do not intend judgment. But those who inquire after the Lord turn their souls toward all things.

6 Better is the pauper walking in his simplicity, than the rich walking in ways of depravity.

7 Whoever keeps the law is a wise son. But whoever feeds gluttons brings shame to his father.

8 Whoever piles up riches by usury and profit gathers them for him who will give freely to the poor.

9 Whoever turns away his ears from listening to the law: his prayer will be detestable.

10 Whoever deceives the just in a malicious way will fall into his own perdition. And the simple shall possess his goods.

11 The rich one seems wise to himself. But the poor one, being prudent, shall evaluate him.

12 In the exultation of the just, there is great glory. When the impious reign, men are brought to ruin.

13 Whoever hides his crimes will not be guided. But whoever will have confessed and abandoned them shall overtake mercy.

14 Blessed is the man who is ever fearful. Yet truly, whoever is hardened in mind will fall into evil.

15 An impious leader over a poor people is like a roaring lion and a hungry bear.

16 A leader destitute of prudence will oppress many through false accusations. But whoever hates avarice shall prolong his days.

17 A man who slanders the blood of a life, even if he flees to the pit, no one will tolerate him.

18 Whoever walks simply shall be saved. Whoever is perverse in his steps will fall all at once.

19 Whoever works his land shall be satisfied with bread. But whoever pursues leisure will be filled with need.

20 A faithful man shall be greatly praised. But whoever rushes to become rich will not be innocent.

21 Whoever shows favoritism in judgment does not do well; even if it is for a morsel of bread, he forsakes the truth.

22 A man who hurries to become rich, and who envies others, does not know that destitution will overwhelm him.

23 Whoever corrects a man, afterward he shall find favor with him, more so than he who deceives him with a flattering tongue.

24 Whoever takes away anything from his father or mother, and who says, "This is not a sin," is the associate of a murderer.

25 Whoever boasts and enlarges himself stirs up conflicts. Yet truly, whoever trusts in the Lord will be healed.

26 Whoever trusts in his own heart is a fool. But whoever treads wisely, the same shall be saved.

27 Whoever gives to the poor shall not be in need. Whoever despises his petition will suffer scarcity.

28 When the impious rise up, men will hide themselves. When they perish, the just shall be multiplied.

Proverbs 29

1 The man who, with a stiff neck, treats the one who corrects him with contempt will be suddenly overwhelmed to his own destruction, and reason shall not follow him.

2 When just men are multiplied, the common people shall rejoice. When the impious take up the leadership, the people shall mourn.

3 The man who loves wisdom rejoices his father. But whoever nurtures promiscuous women will lose his substance.

4 A just king guides the land. A man of avarice will destroy it.

5 A man who speaks to his friend with flattering and feigned words spreads a net for his own feet.

6 A snare will entangle the iniquitous when he sins. And the just shall praise and be glad.

7 The just knows the case of the poor. The impious is ignorant of knowledge.

8 Pestilent men squander a city. Yet truly, the wise avert fury.

9 A wise man, if he were to contend with the foolish, whether in anger or in laughter, would find no rest.

10 Bloodthirsty men hate the simple one; but the just seek out his soul.

11 A foolish one offers everything on his mind. A wise one reserves and defers until later.

12 A leader who freely listens to lying words has only impious servants.

13 The pauper and the creditor have met one another. The Lord is the illuminator of them both.

14 The king who judges the poor in truth, his throne shall be secured in eternity.

15 The rod and its correction distribute wisdom. But the child who is left to his own will brings shame to his mother.

16 When the impious are multiplied, crimes will be multiplied. But the just shall see their ruin.

17 Teach your son, and he will refresh you, and he will give delight to your soul.

18 When prophecy fails, the people will be scattered. Yet truly, whoever guards the law is blessed.

19 A servant cannot be taught by words, because he understands what you say, but he disdains to respond.

20 Have you seen a man rushing to speak? Foolishness has more hope than his correction.

21 Whoever nurtures his servant delicately from childhood, afterwards will find him defiant.

22 A short-tempered man provokes quarrels. And whoever is easily angered is more likely to sin.

23 Humiliation follows the arrogant. And glory shall uphold the humble in spirit.

24 Whoever participates with a thief hates his own soul; for he listens to his oath and does not denounce him.

25 Whoever fears man will quickly fall. Whoever hopes in the Lord shall be lifted up.

26 Many demand the face of the leader. But the judgment of each one proceeds from the Lord.

27 The just abhor an impious man. And the impious abhor those who are on the right way. By keeping the word, the son shall be free from perdition.

Proverbs 30

1 The words of the Gatherer, the son of the Vomiter. The vision that the man spoke. God is with him, and he, being strengthened by God and abiding with him, said:

2 "I am the most foolish among men, and the wisdom of men is not with me.

3 I have not learned wisdom, and I have not known the knowledge of sanctity.

4 Who has ascended to heaven and also descended? Who has grasped the wind in his hands? Who has tied the waters together, as with a garment? Who has raised all the limits of the earth? What is his name, and what is the name of his son, if you know?

5 Every word of God is fire-tested. He is a bronze shield to those who hope in him.

6 Do not add anything to his words, lest you be reproved and be discovered to be a liar.

7 Two things I have asked of you; do not deny them to me before I die.

8 Remove, far from me, vanity and lying words. Give me neither begging, nor wealth. Apportion to me only the necessities of my life,

9 lest perhaps, being filled, I might be enticed into denial, and say: 'Who is the Lord?' Or, being compelled by destitution, I might steal, and then perjure myself in the name of my God.

10 Do not accuse a servant to his lord, lest he curse you, and you fall.

11 There is a generation which curses their father, and which does not bless their mother.

12 There is a generation which seems pure to themselves, and yet they are not even washed from their filthiness.

13 There is a generation, whose eyes have been elevated, and their eyelids are lifted on high.

14 There is a generation which has swords in place of teeth, and which commands their molars to devour the indigent from the earth and the poor from among men.

15 The leech has two daughters, who say, 'Bring, bring.' Three things are insatiable, and a fourth never says 'Enough':

16 Hell, and the mouth of the womb, and a land that is not filled with water. And truly, fire never says, 'Enough.'

17 The eye of one who mocks his father and who despises the childbearing of his mother, let the ravens of the torrent tear it out, and let the sons of the eagles consume it.

18 Three things are difficult for me, and about a fourth, I am nearly ignorant:

19 the way of an eagle in the sky, the way of a serpent on a rock, the way of a ship in the middle of the sea, and the way of a man in adolescence.

20 Such is the way also of an adulterous woman, who eats, and wiping her mouth, says: "I have done no evil."

21 By three things, the earth is moved, and a fourth it is not able to sustain:

22 by a slave when he reigns, by the foolish when he has been filled with food,

23 by a hateful woman when she has been taken in matrimony, and by a handmaid when she has been heir to her mistress.

24 Four things are least upon the earth, and they are wiser than the wise:

25 the ants, an infirm people who provide food for themselves at the harvest,

26 the rabbit, a sickened people who make their bed upon the rock.

27 The locust has no king, but they all depart by their troops.

28 The lizard supports itself on hands and dwells in the buildings of kings.

29 There are three things that advance well, and a fourth that marches happily on:

30 a lion, the strongest of beasts, who fears nothing that he meets,

31 a rooster prepared at the loins, likewise a ram, and a king, whom none can resist.

32 There is one who has appeared foolish, after he was lifted up on high; for if he had understood, he would have placed his hand over his mouth.

33 But whoever strongly squeezes the udder to bring out the milk, presses out butter. And whoever violently blows his nose, brings out blood. And whoever provokes wrath, brings forth discord."

Proverbs 31

1 The words of king Lamuel. The vision by which his mother instructed him:

2 "What, O my beloved? What, O beloved of my womb? What, O beloved of my vows?

3 Do not give your substance to women, or your riches to overthrow kings.

4 Not to kings, O Lamuel, not to kings give wine. For there are no secrets where drunkenness reigns.

5 And perhaps they may drink and forget judgments, and alter the case of the sons of the poor.

6 Give strong drink to the grieving, and wine to those who are bitter in soul.

7 Let them drink, and forget their needs, and remember their sorrow no more.

8 Open your mouth for the mute and for all the cases of the sons who are passing through.

9 Open your mouth, declare what is just, and do justice to the indigent and the poor.

10 Who shall find a strong woman? Far away, and from the furthest parts, is her price.

11 The heart of her husband confides in her, and he will not be deprived of spoils.

12 She will repay him with good, and not evil, all the days of her life.

13 She has sought wool and flax, and she has worked these by the counsel of her hands.

14 She has become like a merchant's ship, bringing her bread from far away.

15 And she has risen in the night, and given a prey to her household, and provisions to her maids.

16 She has considered a field and bought it. From the fruit of her own hands, she has planted a vineyard.

17 She has wrapped her waist with fortitude, and she has strengthened her arm.

18 She has tasted and seen that her tasks are good; her lamp shall not be extinguished at night.

19 She has put her hand to strong things, and her fingers have taken hold of the spindle.

20 She has opened her hand to the needy, and she has extended her hands to the poor.

21 She shall not fear, in the cold of snow, for her household. For all those of her household have been clothed two-fold.

22 She has made embroidered clothing for herself. Fine linen and purple is her garment.

23 Her husband is noble at the gates, when he sits among the senators of the land.

24 She has made finely woven cloth and sold it, and she has delivered a waistband to the Canaanite.

25 Strength and elegance are her clothing, and she will laugh in the final days.

26 She has opened her mouth to wisdom, and the law of clemency is on her tongue.

27 She has considered the paths of her household, and she has not eaten her bread in idleness.

28 Her sons rose up and predicted great happiness; her husband rose up and praised her.

29 Many daughters have gathered together riches; you have surpassed them all.

30 Charm is false, and beauty is vain. The woman who fears the Lord, the same shall be praised.

31 Give to her from the fruit of her own hands. And let her works praise her at the gates.

Ecclesiastes 1

1 The words of Ecclesiastes, the son of David, the king of Jerusalem.

2 Ecclesiastes said: Vanity of vanities! Vanity of vanities, and all is vanity!

3 What more does a man have from all his labor, as he labors under the sun?

4 A generation passes away, and a generation arrives. But the earth stands forever.

5 The sun rises and sets; it returns to its place, and from there, being born again,

6 it circles through the south, and arcs toward the north. The spirit continues on, illuminating everything in its circuit, and turning again in its cycle.

7 All rivers enter into the sea, and the sea does not overflow. To the place from which the rivers go out, they return, so that they may flow again.

8 Such things are difficult; man is not able to explain them with words. The eye is not satisfied by seeing, nor is the ear fulfilled by hearing.

9 What is it that has existed? The same shall exist in the future. What is it that has been done? The same shall continue to be done.

10 There is nothing new under the sun. Neither is anyone able to say: "Behold, this is new!" For it has already been brought forth in the ages that were before us.

11 There is no remembrance of the former things. Indeed, neither shall there be any record of past things in the future, for those who will exist at the very end.

12 I, Ecclesiastes, was king of Israel at Jerusalem.

13 And I was determined in my mind to seek and to investigate wisely, concerning all that is done under the sun. God has given this very difficult task to the sons of men, so that they may be occupied by it.

14 I have seen all that is done under the sun, and behold: all is emptiness and an affliction of the spirit.

15 The perverse are unwilling to be corrected, and the number of the foolish is boundless.

16 I have spoken in my heart, saying: "Behold, I have achieved greatness, and I have surpassed all the wise who were before me in Jerusalem." And my mind has contemplated many things wisely, and I have learned.

17 And I have dedicated my heart, so that I may know prudence and doctrine, and also error and foolishness. Yet I recognize that, in these things also, there is hardship, and affliction of the spirit.

18 Because of this, with much wisdom there is also much anger. And whoever adds knowledge, also adds hardship.

Ecclesiastes 2

1 I said in my heart: "I will go forth and overflow with delights, and I will enjoy good things." And I saw that this, too, is emptiness.

2 Laughter, I considered an error. And to rejoicing, I said: "Why are you being deceived, to no purpose?"

3 I decided in my heart to withdraw my flesh from wine, so that I might bring my mind to wisdom, and turn away from foolishness, until I see what is useful for the sons of men, and what they ought to do under the sun, during the number of the days of their life.

4 I magnified my works. I built houses for myself, and I planted vineyards.

5 I made gardens and orchards. And I planted them with trees of every kind.

6 And I dug out fishponds of water, so that I might irrigate the forest of growing trees.

7 I obtained men and women servants, and I had a great family, as well as herds of cattle and great flocks of sheep, beyond all who were before me in Jerusalem.

8 I amassed for myself silver and gold, and the wealth of kings and governors. I chose men and women singers, and the delights of the sons of men, bowls and pitchers for the purpose of pouring wine.

9 And I surpassed in opulence all who were before me in Jerusalem. My wisdom also persevered with me.

10 And all that my eyes desired, I did not refuse them. Neither did I prohibit my heart from enjoying every pleasure, and from amusing itself in the things that I had prepared. And I regarded this as my share, as if I were making use of my own labors.

11 But when I turned myself toward all the works that my hands had made, and to the labors in which I had perspired to no purpose, I saw emptiness and affliction of the soul in all things, and that nothing is permanent under the sun.

12 I continued on, so as to contemplate wisdom, as well as error and foolishness. "What is man," I said, "that he would be able to follow his Maker, the King?"

13 And I saw that wisdom surpasses foolishness, so much so that they differ as much as light from darkness.

14 The eyes of a wise man are in his head. A foolish man walks in darkness. Yet I learned that one would pass away like the other.

15 And I said in my heart: "If the death of both the foolish and myself will be one, how does it benefit me, if I have given myself more thoroughly to the work of wisdom?" And as I was speaking within my own mind, I perceived that this, too, is emptiness.

16 For there will not be a remembrance in perpetuity of the wise, nor of the foolish. And the future times will cover everything together, with oblivion. The learned die in a manner similar to the unlearned.

17 And, because of this, my life wearied me, since I saw that everything under the sun is evil, and everything is empty and an affliction of the spirit.

18 Again, I detested all my efforts, by which I had earnestly labored under the sun, to be taken up by an heir after me,

19 though I know not whether he will be wise or foolish. And yet he will have power over my labors, in which I have toiled and been anxious. And is there anything else so empty?

20 Therefore, I ceased, and my heart renounced further laboring under the sun.

21 For when someone labors in wisdom, and doctrine, and prudence, he leaves behind what he has obtained to one who is idle. So this, too, is emptiness and a great burden.

22 For how can a man benefit from all his labor and affliction of spirit, by which he has been tormented under the sun?

23 All his days have been filled with sorrows and hardships; neither does he rest his mind, even in the night. And is this not emptiness?

24 Is it not better to eat and drink, and to show his soul the good things of his labors? And this is from the hand of God.

25 So who will feast and overflow with delights as much as I have?

26 God has given, to the man who is good in his sight, wisdom, and knowledge, and rejoicing. But to the sinner, he has given affliction and needless worrying, so as to add, and to gather, and to deliver, to him who has pleased God. But this, too, is emptiness and a hollow worrying of the mind.

Ecclesiastes 3

1 All things have their time, and all things under heaven continue during their interval.

2 A time to be born, and a time to die. A time to plant, and a time to pull up what was planted.

3 A time to kill, and a time to heal. A time to tear down, and a time to build up.

4 A time to weep, and a time to laugh. A time to mourn, and a time to dance.

5 A time to scatter stones, and a time to gather. A time to embrace, and a time to be far from embraces.

6 A time to gain, and a time to lose. A time to keep, and a time to cast away.

7 A time to rend, and a time to sew. A time to be silent, and a time to speak.

8 A time of love, and a time of hatred. A time of war, and a time of peace.

9 What more does a man have from his labor?

10 I have seen the affliction that God has given to the sons of men, in order that they may be occupied by it.

11 He has made all things good in their time, and he has handed over the world to their disputes, so that man may not discover the work which God made from the beginning, even until the end.

12 And I realize that there is nothing better than to rejoice, and to do well in this life.

13 For this is a gift from God: when each man eats and drinks, and sees the good results of his labor.

14 I have learned that all the works which God has made continue on, in perpetuity. We are not able to add anything, nor to take anything away, from those things which God has made in order that he may be feared.

15 What has been made, the same continues. What is in the future, has already existed. And God restores what has passed away.

16 I saw under the sun: instead of judgment, impiety, and instead of justice, iniquity.

17 And I said in my heart: "God will judge the just and the impious, and then the time for each matter shall be."

18 I said in my heart, about the sons of men, that God would test them, and reveal them to be like wild animals.

19 For this reason, the passing away of man and of beasts is one, and the condition of both is equal. For as a man dies, so also do they die. All things breathe similarly, and man has nothing more than beast; for all these are subject to vanity.

20 And all things continue on to one place; for from the earth they were made, and unto the earth they shall return together.

21 Who knows if the spirit of the sons of Adam ascend upward, and if the spirit of the beasts descend downward?

22 And I have discovered nothing to be better than for a man to rejoice in his work: for this is his portion. And who shall add to him, so that he may know the things that will occur after him?

Ecclesiastes 4

1 I turned myself to other things, and I saw the false accusations which are carried out under the sun, and the tears of the innocent, and that there was no one to console them; and that they were not able to withstand their violence, being destitute of all help.

2 And so, I praised the dead more than the living.

3 And happier than both of these, I judged him to be, who has not yet been born, and who has not yet seen the evils which are done under the sun.

4 Again, I was contemplating all the labors of men. And I took notice that their endeavors are open to the envy of their neighbor. And so, in this, too, there is emptiness and superfluous anxiety.

5 The foolish man folds his hands together, and he consumes his own flesh, saying:

6 "A handful with rest is better than both hands filled with labors and with affliction of the soul."

7 While considering this, I also discovered another vanity under the sun.

8 He is one, and he does not have a second: no son, no brother. And yet he does not cease to labor, nor are his eyes satisfied with wealth, nor does he reflect, saying: "For whom do I labor and cheat my soul of good things?" In this, too, is emptiness and a most burdensome affliction.

9 Therefore, it is better for two to be together, than for one to be alone. For they have the advantage of their companionship.

10 If one falls, he shall be supported by the other. Woe to one who is alone. For when he falls, he has no one to lift him up.

11 And if two are sleeping, they warm one another. How can one person alone be warmed?

12 And if a man can prevail against one, two may withstand him, and a threefold cord is broken with difficulty.

13 Better is a boy, poor and wise, than a king, old and foolish, who does not know to look ahead for the sake of posterity.

14 For sometimes, one goes forth from prison and chains, to a kingdom, while another, born to kingly power, is consumed by need.

15 I saw all the living who are walking under the sun, and I saw the next generation, who shall rise up in their places.

16 The number of people, out of all who existed before these, is boundless. And those who will exist afterwards shall not rejoice in them. But this, too, is emptiness and an affliction of the spirit.

17 Guard your foot, when you step into the house of God, and draw near, so that you may listen. For obedience is much better than the sacrifices of the foolish, who do not know the evil that they are doing.

Ecclesiastes 5

1 You should not speak anything rashly, nor should your heart be hasty to present a word before God. For God is in heaven, and you are on earth. For this reason, let your words be few.

2 Dreams follow many worries, and in many words foolishness will be found.

3 If you have vowed anything to God, you should not delay to repay it. And whatever you have vowed, render it. But an unfaithful and foolish promise displeases him.

4 And it is much better not to make a vow, than, after a vow, not to fulfill what was promised.

5 You should not use your mouth so as to cause your flesh to sin. And you should not say, in the sight of an Angel, "There is no Providence." For God, being angry at your words, may scatter all the works of your hands.

6 Where there are many dreams, there are many vanities and innumerable words. Yet truly, you must fear God.

7 If you see false accusations against the indigent, and violent judgments, and subverted justice in the government, do not be surprised over this situation. For those in high places have others who are higher, and there are still others, more eminent, over these.

8 But finally, there is the King who rules over the entire earth, which is subject to him.

9 A greedy man will not be satisfied by money. And whoever loves wealth will reap no fruit from it. Therefore, this, too, is emptiness.

10 Where there are many riches, there will also be many to consume these things. And how does it benefit the one who possesses, except that he discerns the wealth with his own eyes?

11 Sleep is sweet to one who works, whether he consumes little or much. But the satiation of a wealthy man will not permit him to sleep.

12 There is even another most burdensome infirmity, which I have seen under the sun: wealth kept to the harm of the owner.

13 For they are lost in a most grievous affliction. He has produced a son, who will be in the utmost destitution.

14 Just as he went forth naked from his mother's womb, so shall he return, and he shall take nothing with him from his labors.

15 It is an utterly miserable infirmity that, in the same manner as he has arrived, so shall he return. How then does it benefit him, since he has labored for the wind?

16 All the days of his life he consumes: in darkness, and with many worries, and in distress as well as sadness.

17 And so, this has seemed good to me: that a person should eat and drink, and should enjoy the fruits of his labor, in which he has toiled under the sun, for the number of the days of his life that God has given him. For this is his portion.

18 And this is a gift from God: that every man to whom God has given wealth and resources, and to whom he has granted the ability to consume these, may enjoy his portion, and may find joy in his labors.

19 And then he will not fully remember the days of his life, because God occupies his heart with delights.

Ecclesiastes 6

1 There is also another evil, which I have seen under the sun, and, indeed, it is frequent among men.

2 It is a man to whom God has given wealth, and resources, and honor; and out of all that he desires, nothing is lacking to his life; yet God does not grant him the ability to consume these things, but instead a man who is a stranger will devour them. This is emptiness and a great misfortune.

3 If a man were to produce one hundred children, and to live for many years, and to attain to an age of many days, and if his soul were to make no use of the goods of his resources, and if he were lacking even a burial: concerning such a man, I declare that a miscarried child is better than he.

4 For he arrives without a purpose and he continues on into darkness, and his name shall be wiped away, into oblivion.

5 He has not seen the sun, nor recognized the difference between good and evil.

6 Even if he were to live for two thousand years, and yet not thoroughly enjoy what is good, does not each one hurry on to the same place?

7 Every labor of man is for his mouth, but his soul will not be filled.

8 What do the wise have which is more than the foolish? And what does the pauper have, except to continue on to that place, where there is life?

9 It is better to see what you desire, than to desire what you cannot know. But this, too, is emptiness and a presumption of spirit.

10 Whoever shall be in the future, his name has already been called. And it is known that he is a man and that he is not able to contend in judgment against one who is stronger than himself.

11 There are many words, and many of these, in disputes, hold much emptiness.

Ecclesiastes 7

1 Why is it necessary for a man to seek things that are greater than himself, when he does not know what is advantageous for himself in his life, during the number of the days of his sojourn, and while time passes by like a shadow? Or who will be able to tell him what will be in the future after him under the sun?

2 A good name is better than precious ointments, and a day of death is better than a day of birth.

3 It is better to go to a house of mourning, than to a house of feasting. For in the former, we are admonished about the end of all things, so that the living consider what may be in the future.

4 Anger is better than laughter. For through the sadness of the countenance, the soul of one who offends may be corrected.

5 The heart of the wise is a place of mourning, and the heart of the foolish is a place of rejoicing.

6 It is better to be corrected by a wise man, than to be deceived by the false praise of the foolish.

7 For, like the crackling of thorns burning under a pot, so is the laughter of the foolish. But this, too, is emptiness.

8 A false accusation troubles the wise man and saps the strength of his heart.

9 The end of a speech is better than the beginning. Patience is better than arrogance.

10 Do not be quickly moved to anger. For anger resides in the sinews of the foolish.

11 You should not say: "What do you think is the reason that the former times were better than they are now?" For this type of question is foolish.

12 Wisdom with riches is more useful and more advantageous, for those who see the sun.

13 For as wisdom protects, so also does money protect. But learning and wisdom have this much more: that they grant life to one who possesses them.

14 Consider the works of God, that no one is able to correct whomever he has despised.

15 In good times, enjoy good things, but beware of an evil time. For just as God has establish the one, so also the other, in order that man may not find any just complaint against him.

16 I also saw this, in the days of my vanity: a just man perishing in his justice, and an impious man living a long time in his malice.

17 Do not try to be overly just, and do not try to be more wise than is necessary, lest you become stupid.

18 Do not act with great impiety, and do not choose to be foolish, lest you die before your time.

19 It is good for you to support a just man. Furthermore, you should not withdraw your hand from him, for whoever fears God, neglects nothing.

20 Wisdom has strengthened the wise more than ten princes of a city.

21 But there is no just man on earth, who does good and does not sin.

22 So then, do not attach your heart to every word that is spoken, lest perhaps you may hear your servant speaking ill of you.

23 For your conscience knows that you, too, have repeatedly spoken evil of others.

24 I have tested everything in wisdom. I have said: "I will be wise." And wisdom withdrew farther from me,

25 so much more than it was before. Wisdom is very profound, so who shall reveal her?

26 I have examined all things in my soul, so that I may know, and consider, and seek out wisdom and reason, and so that I may recognize the impiety of the foolish, and the error of the imprudent.

27 And I have discovered a woman more bitter than death: she who is like the snare of a hunter, and whose heart is like a net, and whose hands are like chains. Whoever pleases God shall flee from her. But whoever is a sinner shall be seized by her.

28 Behold, Ecclesiastes said, I have discovered these things, one after another, in order that I might discover the explanation

29 which my soul still seeks and has not found. One man among a thousand, I have found; a woman among them all, I have not found.

30 This alone have I discovered: that God made man righteous, and yet he has adulterated himself with innumerable questions. Who is so great as the wise? And who has understood the meaning of the word?

Ecclesiastes 8

1 The wisdom of a man shines in his countenance, and even the expression of a most powerful man will change.

2 I heed the mouth of the king, and the commandment of an oath to God.

3 You should not hastily withdraw from his presence, nor should you remain in an evil work. For all that pleases him, he will do.

4 And his word is filled with authority. Neither is anyone able to say to him: "Why are you acting this way?"

5 Whoever keeps the commandment will not experience evil. The heart of a wise man understands the time to respond.

6 For every matter, there is a time and an opportunity, as well as many difficulties, for man.

7 For he is ignorant of the past, and he is able to know nothing of the future by means of a messenger.

8 It is not in the power of a man to prohibit the spirit, nor does he have authority over the day of death, nor is he permitted to rest when war breaks out, and neither will impiety save the impious.

9 I have considered all these things, and I have applied my heart to all the works which are being done under the sun. Sometimes one man rules over another to his own harm.

10 I have seen the impious buried. These same, while they were still living, were in the holy place, and they were praised in the city as workers of justice. But this, too, is emptiness.

11 For the sons of men perpetrate evils without any fear, because judgment is not pronounced quickly against the evil.

12 But although a sinner may do evil of himself one hundred times, and by patience still endure, I realize that it will be well with those who fear God, who revere his face.

13 So, may it not go well with the impious, and may his days not be prolonged. And let those who do not fear the face of the Lord pass away like a shadow.

14 There is also another vanity, which is done upon the earth. There are the just, to whom evils happen, as though they had done the works of the impious. And there are the impious, who are very secure, as though they possess the deeds of the just. But this, too, I judge to be a very great vanity.

15 And so, I praised rejoicing, because there was no good for a man under the sun, except to eat and drink, and to be cheerful, and because he may take nothing with him from his labor in the days of his life, which God has given to him under the sun.

16 And I applied my heart, so that I might know wisdom, and so that I might understand a disturbance that turns upon the earth: it is a man, who takes no sleep with his eyes, day and night.

17 And I understood that man is able to find no explanation for all those works of God which are done under the sun. And so, the more that he labors to seek, so much the less does he find. Yes, even if a wise man were to claim that he knows, he would not be able to discover it.

Ecclesiastes 9

1 I have drawn all these things through my heart, so that I might carefully understand. There are just men as well as wise men, and their works are in the hand of God. And yet a man does not know so much as whether he is worthy of love or of hatred.

2 But all things in the future remain uncertain, because all things happen equally to the just and to the impious, to the good and to the bad, to the pure and to the impure, to those who offer sacrifices and to those who despise sacrifices. As the good are, so also are sinners. As those who commit perjury are, so also are those who swear to the truth.

3 This is a very great burden among all things that are done under the sun: that the same things happen to everyone. And when the hearts of the sons of men are filled with malice and contempt in their lives, afterwards they shall be dragged down to hell.

4 There is no one who lives forever, or who even has confidence in this regard. A living dog is better than a dead lion.

5 For the living know that they themselves will die, yet truly the dead know nothing anymore, nor do they have any recompense. For the memory of them is forgotten.

6 Likewise, love and hatred and envy have all perished together, nor have they any place in this age and in the work which is done under the sun.

7 So then, go and eat your bread with rejoicing, and drink your wine with gladness. For your works are pleasing to God.

8 Let your garments be white at all times, and let not oil be absent from your head.

9 Enjoy life with the wife whom you love, all the days of your uncertain life which have been given to you under the sun, during all the time of your vanity. For this is your portion in life and in your labor, with which you labor under the sun.

10 Whatever your hand is able to do, do it earnestly. For neither work, nor reason, nor wisdom, nor knowledge will exist in death, toward which you are hurrying.

11 I turned myself toward another thing, and I saw that under the sun, the race is not to the swift, nor the battle to the strong, nor bread to the wise, nor wealth to the learned, nor grace to the skilful: but there is a time and an end for all these things.

12 Man does not know his own end. But, just as fish are caught with a hook, and birds are captured with a snare, so are men seized in the evil time, when it will suddenly overwhelm them.

13 This wisdom, likewise, I have seen under the sun, and I have examined it intensely.

14 There was a small city, with a few men in it. There came against it a great king, who surrounded it, and built fortifications all around it, and the blockade was completed.

15 And there was found within it, a poor and wise man, and he freed the city through his wisdom, and nothing was recorded afterward of that poor man.

16 And so, I declared that wisdom is better than strength. But how is it, then, that the wisdom of the poor man is treated with contempt, and his words are not heeded?

17 The words of the wise are heard in silence, more so than the outcry of a prince among the foolish.

18 Wisdom is better than weapons of war. And whoever offends in one thing, shall lose many good things.

Ecclesiastes 10

1 Dying flies ruin the sweetness of the ointment. Wisdom and glory is more precious than a brief and limited foolishness.

2 The heart of a wise man is in his right hand, and the heart of a foolish man is in his left hand.

3 Moreover, as a foolish man is walking along the way, even though he himself is unwise, he considers everyone to be foolish.

4 If the spirit of one who holds authority rises over you, do not leave your place, because attentiveness will cause the greatest sins to cease.

5 There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, proceeding from the presence of a prince, as if by mistake:

6 a foolish man appointed to a high dignity, and the rich sitting beneath him.

7 I have seen servants on horses, and princes walking on the ground like servants.

8 Whoever digs a pit will fall into it. And whoever tears apart a hedge, a snake will bite him.

9 Whoever carries away stones will be harmed by them. And whoever cuts down trees will be wounded by them.

10 If the iron is dull, and if it was not that way before, but has been made dull by much labor, then it will be sharpened. And wisdom will follow after diligence.

11 Whoever slanders in secret is nothing less than a snake that bites silently.

12 Words from the mouth of a wise man are graceful, but the lips of a foolish man will throw him down with violence.

13 At the beginning of his words is foolishness, and at the end of his talk is a most grievous error.

14 The fool multiplies his words. A man does not know what has been before him, and who is able to reveal to him what will be in the future after him?

15 The hardship of the foolish will afflict those who do not know to go into the city.

16 Woe to you, the land whose king is a boy, and whose princes consume in the morning.

17 Blessed is the land whose king is noble, and whose princes eat at the proper time, for refreshment and not for self-indulgence.

18 By laziness, a framework shall be brought down, and by the weakness of hands, a house shall collapse through.

19 While laughing, they make bread and wine, so that the living may feast. And all things are obedient to money.

20 You should not slander the king, even in your thoughts, and you should not speak evil of a wealthy man, even in your private chamber. For even the birds of the air will carry your voice, and whatever has wings will announce your opinion.

Ecclesiastes 11

1 Cast your bread over running waters. For, after a long time, you shall find it again.

2 Give a portion to seven, and indeed even to eight. For you do not know what evil may be upon the earth in the future.

3 If the clouds have been filled, they will pour forth rain upon the earth. If a tree falls to the south, or to the north, or to whatever direction it may fall, there it shall remain.

4 Whoever heeds the wind will not sow. And whoever considers the clouds will never reap.

5 In the same manner that you do not know the way of the spirit, nor the way that bones are joined together in the womb of a pregnant woman, so you do not know the works of God, who is the Maker of all.

6 In the morning, sow your seed, and in the evening, do not let your hand cease. For you do not know which of these may rise up, the one or the other. But if both rise up together, so much the better.

7 Light is pleasant, and it is delightful for the eyes to see the sun.

8 If a man lives for many years, and if he has rejoiced in all of these, he must remember the many days of the dark times, which, when they will have arrived, will accuse the past of vanity.

9 So then, rejoice, O young man, in your youth, and let your heart remain in what is good during the days of your youth. And walk in the ways of your heart, and with the perception of your eyes. And know that, concerning all these things, God will bring you to judgment.

10 Remove anger from your heart, and set aside evil from your flesh. For youth and pleasure are empty.

Ecclesiastes 12

1 Remember your Creator in the days of your youth, before the time of affliction arrives and the years draw near, about which you will say, "These do not please me."

2 Before the sun, and the light, and the moon, and the stars are darkened and the clouds return after the rain,

3 when the guardians of the house will tremble, and the strongest men will waver, and those who grind grain will be idle, except for a small number, and those who look through the keyholes will be darkened.

4 And they will close the doors to the street, when the voice of he who grinds the grain will be humbled, and they will be disturbed at the sound of a flying thing, and all the daughters of song shall become deaf.

5 Likewise, they will fear the things above them, and they will dread the way. The almond tree will flourish; the locust will be fattened; and the caper plant will scattered, because man shall go into the house of his eternity, and the mourners shall wander around in the street.

6 Before the silver cord is broken, and the golden band pulls away, and the pitcher is crushed over the fountain, and the wheel is broken above the cistern,

7 and the dust returns to its earth, from which it was, and the spirit returns to God, who granted it.

8 Vanity of vanities, said Ecclesiastes, and all is vanity!

9 And since Ecclesiastes was very wise, he taught the people, and he described what he had accomplished. And while searching, he composed many parables.

10 He sought useful words, and he wrote most righteous words, which were full of truth.

11 The words of the wise are like a goad, and like nails deeply fastened, which, through the counsel of teachers, are set forth by one pastor.

12 You should require no more than this, my son. For there is no end to the making of many books. And excessive study is an affliction to the flesh.

13 Let us all listen together to the end of the discourse. Fear God, and observe his commandments. This is everything for man.

14 And so, for all that is done and for each error, God will bring judgment: whether it was good or evil.

Song of Solomon 1

1 Bride: May he kiss me with the kiss of his mouth.

2 Groom to Bride: So much better than wine are your breasts, fragranced with the finest perfumes.

3 Bride to Groom: Your name is oil that has been poured out; therefore, the maidens have loved you. Draw me forward.

4 Chorus to Bride: We will run after you in the odor of your perfumes.

5 Bride to Chorus: The king has led me into his storerooms.

6 Chorus to Bride: We will exult and rejoice in you, remembering your breasts above wine.

7 Groom to Bride: The righteous love you.

8 Bride to Chorus: O daughters of Jerusalem: I am black, but shapely, like the tabernacles of Kedar, like the tents of Solomon.

9 Do not be concerned that I am dark, for the sun has changed my color.

10 The sons of my mother have fought against me. They have made me the keeper of the vineyards. My own vineyard I have not kept.

11 Bride to Groom: Reveal to me, you whom my soul loves, where you pasture, where you recline at midday, lest I begin to wander after the flocks of your companions.

12 Groom to Bride: If you yourself do not know, O most beautiful among women, then go out and follow after the steps of the flocks, and pasture your young goats beside the tabernacles of the shepherds.

13 O my love, I have compared you to my company of horsemen against the chariots of Pharaoh.

14 Your cheeks are beautiful, like those of a turtledove. Your neck is like a bejeweled collar.

15 Chorus to Bride: We will fashion for you chains of gold, accented with reddened silver.

16 Bride to Chorus: While the king was taking his rest, my aromatic ointment sent forth its odor.

17 My beloved is a bundle of myrrh to me. He shall abide between my breasts.

18 My beloved is a cluster of Cyprus grapes to me, in the vineyards of Engaddi.

19 Groom to Bride: Behold, you are beautiful, O my love. Behold, you are beautiful. Your eyes are those of a dove.

20 Bride to Groom: Behold, you are handsome, O my beloved, and graceful. Our bed is flourishing.

21 Groom to Bride: The timbers of our houses are of cedar; our ceilings are of cypress.

Song of Solomon 2

1 Bride: I am a flower of the open field and a lily of the steep valleys.

2 Groom: Like a lily among the thorns, so is my loved one among the daughters.

3 Bride to Chorus: Like an apple tree among the trees of the forest, so is my beloved among the sons. I sat beneath the shadow of the one whom I desired, and his fruit was sweet to my palate.

4 He brought me into the storeroom of wine. He set charity in order within me.

5 Prop me up with flowers. Close me in with apples. For I languish through love.

6 His left hand is under my head, and his right hand shall embrace me.

7 Groom to Chorus: I bind you by oath, O daughters of Jerusalem, by the does and the stags of the open field, not to disturb or awaken the beloved, even for as long as she wills.

8 Bride to Chorus: The voice of my beloved! Behold, he arrives leaping along the mountains, jumping across the hills.

9 My beloved is like a doe and like a young stag.

10 Lo, he stands beyond our wall, gazing through the windows, watching through the lattices.

11 Lo, my beloved speaks to me:

12 Groom to Bride: Rise up, quickly, my love, my dove, my shapely one, and advance.

13 For winter has now past; the rain has decreased and gone away.

14 The flowers have appeared in our land; the time for pruning has arrived. The voice of the turtledove has been heard in our land.

15 The fig tree has brought forth its green figs; the flowering vines bestow their odor. Rise up, my love, my brilliant one, and advance.

16 My dove in the clefts of the rock, in the hollows of the wall, reveal to me your face. Let your voice sound in my ears. For your voice is sweet, and your face is graceful.

17 Chorus to Groom and Bride: Capture for us the little foxes, which are tearing down the vines; for our vineyard has flourished.

18 Bride to Chorus: My beloved is for me, and I am for him. He pastures among the lilies, until the day rises and the shadows decline.

19 Bride to Groom: Return, O my beloved. Be like a doe and like a young stag upon the mountains of Bether.

Song of Solomon 3

1 Bride: On my bed, throughout the night, I sought him whom my soul loves. I sought him, and did not find him.

2 I will rise up, and I will circle through the city. Through the side streets and thoroughfares, I will seek him whom my soul loves. I sought him, and did not find him.

3 The watchers who guard the city found me: "Have you seen him whom my soul loves?"

4 When I had passed by them a little, I found him whom my soul loves. I held him, and would not release him, until I would bring him into my mother's house, and into the chamber of her who bore me.

5 Groom to Chorus: I bind you by oath, O daughters of Jerusalem, by the does and the stags of the open field, not to disturb or awaken the beloved, until she wills.

6 Chorus to Groom: Who is she, who ascends through the desert, like a staff of smoke from the aromatics of myrrh, and frankincense, and every powder of the perfumer?

7 Chorus to Bride: Lo, sixty strong ones, out of all the strongest in Israel, stand watch at the bed of Solomon,

8 all holding swords and well-trained in warfare, each one's weapon upon his thigh, because of fears in the night.

9 Bride to Chorus: King Solomon made himself a portable throne from the wood of Lebanon.

10 He made its columns of silver, the reclining place of gold, the ascent of purple; the middle he covered well, out of charity for the daughters of Jerusalem.

11 O daughters of Zion, go forth and see king Solomon with the diadem with which his mother crowned him, on the day of his espousal, on the day of the rejoicing of his heart.

Song of Solomon 4

1 Groom to Bride: How beautiful you are, my love, how beautiful you are! Your eyes are those of a dove, except for what is hidden within. Your hair is like flocks of goats, which ascend along the mountain of Gilead.

2 Your teeth are like flocks of shorn sheep, which ascend from the washing, each one with its identical twin, and not one among them is barren.

3 Your lips are like a scarlet ribbon, and your eloquence is sweetness. Like a piece of pomegranate, so are your cheeks, except for what is hidden within.

4 Your neck is like the tower of David, which was built with ramparts: a thousand shields are hanging from it, all the armor of the strong.

5 Your two breasts are like two young does, twins that pasture among the lilies.

6 Until the day rises and the shadows decline, I will go to the mountain of myrrh and to the hill of frankincense.

7 You are totally beautiful, my love, and there is no blemish in you.

8 Advance from Lebanon, my spouse, advance from Lebanon, advance. You shall be crowned at the head of Amana, near the summit of Senir and Hermon, by the dens of lions, by the mountains of leopards.

9 You have wounded my heart, my sister, my spouse. You have wounded my heart with one look of your eyes, and with one lock of hair on your neck.

10 How beautiful are your breasts, my sister, my spouse! Your breasts are more beautiful than wine, and the fragrance of your ointments is above all aromatic oils.

11 Your lips, my spouse, are a dripping honeycomb; honey and milk are under your tongue. And the fragrance of your garments is like the odor of frankincense.

12 An enclosed garden is my sister, my spouse: an enclosed garden, a sealed fountain.

13 You send forth a paradise of pomegranates along with the fruits of the orchard: Cypress grapes, with aromatic oil;

14 aromatic oil and saffron; sweet cane and cinnamon, with all the trees of Lebanon; myrrh and aloe, with all the best ointments.

15 The fountain of the gardens is a well of living waters, which flow forcefully from Lebanon.

16 Rise up, north wind, and advance, south wind. Send a breeze through my garden, and carry its aromatic scents.

Song of Solomon 5

1 Bride: May my beloved enter into his garden, and eat the fruit of his apple trees.

2 Groom to Bride: I have arrived in my garden, O my sister, my spouse. I have harvested my myrrh, with my aromatic oils. I have eaten the honeycomb with my honey. I have drunk my wine with my milk. Eat, O friends, and drink, and be inebriated, O most beloved.

3 Bride: I sleep, yet my heart watches. The voice of my beloved knocking:

4 Groom to Bride: Open to me, my sister, my love, my dove, my immaculate one. For my head is full of dew, and the locks of my hair are full of the drops of the night.

5 Bride: I have taken off my tunic; how shall I be clothed in it? I have washed my feet; how shall I spoil them?

6 My beloved put his hand through the window, and my inner self was moved by his touch.

7 I rose up in order to open to my beloved. My hands dripped with myrrh, and my fingers were full of the finest myrrh.

8 I opened the bolt of my door to my beloved. But he had turned aside and had gone away. My soul melted when he spoke. I sought him, and did not find him. I called, and he did not answer me.

9 The keepers who circulate through the city found me. They struck me, and wounded me. The keepers of the walls took my veil away from me.

10 I bind you by oath, O daughters of Jerusalem, if you find my beloved, announce to him that I languish through love.

11 Chorus to Bride: What kind of beloved is your beloved, O most beautiful among women? What kind of beloved is your beloved, so that you would bind us by oath?

12 Bride: My beloved is white and ruddy, elect among thousands.

13 His head is like the finest gold. His locks are like the heights of palm trees, and as black as a raven.

14 His eyes are like doves, which have been washed with milk over rivulets of waters, and which reside near plentiful streams.

15 His cheeks are like a courtyard of aromatic plants, sown by perfumers. His lips are like lilies, dripping with the best myrrh.

16 His hands are smoothed gold, full of hyacinths. His abdomen is ivory, accented with sapphires.

17 His legs are columns of marble, which have been established over bases of gold. His appearance is like that of Lebanon, elect like the cedars.

18 His throat is most sweet, and he is entirely desirable. Such is my beloved, and he is my friend, O daughters of Jerusalem.

19 Chorus to Bride: Where has your beloved gone, O most beautiful among women? To where has your beloved turned aside, so that we may seek him with you?

Song of Solomon 6

1 Bride: My beloved has descended to his garden, to the courtyard of aromatic plants, in order to pasture in the gardens and gather the lilies.

2 I am for my beloved, and my beloved is for me. He pastures among the lilies.

3 Groom to Bride: My love, you are beautiful: sweet and graceful, like Jerusalem; terrible, like an army in battle array.

4 Avert your eyes from me, for they have caused me fly away. Your hair is like a flock of goats, which have appeared out of Gilead.

5 Your teeth are like a flock of sheep, which have ascended from the washing, each one with its identical twin, and not one among them is barren.

6 Like the skin of a pomegranate, so are your cheeks, except for your hiddenness.

7 There are sixty queens, and eighty concubines, and maidens without number.

8 One is my dove, my perfect one. One is her mother; elect is she who bore her. The daughters saw her, and they proclaimed her most blessed. The queens and concubines saw her, and they praised her.

9 Chorus to Groom: Who is she, who advances like the rising dawn, as beautiful as the moon, as elect as the sun, as terrible as an army in battle array?

10 Bride: I descended to the garden of nuts, in order to see the fruits of the steep valleys, and to examine whether the vineyard had flourished and the pomegranates had produced buds.

11 I did not understand. My soul was stirred up within me because of the chariots of Amminadab.

12 Chorus to Bride: Return, return, O Sulamitess. Return, return, so that we may consider you.

Song of Solomon 7

1 Chorus to Groom: What will you see in the Sulamitess, other than choruses of encampments?

2 Chorus to Bride: How beautiful are your footsteps in shoes, O daughter of a ruler! The joints of your thighs are like jewels, which have been fabricated by the hand of an artist.

3 Your navel is a round bowl, never lacking in curvature. Your abdomen is like a bundle of wheat, surrounded with lilies.

4 Your two breasts are like two young twin does.

5 Your neck is like a tower of ivory. Your eyes like the fish ponds at Heshbon, which are at the entrance to the daughter of the multitude. Your nose is like the tower of Lebanon, which looks out toward Damascus.

6 Your head is like Carmel, and the hairs of your head are like the purple of the king, bound into pleats.

7 Most beloved one, how beautiful you are, and how graceful in delights!

8 Your stature is comparable to the palm tree, and your breasts to clusters of grapes.

9 Groom: I said, I will ascend to the palm tree, and take hold of its fruit. And your breasts will be like clusters of grapes on the vine. And the fragrance of your mouth will be like apples.

10 Bride: Your throat is like the finest wine: wine worthy for my beloved to drink, and for his lips and teeth to contemplate.

11 I am for my beloved, and his turning is to me.

12 Approach, my beloved. Let us go out into the field; let us linger in the villages.

13 Let us go up in the morning to the vineyards; let us see if the vineyard has flourished, if the flowers are ready to bear fruit, if the pomegranates have flourished. There I will give my breasts to you.

14 The mandrakes yield their fragrance. At our gates is every fruit. The new and the old, my beloved, I have kept for you.

Song of Solomon 8

1 Bride to Groom: Who will give you to me as my brother, feeding from the breasts of my mother, so that I may discover you outside, and may kiss you, and so that now no one may despise me?

2 I will take hold of you and lead you into my mother's house. There you will teach me, and I will give you a cup of spiced wine, and of new wine from my pomegranates.

3 His left hand is under my head, and his right hand shall embrace me.

4 Groom to Chorus: I bind you by oath, O daughters of Jerusalem, not to disturb or awaken the beloved, until she wills.

5 Chorus to Groom: Who is she, who ascends from the desert, flowing with delights, leaning upon her beloved?

6 Groom to Bride: Under the apple tree, I awakened you. There your mother was corrupted. There she who bore you was violated.

7 Set me like a seal upon your heart, like a seal upon your arm. For love is strong, like death, and envy is enduring, like hell: their lamps are made of fire and flames.

8 A multitude of waters cannot extinguish love, nor can a river overwhelm it. If a man were to give all the substance of his house in exchange for love, he would despise it as nothing.

9 Chorus: Our sister is little and has no breasts. What shall we do for our sister on the day when she is called upon?

10 If she is a wall, let us build a rampart of silver upon it. If she is a door, let us join it together with boards of cedar.

11 Bride to Chorus: I am a wall, and my breasts are like towers, since, in his presence, I have become like one who has discovered peace.

12 The peaceful one had a vineyard, in that which held the peoples. He handed it on to the caretakers; a man brought, in exchange for its fruit, a thousand pieces of silver.

13 Groom: My vineyard is before me. The thousand is for your peacefulness, and two hundred is for those who care for its fruit.

14 Bride to Groom: Your friends are attentive to those who have been dwelling in the gardens. Cause me to heed your voice.

15 Flee away, my beloved, and become like the doe and the young stag upon the mountains of aromatic plants.

Isaiah 1

1 The vision of Isaiah, the son of Amoz, which he saw concerning Judah and Jerusalem, in the days of Uzziah, Joatham, Ahaz, and Hezekiah, kings of Judah.

2 Listen, O heavens, and pay attention, O earth, for the Lord has spoken. I have nurtured and raised children, but they have spurned me.

3 An ox knows his owner, and a donkey knows the manger of his lord, but Israel has not known me, and my people have not understood.

4 Woe to a sinful nation, a people burdened by iniquity, a wicked offspring, accursed children. They have abandoned the Lord. They have blasphemed the Holy One of Israel. They been taken away backwards.

5 For what reason shall I continue to strike you, as you increase transgressions? The entire head is feeble, and the entire heart is grieving.

6 From the sole of the foot, even to the top of the head, there is no soundness within. Wounds and bruises and swelling sores: these are not bandaged, nor treated with medicine, nor soothed with oil.

7 Your land is desolate. Your cities have been set ablaze. Foreigners devour your countryside in your sight, and it will become desolate, as if devastated by enemies.

8 And the daughter of Zion will be left behind, like an arbor in a vineyard, and like a shelter in a cucumber field, and like a city being laid to waste.

9 If the Lord of hosts had not bequeathed us offspring, we would have been like Sodom, and we would have been comparable to Gomorrah.

10 Listen to the Word of the Lord, you leaders of the people of Sodom. Listen closely to the law of our God, O people of Gomorrah.

11 The multitude of your sacrifices, what is that to me, says the Lord? I am full. I do not desire holocausts of rams, nor the fat of fatlings, nor the blood of calves and of lambs and of he-goats.

12 When you approach before my sight, who is it that requires these things from your hands, so that you would walk in my courts?

13 You should no longer offer sacrifice vain. Incense is an abomination to me. The new moons and the Sabbaths and the other feast days, I will not receive. Your gatherings are iniquitous.

14 My soul hates your days of proclamation and your solemnities. They have become bothersome to me. I labor to endure them.

15 And so, when you extend your hands, I will avert my eyes from you. And when you multiply your prayers, I will not heed you. For your hands are full of blood.

16 Wash, become clean, take away the evil of your intentions from my eyes. Cease to act perversely.

17 Learn to do good. Seek judgment, support the oppressed, judge for the orphan, defend the widow.

18 And then approach and accuse me, says the Lord. Then, if your sins are like scarlet, they shall be made white like snow; and if they are red like vermillion, they shall become white like wool.

19 If you are willing, and you listen to me, then you will eat the good things of the land.

20 But if you are not willing, and you provoke me to anger, then the sword will devour you. For the mouth of the Lord has spoken.

21 How has the faithful city, full of judgment, become a harlot? Justice lived in her, but now murderers.

22 Your silver has turned into dross. Your wine has been mixed with water.

23 Your leaders are unfaithful, the associates of thieves. They all love gifts; they pursue rewards. They do not judge for orphans, and the widow's case is not brought before them.

24 Because of this, the Lord God of hosts, the Strength of Israel, says: Ah! I will be consoled over my enemies, and I will be vindicated from my adversaries.

25 And I will turn my hand to you. And I will temper your dross unto purity, and I will take away all your tin.

26 And I will restore your judges, so that they will be as before, and your counselors as in times long past. After this, you shall be called the City of the Just, the Faithful City.

27 Zion will be redeemed in judgment, and they will lead her back to justice.

28 And he shall crush the accursed and sinners together. And those who have abandoned the Lord will be consumed.

29 For they shall be confounded because of the idols, to which they have sacrificed. And you shall be ashamed over the gardens that you chose,

30 when you were like an oak with falling leaves, and like a garden without water.

31 And your strength will be like the embers from stubble, and your work will be like a spark, and both will burn together, and there will be no one to extinguish it.

Isaiah 2

1 The word that Isaiah, the son of Amoz, saw concerning Judah and Jerusalem.

2 And in the last days, the mountain of the house of the Lord will be prepared at the summit of the mountains, and it will be exalted above the hills, and all the nations shall flow to it.

3 And many peoples will go, and they will say: "Let us approach and ascend to the mountain of the Lord, and to the house of the God of Jacob. And he will teach us his ways, and we will walk in his paths." For the law will go forth from Zion, and the Word of the Lord from Jerusalem.

4 And he will judge the nations, and he will rebuke many peoples. And they shall forge their swords into plowshares, and their spears into sickles. Nation will not lift up sword against nation, neither will they continue to train for battle.

5 O house of Jacob, let us approach and walk in the light of the Lord.

6 For you have cast aside your people, the house of Jacob, because they have been filled up, as in past times, and because they have had soothsayers as the Philistines have, and because they have joined themselves to foreign servants.

7 Their land has been filled with silver and gold. And there is no end to their storehouses.

8 And their land has been filled with horses. And their four-horse chariots are innumerable. And their land has been filled with idols. They have adored the work of their hands, which their own fingers have made.

9 And man has bowed himself down, and so man has become debased. Therefore, you should not forgive them.

10 Enter into the rock, and hide in a ditch in the soil, from the presence of the fear of the Lord, and from the glory of his majesty.

11 The lofty eyes of man have been humbled, and the haughtiness of men will be bowed down. Then the Lord alone shall be exalted, in that day.

12 For the day of the Lord of hosts will prevail over all the proud and self-exalted, and over all the arrogant, and each one shall be humbled,

13 and over all the straight and tall cedars of Lebanon, and over all the oaks of Bashan;

14 and over all the lofty mountains, and over all the elevated hills;

15 and over every lofty tower, and over every fortified wall;

16 and over all the ships of Tarshish, and over all the beauty that may be seen.

17 And the loftiness of men will be bowed down, and the haughtiness of men will be brought low. And the Lord alone shall be exalted, in that day.

18 And idols will be thoroughly crushed.

19 And they will go into the caves of the rocks, and into the caverns of the earth, from the presence of the dread of the Lord, and from the glory of his majesty, when he will have risen up to strike the earth.

20 In that day, man shall cast aside his idols of silver and his images of gold, which he had made for himself, as if to reverence the moles and the bats.

21 And so he will go into the clefts of the rocks, and into the caverns of stone, from the presence of the dread of the Lord, and from the glory of his majesty, when he will have risen up to strike the earth.

22 Therefore, rest away from man, whose breath is in his nostrils, for he considers himself to be exalted.

Isaiah 3

1 For behold, the sovereign Lord of hosts will take away, from Jerusalem and from Judah, the powerful and the strong: all the strength from bread, and all the strength from water;

2 the strong man, and the man of war, the judge and the prophet, and the seer and the elder;

3 the leader over fifty and the honorable in appearance; and the counselor, and the wise among builders, and the skillful in mystical speech.

4 And I will provide children as their leaders, and the effeminate will rule over them.

5 And the people will rush, man against man, and each one against his neighbor. The child shall rebel against the elder, and the ignoble against the noble.

6 For a man will apprehend his brother, from the household of his own father, saying: "The vestment is yours. Be our leader, but let this ruin be under your hand."

7 In that day, he will respond by saying: "I am not a healer, and there is no bread or vestment in my house. Do not choose to appoint me as a leader of the people."

8 For Jerusalem is ruined, and Judah has fallen, because their words and their plans are against the Lord, in order to provoke the eyes of his majesty.

9 The acknowledgement of their countenance is their response. For they have proclaimed their own sin, like Sodom; and they have not concealed it. Woe to their souls! For evils are being repaid to them.

10 Tell the just man that it is well, for he shall eat from the fruit from his own plans.

11 Woe to the impious man immersed in evil! For retribution will be given to him from his own hands.

12 As for my people, their oppressors have despoiled them, and women have ruled over them. My people, who call you blessed, the same are deceiving you and disrupting the path of your steps.

13 The Lord stands for judgment, and he stands to judge the people.

14 The Lord will enter into judgment with the elders of his people, and with their leaders. For you have been devouring the vineyard, and the plunder from the poor is in your house.

15 Why do you wear down my people, and grind up the faces of the poor, says the Lord, the God of hosts?

16 And the Lord said: Because the daughters of Zion have been lifted up, and have walked with extended necks and winking eyes, because they have continued on, walking noisily and advancing with a pretentious stride,

17 the Lord will make the heads of the daughters of Zion bald, and the Lord will strip them of the locks of their hair.

18 In that day, the Lord will take away their decorative shoes,

19 and the little moons and chains, and the necklaces and bracelets, and the hats,

20 and the ornaments for their hair, and the anklets, and the touches of myrrh and little bottles of perfumes, and the earrings,

21 and the rings, and the jewels hanging on their foreheads,

22 and the continual changes in appearance, and the short skirts, and the fine linens and embroidered cloths,

23 and the mirrors, and scarves, and ribbons, and their sparse clothing.

24 And in place of a sweet fragrance, there will be stench. And in place of a belt, there will be a rope. And in place of stylish hair, there will be baldness. And in place of a blouse, there will be haircloth.

25 Likewise, your most handsome men will fall by the sword, and your strong men will fall in battle.

26 And her gates will grieve and mourn. And she will sit on the ground, desolate.

Isaiah 5

1 I will sing to my beloved the canticle of my paternal cousin, about his vineyard. A vineyard was made for my beloved, at the horn in the son of oil.

2 And he fenced it in, and he picked the stones out of it, and he planted it with the best vines, and he built a tower in the middle of it, and he set up a winepress within it. And he expected it to produce grapes, but it produced wild vines.

3 Now then, inhabitants of Jerusalem and men of Judah: judge between me and my vineyard.

4 What more should I have done for my vineyard that I did not do for it? Should I not have expected it to produce grapes, though it produced wild vines?

5 And now, I will reveal to you what I will do to my vineyard. I will take away its fence, and it will be plundered. I will pull down its wall, and it will be trampled.

6 And I will make it desolate. It will not be pruned, and it will not be dug. And briers and thorns will rise up. And I will command the clouds not to rain upon it.

7 For the vineyard of the Lord of hosts is the house of Israel. And the man of Judah is his delightful seedling. And I expected that he would do judgment, and behold iniquity, and that he would do justice, and behold an outcry.

8 Woe to you who join house to house, and who combine field to field, even to the limits of the place! Do you intend to live alone in the midst of the earth?

9 These things are in my ears, says the Lord of hosts. Otherwise, many houses, great and beautiful, will become desolate, without an inhabitant.

10 Then ten acres of vineyard will produce one small bottle of wine, and thirty measures of seed will produce three measures of grain.

11 Woe to you who rise up in the morning to pursue drunkenness, and to drink even until evening, so as to be inflamed with wine.

12 Harp and lyre and timbrel and pipe, as well as wine, are at your feasts. But you do not respect the work of the Lord, nor do you consider the works of his hands.

13 Because of this, my people have been led away as captives, for they did not have knowledge, and their nobles have passed away from famine, and their multitudes have dried up from thirst.

14 For this reason, Hell has expanded its soul, and has opened its mouth without any limits. And their strong ones, and their people, and their exalted and glorious ones will descend into it.

15 And man will be bowed down, and man will be humbled, and the eyes of the exalted will be brought low.

16 And the Lord of hosts will be exalted in judgment, and the holy God will be sanctified in justice.

17 And the lambs will pasture in proper order, and new arrivals will eat from the deserts turned into fertile lands.

18 Woe to you who draw iniquity with cords of vanity, and who draw sin as if with the rope of a cart,

19 and who say: "Let him hurry, and let his work arrive soon, so that we may see it. And let the plan of the Holy One of Israel approach and arrive, so that we may know it."

20 Woe to you who call evil good, and good evil; who substitute darkness for light, and light for darkness; who exchange bitter for sweet, and sweet for bitter!

21 Woe to you who are wise in your own eyes, and prudent in your own sight!

22 Woe to you who are powerful at drinking wine, who are strong men in contriving inebriation!

23 For you justify an impious man in exchange for bribes, and you carry away the justice of a just man from him.

24 Because of this, as the tongue of fire devours stubble, and as the heat of a flame burns it completely, so will their root become like glowing embers, and so will their offshoot ascend like dust. For they have cast aside the law of the Lord of hosts, and they have blasphemed the eloquence of the Holy One of Israel.

25 For this reason, the fury of the Lord has been enraged against his people, and he has extended his hand over them, and he has struck them. And the mountains were disturbed. And their carcasses became like dung in the midst of the streets. After all this, his fury was not turned away; instead, his hand was still extended.

26 And he will lift up a sign to nations far away, and he will whistle to them from the ends of the earth. And behold, they will rush forward speedily.

27 There is no one weak or struggling among them. They will not become drowsy, and they will not sleep. Neither will the belt around their waist be loosened, nor the laces of their boots be broken.

28 Their arrows are sharp, and all their bows are taut. The hoofs of their horses are like flint, and their wheels are like the force of a tempest.

29 Their roaring is like the lion; they will roar like young lions. They will both roar and seize their prey. And they will wrap themselves around it, and there will be no one who can rescue it.

30 And in that day, they will make a noise over it, like the sound of the sea. We will gaze out toward the land, and behold, the darkness of the tribulation, and even the light has been darkened by its gloom.

Isaiah 6

1 In the year in which king Uzziah died, I saw the Lord sitting on a throne, sublime and exalted, and the things that were under him filled the temple.

2 The Seraphims were standing above the throne. One had six wings, and the other had six wings: with two they were covering his face, and with two they were covering his feet, and with two they were flying.

3 And they were crying out to one another, and saying: "Holy, holy, holy is the Lord God of hosts! All the earth is filled with his glory!"

4 And the lintels above the hinges were shaken at the voice of the one crying out. And the house was filled with smoke.

5 And I said: "Woe to me! For I have remained silent. For I am a man of unclean lips, and I live in the midst of a people having unclean lips, and I have seen with my eyes the King, the Lord of hosts!"

6 And one of the Seraphims flew to me, and in his hand was a burning coal, which he had taken with tongs from the altar.

7 And he touched my mouth, and he said, "Behold, this has touched your lips, and so your iniquities will be taken away, and your sin will be cleansed."

8 And I heard the voice of the Lord, saying: "Whom shall I send?" and, "Who will go for us?" And I said: "Here I am. Send me."

9 And he said: "Go forth! And you shall say to this people: 'When you listen, you will hear and not understand. And when you see a vision, you will not comprehend.'

10 Blind the heart of this people. Make their ears heavy and close their eyes, lest they see with their eyes, and hear with their ears, and understand with their heart, and be converted, and then I would heal them."

11 And I said, "For how long, O Lord?" And he said, "Until the cities are desolate, without an inhabitant, and the houses are without a man, and the land will be left behind, deserted."

12 For the Lord will take the men far away, and she who will have been left behind will be multiplied in the midst of the earth.

13 But still, there will be a tithing within her, and she will be converted, and she will be put on display, like a terebinth tree and like an oak which extends its branches. And what will remain standing within her will be a holy offspring.

Isaiah 7

1 And it happened in the days of Ahaz, the son of Jotham, the son of Uzziah, the king of Judah, that Rezin, the king of Syria, and Pekah, the son of Remaliah, king of Israel, ascended to Jerusalem to battle against it. But they were not able to defeat it.

2 And they reported to the house of David, saying: "Syria has withdrawn to Ephraim." And his heart was shaken, with the heart of his people, just as the trees of the forest are moved by the face of the wind.

3 And the Lord said to Isaiah: Go out to meet Ahaz, you and your son, Jashub, who was left behind, to the end of the aqueduct, at the upper pool, on the road to the fuller's field.

4 And you shall say to him: "See to it that you are silent. Do not be afraid. And have no dread in your heart over the two tails of these firebrands, nearly extinguished, which are the wrath of the fury of Rezin, king of Syria, and of the son of Remaliah."

5 For Syria has undertaken a plan against you, with the evil of Ephraim and the son of Remaliah, saying:

6 "Let us ascend to Judah, and stir it up, and tear it away for ourselves, and appoint the son of Tabeel as a king in its midst."

7 Thus says the Lord God: This shall not stand, and this shall not be.

8 For the head of Syria is Damascus, and the head of Damascus is Rezin; and within sixty-five years from now, Ephraim will cease to be a people.

9 For the head of Ephraim is Samaria, and the head of Samaria is the son of Remaliah. If you will not believe, you will not continue.

10 And the Lord spoke further to Ahaz, saying:

11 Ask for a sign for yourself from the Lord your God, from the depths below, even to the heights above.

12 And Ahaz said, "I will not ask, for I will not tempt the Lord."

13 And he said: "Then listen, O house of David. Is it such a small thing for you to trouble men, that you must also trouble my God?

14 For this reason, the Lord himself will grant to you a sign. Behold, a virgin will conceive, and she will give birth to a son, and his name will be called Immanuel.

15 He will eat butter and honey, so that he may know to reject evil and to choose good.

16 But even before the boy knows to refuse evil and to choose good, the land that you detest will be abandoned by the face of her two kings.

17 The Lord will lead over you, and over your people, and over the house of your father, such days as have not occurred since the days of the separation of Ephraim from Judah by the king of the Assyrians.

18 And this shall be in that day: the Lord will call for the fly, which is in the most distant parts of the rivers of Egypt, and for the swarm, which is in the land of Assur.

19 And they will arrive, and they all will rest in the torrents of the valleys, and in the caverns of the rocks, and in every thicket, and in every opening.

20 In that day, the Lord will shave with a razor the ones hired by those who are across the river, by the king of the Assyrians, from the head to the hairs of the feet, with the entire beard.

21 And this shall be in that day: a man will raise a cow among oxen, and two sheep,

22 and, instead of an abundance of milk, he will eat butter. For all who are left behind in the midst of the land will eat butter and honey.

23 And this shall be in that day: every place, where there were a thousand grapevines worth a thousand pieces of silver, will become thorns and briers.

24 They will enter such places with arrows and bows. For briers and thorns will be throughout the entire land.

25 But as for all the mountains, which will be dug with a hoe, the terror of thorns and briers will not approach those places. And there will be pasture land for oxen, and a range for cattle."

Isaiah 8

1 And the Lord said to me: "Take up for yourself a large book, and with a man's pen write in it: 'Take away the spoils quickly; plunder swiftly.' "

2 And I summoned to myself faithful witnesses: Uriah, the priest, and Zechariah, the son of Berechiah.

3 And I joined with the prophetess, and she conceived and gave birth to a son. And the Lord said to me: "Call his name: 'Rush to take away the spoils; Hurry to be plundered.'

4 For before the boy knows how to call to his father and his mother, the strength of Damascus and the spoils of Samaria will be taken away, in the sight of the king of the Assyrians."

5 And the Lord spoke to me further, saying:

6 "Because this people has cast aside the waters of Shiloah, which go forth silently, and has instead chosen Rezin and the son of Remaliah,

7 for this reason, behold, the Lord will lead over them the waters of a river, strong and plentiful: the king of the Assyrians with all his glory. And he will rise up throughout all his streams, and he will overflow all his banks.

8 And he will pass through Judah, inundating it, and he will cross over and arrive, even at its neck. And he will extend his wings, filling the breadth of your land, O Immanuel."

9 O people, gather together, and be conquered! All distant lands, listen! Be strengthened, and be conquered! Gird yourselves, and be conquered!

10 Undertake a plan, and it will be dissipated! Speak a word, and it will not be done! For God is with us.

11 For the Lord said this to me, and he has instructed this to me with a strong hand, lest I go forth in the way of this people, saying:

12 "You should not say 'It is conspiracy!' For all that this people speaks is a conspiracy. And you should be frightened or alarmed with their fear.

13 Sanctify the Lord of hosts himself. Let him be your dread, and let him be your fear.

14 And so shall he be a sanctification to you. But he will be a stone of offense and a rock of scandal to the two houses of Israel, and a snare and a ruin to the inhabitants of Jerusalem.

15 And very many of them will stumble and fall, and they will be broken and entangled and seized.

16 Bind the testimony, seal the law, among my disciples."

17 And I will wait for the Lord, who has concealed his face from the house of Jacob, and I will stand before him.

18 Behold: I and my children, whom the Lord has given to me as a sign and a portent, in Israel, from the Lord of hosts, who lives on Mount Zion.

19 And though they say to you, "Seek from seers and diviners," they who hiss in their incantations, should not the people seek from their God, for the sake of the living, and not from the dead?

20 And this is, moreover, for the sake of the law and the testimony. But if they do not speak according to this Word, then he will not have the morning light.

21 And he will pass by it; he will fall and become hungry. And when he is hungry, he will become angry, and he will speak evil against his king and his God, and he will lift himself upward.

22 And he will gaze downward to the earth, and behold: tribulation and darkness, dissolution and distress, and a pursuing gloom. For he will not be able to fly away from its distress.

Isaiah 9

1 In the earlier time, the land of Zebulun and the land of Naphtali were lifted up. But in the later time, the way of the sea beyond the Jordan, the Galilee of the Gentiles, was weighed down.

2 The people who walked in darkness have seen a great light. A light has risen for the inhabitants of the region of the shadow of death.

3 You have increased the nation, but you have not increased the rejoicing. They will rejoice before you, like those who rejoice at the harvest, like the victorious exulting after capturing the prey, when they divide the spoils.

4 For you have prevailed over the yoke of their burden, and over the rod of their shoulder, and over the scepter of their oppressor, as in the day of Midian.

5 For every violent plunder with a tumult, and every garment mixed with blood, will be burned up and will become fuel for the fire.

6 For unto us a child is born, and unto us a son is given. And leadership is placed upon his shoulder. And his name shall be called: wonderful Counselor, mighty God, father of the future age, Prince of Peace.

7 His reign will be increased, and there will be no end to his peace. He will sit upon the throne of David and over his kingdom, to confirm and strengthen it, in judgment and justice, from now even unto eternity. The zeal of the Lord of hosts shall accomplish this.

8 The Lord sent a word to Jacob, and it fell upon Israel.

9 And all the people of Ephraim will know it. And the inhabitants of Samaria will say it, in the arrogance and haughtiness of their heart:

10 "The bricks have fallen, but we will build with squared stones. They have cut down the sycamores, but we will replace them with cedars."

11 And the Lord will raise up the enemies of Rezin over him, and he will turn his adversaries into a tumult:

12 the Syrians from the east and the Philistines from the west. And they will devour Israel with their whole mouth. After all this, his fury was not turned away; instead, his hand was still extended.

13 And the people did not return to the One who struck them, and they did not seek the Lord of hosts.

14 And so, the Lord will disperse, away from Israel, the head and the tail, he who bows down and he who refrains, in one day.

15 The long-lived and honorable, he is the head; and the prophet who teaches lies, he is the tail.

16 And those who deceitfully praise this people, and those who are praised, will be thrown down violently.

17 For this reason, the Lord will not rejoice over their youths. And he will not take pity on their orphans and widows. For each one is a hypocrite, and each one is wicked, and every mouth has spoken foolishness. After all this, his fury was not turned away; instead, his hand was still extended.

18 For impiety has been kindled like a fire: it will devour brier and thorn, and it will burn in the dense forest, and it will be interwoven with the ascending smoke.

19 The earth has been shaken by the wrath of the Lord of hosts, and the people will become like fuel for the fire. A man will not spare his own brother.

20 And he will turn toward the right, and he will be hungry. And he will eat toward the left, and he will not be satisfied. Each one will eat the flesh of his own arm: Manasseh Ephraim, and Ephraim Manasseh, and together they will be against Judah.

21 After all this, his fury was not turned away; instead, his hand was still extended.

Isaiah 10

1 Woe to those who make unfair laws, and who, when writing, write injustice:

2 in order to oppress the poor in judgment, and to do violence to the case of the humble of my people, in order that widows may be their prey, and that they might plunder the orphan.

3 What will you do on the day of visitation and calamity which is approaching from afar? To whom will you flee for assistance? And where will you leave behind your own glory,

4 so that you may not be bowed down under the chains, and fall with the slain? Concerning all this, his fury was not turned away; instead, his hand was still extended.

5 Woe to Assur! He is the rod and the staff of my fury, and my indignation is in their hands.

6 I will send him to a deceitful nation, and I will order him against the people of my fury, so that he may take away the plunder, and tear apart the prey, and place it to be trampled like the mud of the streets.

7 But he will not consider it to be so, and his heart will not suppose it to be this way. Instead, his heart will be set to crush and to exterminate more than a few nations.

8 For he will say:

9 "Are not my princes like many kings? Is not Calno like Carchemish, and Hamath like Arpad? Is not Samaria like Damascus?

10 In the same manner as my hand reached the kingdoms of the idol, so also will it reach their false images, those of Jerusalem and of Samaria.

11 Should I not do to Jerusalem and her false images, just as I have done to Samaria and her idols?"

12 And this shall be: when the Lord will have completed each of his works on Mount Zion and in Jerusalem, I will act against the fruit of the exalted heart of king Assur, and against the glory of the haughtiness of his eyes.

13 For he has said: "I have acted with the strength of my own hand, and I have understood with my own wisdom, and I have removed the limits of the people, and I have plundered their leaders, and, like one with power, I have pulled down those residing on high.

14 And my hand has reached to the strength of the people, as to a nest. And, just as the eggs which have been left behind are gathered, so have I gathered the entire earth. And there was no one who moved a wing, or opened a mouth, or uttered a snarl."

15 Should the axe glorify itself over him who wields it? Or can the saw exalt itself over him who pulls it? How can a rod lift itself up against him who wields it, or a staff exalt itself, though it is only wood?

16 Because of this, the sovereign Lord, the Lord of hosts, will send leanness among his fat ones. And under the influence of his glory, a burning ardor will rage, like a consuming fire.

17 And the light of Israel will be like a fire, and the Holy One of Israel will be like a flame. And his thorns and briers will be set ablaze and devoured, in one day.

18 And the glory of his forest and of his beautiful hill will be consumed, from the soul even to the flesh. And he will flee away in terror.

19 And what remain of the trees of his forest will be so few, and so easily numbered, that even a child could write them down.

20 And this shall be in that day: those not added to the remnant of Israel, and those who escape of the house of Jacob, will not lean upon him who strikes them. Instead, they will lean upon the Lord, the Holy One of Israel, in truth.

21 The remnant of Jacob, again I say the remnant, will be converted to the mighty God.

22 For though your people, O Israel, will be like the sand of the sea, yet only a remnant of them will be converted. The consummation, having been shortened, will be inundated with justice.

23 For the Lord, the God of hosts, will accomplish an abbreviation and a consummation, in the midst of all the earth.

24 For this reason, the Lord, the God of hosts, says this: "My people, who inhabit Zion: do not be afraid of Assur. He will strike you with his rod, and he will lift up his staff over you, on the way of Egypt.

25 But after a little while and a brief time, my indignation will be consumed, and my fury will turn to their wickedness."

26 And the Lord of hosts will raise up a scourge over him, like the scourge of Midian at the rock of Oreb, and he will raise up his rod over the sea, and he will lift it up against the way of Egypt.

27 And this shall be in that day: his burden will be taken away from your shoulder, and his yoke will be taken away from your neck, and the yoke will decay at the appearance of the oil.

28 He will approach Aiath; he will cross into Migron; he will entrust his vessels to Michmash.

29 They have passed through in haste; Geba is our seat; Ramah was stupefied; Gibeah of Saul fled.

30 Neigh with your voice, daughter of Gallim; pay attention, Laishah, impoverished woman of Anathoth.

31 Madmenah has moved away; be strengthened, you inhabitants of Gebim.

32 It is still daylight, so stand at Nob. He will shake his hand against the mountain of the daughter of Zion, the hill of Jerusalem.

33 Behold, the sovereign Lord of hosts will crush the little bottle of wine with terror, and the exalted in stature will be cut down, and the lofty will be brought low.

34 And the dense forest will be overturned with iron. And Lebanon, with its exalted ones, will fall.

Isaiah 11

1 And a rod will go forth from the root of Jesse, and a flower will ascend from his root.

2 And the Spirit of the Lord will rest upon him: the spirit of wisdom and understanding, the spirit of counsel and fortitude, the spirit of knowledge and piety.

3 And he will be filled with the spirit of the fear of the Lord. He will not judge according to the sight of the eyes, nor reprove according to the hearing of the ears.

4 Instead, he will judge the poor with justice, and he will reprove the meek of the earth with fairness. And he will strike the earth with the rod of his mouth, and he will slay the impious with the spirit of his lips.

5 And justice will be the belt around his waist. And faith will be the warrior's belt at his side.

6 The wolf will dwell with the lamb; and the leopard will lie down with the kid; the calf and the lion and the sheep will abide together; and a little boy will drive them.

7 The calf and the bear will feed together; their young ones will rest together. And the lion will eat straw like the ox.

8 And a breastfeeding infant will play above the lair of the asp. And a child who has been weaned will thrust his hand into the den of the king snake.

9 They will not harm, and they will not kill, on all my holy mountain. For the earth has been filled with the knowledge of the Lord, like the waters covering the sea.

10 In that day, the root of Jesse, who stands as a sign among the people, the same the Gentiles shall beseech, and his sepulcher will be glorious.

11 And this shall be in that day: the Lord will send forth his hand a second time to take possession of the remnant of his people who will be left behind: from Assyria, and from Egypt, and from Pathros, and from Ethiopia, and from Elam, and from Shinar, and from Hamath, and from the islands of the sea.

12 And he will lift up a sign to the nations, and he will gather together the fugitives of Israel, and he will collect the dispersed of Judah from the four regions of the earth.

13 And the envy of Ephraim will be taken away, and the enemies of Judah will perish. Ephraim will not be a rival to Judah, and Judah will not fight against Ephraim.

14 And they will fly upon the shoulders of the Philistines through the sea; together they will plunder the sons of the east. Idumea and Moab will be under the rule of their hand, and the sons of Ammon will be obedient.

15 And the Lord will desolate the tongue of the sea of Egypt. And he will lift up his hand over the river, with the strength of his Spirit; and he will strike it, in its seven streams, so that they may cross through it in their shoes.

16 And there will be a way for the remnant of my people, who will be left behind by the Assyrians: just as there was for Israel in the day that he ascended from the land of Egypt.

Isaiah 13

1 The burden of Babylon which Isaiah, the son of Amoz, saw.

2 Over the foggy mountain lift up a sign! Raise the voice, lift up the hand, and let the rulers enter through the gates!

3 In my wrath, I commanded my sanctified ones, and I called my strong ones, those who exult in my glory.

4 On the mountains, there is the voice of a multitude, as if of a numerous people, a voice with the sound of kings, of nations gathered together. For the Lord of hosts has given orders to soldiers of war,

5 to those who are arriving from a far off land, from the heights of the heavens. It is the Lord and the instruments of his fury, so that he may bring ruin to all the earth.

6 Wail aloud! For the day of the Lord draws near! It will arrive like a devastation from the Lord.

7 Because of it, every hand will fail, and every heart of man will waste away and be crushed.

8 Writhing and pain will seize them. They will be in pain, like a woman in labor. Each one will appear stupefied to his neighbor. Their countenances will be like faces which have been burned up.

9 Behold, the day of the Lord approaches: a cruel day, full of indignation and wrath and fury, which will place the earth in solitude and crush the sinners from it.

10 For the stars of the heavens, in their splendor, will not display their light. The sun will be obscured at its rising, and the moon will not shine in her brightness.

11 And I will act against the evils of the world, and against the impious for their iniquity. And I will cause the pride of the unfaithful to cease, and I will bring down the arrogance of the strong.

12 A man will be more precious than gold, and mankind will become like pure refined gold.

13 For this purpose, I will stir up heaven, and the earth will be moved from its place, because of the indignation of the Lord of hosts, because of the day of his furious wrath.

14 And they will be like a doe fleeing away, or like sheep; and there will be no one who may gather them together. Each one will turn to his own people, and every one will flee to his own land.

15 All who are found will be killed, and all who are caught unaware will fall by the sword.

16 Their infants will be thrown down violently before their eyes. Their houses will be plundered, and their wives will be violated.

17 Behold, I will stir up the Medes against them. They will not seek silver, nor desire gold.

18 Instead, with their arrows, they will put the little children to death, and they will take no pity on breastfeeding women, and their eye will not spare their children.

19 And then Babylon, the glorious one among kingdoms, that famous pride of the Chaldeans, will be destroyed, even as the Lord destroyed Sodom and Gomorrah.

20 It will not be inhabited, even unto the end, and it will not be reestablished, even from generation to generation. The Arab will not pitch his tents there, nor will the shepherds take rest there.

21 Instead, the wild beasts will rest there, and their houses will be filled with serpents, and ostriches will live there, and the hairy ones will leap about there.

22 And the tawny owls will answer one another there, in its buildings, and the Sirens in its shrines of pleasure.

Isaiah 14

1 Her time is drawing near, and her days will not be prolonged. For the Lord will take pity on Jacob, and he will still choose from Israel, and he will cause them to rest upon their own soil. And the new arrival will be joined to them, and he will adhere to the house of Jacob.

2 And the people will take them, and lead them to their place. And the house of Israel will possess them, in the land of the Lord, as men and women servants. And they will take captive those who had taken them captive. And they will subjugate their oppressors.

3 And this shall be in that day: when God will have given you rest from your labor, and from your oppression, and from the difficult servitude under which you served before,

4 you will accept this parable against the king of Babylon, and you will say: "How is it that the oppressor has ceased, along with his tribute?

5 The Lord has crushed the staff of the impious, the scepter of despots,

6 which struck the people in wrath with an incurable wound, which subjugated the nations in fury, which persecuted with cruelty.

7 All the earth has become quiet and still; it has been gladdened and has rejoiced.

8 The evergreens, too, have rejoiced over you, and the cedars of Lebanon, saying: 'Since you have slept, no one has ascended who would cut us down.'

9 Hell below was stirred up to meet you at your advent; it has awakened the giants for you. All the leaders of the earth have risen from their thrones, all the leaders among the nations."

10 Everyone will respond and will say to you: "Now you are wounded, just as we were; you have become like us.

11 Your arrogance has been dragged down to Hell. Your body has fallen dead. The moths will be strewn beneath you, and the worms will be your covering.

12 How is it that you have fallen from heaven, O Lucifer, who used to rise like the sun? How is it that you have fallen to the earth, you who wounded the peoples?

13 And you said in your heart: 'I will climb up to heaven. I will exalt my throne above the stars of God. I will be enthroned upon the mountain of the covenant, on the northern parts.

14 I will ascend above the tops of the clouds. I will be like the Most High.'

15 Yet truly, you shall be dragged down to Hell, into the depths of the pit.

16 Those who see you, will lean toward you, and will gaze upon you, saying: 'Could this be the man who disturbed the earth, who shook kingdoms,

17 who made the world into a desert and destroyed its cities, who would not even open a prison for his prisoners?' "

18 All the kings of the nations throughout the whole world have slept in glory, each man in his own house.

19 But you have been rejected from your grave, like a useless polluted plant, and you have been bound up with those who were slain by the sword, and who descended to the bottom of the pit, like a rotting carcass.

20 You will not be associated with them, even in the grave. For you have destroyed your own land; you have slain your own people. The offspring of the wicked ones will not be called upon for eternity.

21 Prepare his sons for the slaughter, according to the iniquity of their fathers. They will not rise up, nor inherit the earth, nor fill the face of the world with cities.

22 But I will rise up against them, says the Lord of hosts. And I will perish the name of Babylon and its remnants: both the plant and its progeny, says the Lord.

23 And I will appoint it as a possession for the hedgehog, with swamps of water. And I will sweep it out and wear it away with a brush, says the Lord of hosts.

24 The Lord of hosts has sworn, saying: Surely, just as I have considered it, so shall it be, and in the same manner as I have drawn it through my mind,

25 so shall it occur. So shall I crush the Assyrian in my land, and I will trample him upon my mountains, and his yoke will be taken away from them, and his burden will be removed from their shoulder.

26 This is the plan that I have decided, concerning the entire earth, and this is the hand which is extended over all the nations.

27 For the Lord of hosts has decreed it, and who is able to weaken it? And his hand is extended, so who can avert it?

28 In the year in which king Ahaz died, this burden was given:

29 You should not rejoice, all you of Philistia, that the rod of him who struck you has been crushed. For from the root of the serpent will go forth a king snake, and his offspring will engulf that which flies.

30 And the firstborn of the poor will be pastured, and the poor will rest in faithfulness. And I will cause your root to pass away by famine, and I will put to death your remnant.

31 Wail, O gate! Cry out, O city! All of Philistia has been prostrated. For a smoke will arrive from the north, and there is no one who will escape his army.

32 And what will be the response to this news among the nations? It will be that the Lord has established Zion, and that the poor of his people will hope in him.

Isaiah 15

1 The burden of Moab. Because Ar of Moab has been destroyed by night, it is utterly silent. Because the wall of Moab has been destroyed by night, it is utterly silent.

2 The house has ascended with Dibon to the heights, in mourning over Nebo and over Medeba. Moab has wailed. There will be baldness on all of their heads, and every beard will be shaven.

3 At their crossroads, they have been wrapped with sackcloth. On their rooftops and in their streets, everyone descends, wailing and weeping.

4 Heshbon will cry out with Elealeh. Their voice has been heard as far as Jahaz. Over this, the well-equipped men of Moab wail; each soul will wail to itself.

5 My heart will cry out to Moab; its bars will cry out even to Zoar, like a three-year-old calf. For they will ascend weeping, by way of the ascent of Luhith. And along the way of Horonaim, they will lift up a cry of contrition.

6 For the waters of Nimrim will be desolate, because the plants have withered, and the seedling has failed, and all the greenery has passed away.

7 This is in accord with the magnitude of their works and of their visitation. They will lead them to the torrent of the willows.

8 For an outcry has circulated along the border of Moab; its wailing even to Eglaim, and its clamor even to the well of Elim.

9 Because the waters of Dibon have been filled with blood, I will place even more upon Dibon: those from Moab who flee the lion, and the survivors of the earth.

Isaiah 16

1 O Lord, send forth the Lamb, the Ruler of the earth, from the Rock of the desert to the mountain of the daughter of Zion.

2 And this shall be: like a bird fleeing away, and like fledglings flying from the nest, so will the daughters of Moab be at the passage of Arnon.

3 Form a plan. Call a council. Let your shadow be as if it were night, even at midday. Conceal the fugitives, and do not betray the wanderers.

4 My fugitives will live with you. Become a hiding place, O Moab, from the face of the destroyer. For the dust is at its end; the miserable one has been consumed. He who trampled the earth has failed.

5 And a throne will be prepared in mercy, and One shall sit upon it in truth, in the tabernacle of David, judging and seeking judgment, and quickly repaying what is just.

6 We have heard of the pride of Moab; he is very proud. His pride and his arrogance and his indignation is more than his strength.

7 For this reason, Moab will wail to Moab; each one will wail. Speak of their wounds to those who rejoice upon the brick walls.

8 For the suburbs of Heshbon are deserted, and the lords of the Gentiles have cut down the vineyard of Sibmah. Its vines have arrived even at Jazer. They have wandered in the desert. Its seedlings have been abandoned. They have crossed over the sea.

9 I will weep with the tears of Jazer over this, the vineyard of Sibmah. I will inebriate you with my tears, Heshbon and Elealeh! For the sound of those who trample has rushed over your vintage and over your harvest.

10 And so, rejoicing and exultation will be taken away from Carmel, and there will be no jubilation or exultation in the vineyards. He who was accustomed to tread will not tread out the wine in the winepress. I have taken away the sound of those who tread.

11 Over this, my heart will resonate like a harp for Moab, and my inner most being for the brick wall.

12 And this shall be: when it is seen that Moab has struggled upon his high places, he will enter his holy places to pray, but he will not prevail.

13 This is the word that the Lord has spoken to Moab concerning that time.

14 And now the Lord has spoken, saying: In three years, like the years of a hired hand, the glory of Moab concerning the entire multitude of the people will be taken away, and what is left behind will be small and weak and not so numerous.

Isaiah 17

1 The burden of Damascus. Behold, Damascus will cease to be a city, and it will be like a heap of stones in ruin.

2 The cities in ruin will be left for the flocks, and they will take rest there, and there will be no one who may terrify them.

3 And assistance will cease from Ephraim, and the kingdom will cease from Damascus. And the remnant of Syria will be like the glory of the sons of Israel, says the Lord of hosts.

4 And this shall be in that day: the glory of Jacob will be thinned, and the fatness of his flesh will be reduced.

5 And it shall be like the gathering of the harvest which remains, and his arm will pick the ears of grain. And it shall be like a search for grain in the valley of Rephaim.

6 And what is left behind in it will be like one cluster of grapes, or like a shaken olive tree with two or three olives at the top of a branch, or like four or five olives at the top of a tree, says the Lord God of Israel.

7 In that day, a man will bow before his Maker, and his eyes will consider the Holy One of Israel.

8 And he will not bow before the altars that his hands have made. And he will not consider the things that his fingers have made, the sacred groves and the shrines.

9 In that day, his strong cities will be abandoned, like the plows and the grain fields which were left behind before the face of the sons of Israel, and you shall be deserted.

10 For you have forgotten God your Savior, and you have not remembered your strong Helper. Because of this, you will plant trustworthy plants, but you will sow a foreign seed.

11 In the day of your planting, the wild grapevine and your morning seed will flourish. The harvest has been taken away to the day of inheritance, and you will grieve heavily.

12 Woe to the multitude of many peoples, like the multitude of the roaring sea! Woe to the tumult of crowds, like the noise of many waters!

13 The peoples will make a noise, like the noise of waters overflowing, but he will rebuke him, and so he will flee far away. And he will be quickly taken away, like the dust of the mountains before the face of the wind, and like a whirlwind before a tempest.

14 In the time of the evening, behold: there will be a disturbance. When it is early morning, he will not remain. This is the portion of those who have devastated us, and this is the lot of those who have plundered us.

Isaiah 18

1 Woe to the land, that winged cymbal, which is beyond the rivers of Ethiopia,

2 which sends ambassadors by sea and in vessels of papyrus above the waters. Go forth, O swift Angels, to a nation which has been convulsed and torn apart, to a terrible people, after whom there is no other, to a nation apprehensive and downtrodden, whose land the rivers have spoiled.

3 All inhabitants of the world, you who dwell upon the earth: when the sign will have been elevated on the mountains, you will see, and you will hear the blast of the trumpet.

4 For the Lord says this to me: I will be quiet, and I will consider in my place, as the light at midday is clear, and as a cloud of dew in the day of the harvest.

5 For before the harvest, all was flourishing. And it will spring forth with an untimely completion, and its little branches will be pruned with a curved blade. And what is left over will be cut away and shaken off.

6 And together they will be abandoned to the birds of the mountains and to the wild beasts of the earth. And the birds will be continuously on them in the summer, and all the wild beasts of the earth will winter over them.

7 In that time, a gift will be carried to the Lord of hosts, from a people divided and torn apart, from a terrible people, after whom there has been no other, from an apprehensive nation, apprehensive and downtrodden, whose land the rivers have ruined, and it will be carried to the place of the name of the Lord of hosts, to mount Zion.

Isaiah 19

1 The burden of Egypt. Behold, the Lord will ascend upon a lofty cloud, and he will enter into Egypt, and the false images of Egypt will be moved before his face, and the heart of Egypt will waste away in its midst.

2 And I will cause Egyptian to rush against Egyptian. And they will fight: a man against his brother, and a man against his friend, city against city, kingdom against kingdom.

3 And the spirit of Egypt will be ruptured to its very core. And I will cast down their plan violently. And they will seek answers from their false images, and their diviners, and those led by demons, and their seers.

4 And I will deliver Egypt into the hand of cruel masters, and a strong king will dominate them, says the Lord, the God of hosts.

5 And the waters of the sea will dry up, and the river will be desolate and dry.

6 And the rivers will fail. The streams of its banks will diminish and dry up. The reed and the bulrush will wither away.

7 The channel of the river will be stripped down to its source, and everything irrigated by it will dry up and wither and be no more.

8 And the fishermen will grieve. And all who cast a hook into the river will mourn. And those who cast a net upon the surface of its waters will languish.

9 Those who work with linen, combing and weaving fine textiles, will be confounded.

10 And its irrigated places will begin to fail, with all those who make pools to take fish.

11 The leaders of Tanis are foolish. The wise counselors of Pharaoh have given foolish counsel. How can you say to Pharaoh: "I am the son of wisemen, the son of the kings of antiquity?"

12 Where are your wisemen now? Let them announce it to you, and let them reveal what the Lord of hosts intends for Egypt.

13 The leaders of Tanis have become foolish. The leaders of Memphis have decayed. They have deceived Egypt, the corner of its people.

14 The Lord has mixed a spirit of giddiness into its midst. And they have caused Egypt to err in all its works, like a drunken man who staggers and vomits.

15 And there will be no work for Egypt that would produce a head or a tail, one who bows down or one who refrains from bowing down.

16 In that day, Egypt will be like women, and they will be stupefied and fearful before the presence of the shaking hand of the Lord of hosts, the hand which he will move over them.

17 And the land of Judah will be a dread to Egypt. Everyone who thinks about it will be terrified before the presence of the plan of the Lord of hosts, the plan which he has decided concerning them.

18 In that day, there will be five cities in the land of Egypt which speak the language of Canaan, and which swear by the Lord of hosts. One will be called the City of the Sun.

19 In that day, there will be an altar of the Lord in the midst of the land of Egypt and a monument of the Lord beside its borders.

20 This shall be a sign and a testimony to the Lord of hosts in the land of Egypt. For they will cry out to the Lord before the face of the tribulation, and he will send them a savior and a defender who will free them.

21 And the Lord will be acknowledged by Egypt, and the Egyptians will recognize the Lord in that day, and they will worship him with sacrifices and gifts. And they will make vows to the Lord, and they will fulfill them.

22 And the Lord will strike Egypt with a scourge, and he will heal them. And they will return to the Lord. And he will be placated toward them, and he will heal them.

23 In that day, there will be a way from Egypt to the Assyrians, and the Assyrian will enter into Egypt, and the Egyptian will be with the Assyrians, and the Egyptians will serve Assur.

24 In that day, will Israel be the third to the Egyptian and the Assyrian, a blessing in the midst of the earth,

25 which the Lord of hosts has blessed, saying: Blessed be my people of Egypt, and the work of my hands for the Assyrian, but Israel is my inheritance.

Isaiah 21

1 The burden of the desert of the sea. Just as the whirlwinds approach from Africa, it approaches from the desert, from a terrible land.

2 A difficult vision has been announced to me: he who is unbelieving, he acts unfaithfully, and he who is a plunderer, he devastates. Ascend, O Elam! Lay siege, O Media! I have caused all its mourning to cease.

3 Because of this, my lower back has been filled with pain, and anguish has possessed me, like the anguish of a woman in labor. I fell down when I heard it. I was disturbed when I saw it.

4 My heart withered. The darkness stupefied me. Babylon, my beloved, has become a wonder to me.

5 Prepare the table. Contemplate, from a place of observation, those who eat and drink. Rise up, you leaders! Take up the shield!

6 For the Lord has said this to me: "Go and station a watchman. And let him announce whatever he will see."

7 And he saw a chariot with two horsemen, and a rider on an donkey, and a rider on a camel. And he considered them diligently, with an intense gaze.

8 And a lion cried out: "I am on the watchtower of the Lord, standing continually by day. And I am at my station, standing throughout the night.

9 Behold, a certain man approaches, a man riding on a two-horse chariot." And he responded, and he said: "Fallen, fallen is Babylon! And all its graven gods have been crushed into the earth!

10 O my threshed grain! O sons of my threshing floor! What I have heard from the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel, I have announced to you."

11 The burden of Dumah, cried out to me from Seir: "Watchman, how goes the night? Watchman, how goes the night?"

12 The watchman said: "Morning approaches with the night. If you are seeking: seek, and convert, and approach."

13 The burden in Arabia. In the forest you shall sleep, in the evening on the paths of Dedanim.

14 You who inhabit the land of the south: upon meeting the thirsty, bring water; meet the fugitive with bread.

15 For they are fleeing before the face of swords, before the face of a sword hanging over them, before the face of a bent bow, before the face of a grievous battle.

16 For the Lord said this to me: "After one more year, just like one year for a hired hand, all the glory of Kedar will be taken away.

17 And the remainder of the multitude of strong archers from the sons of Kedar will be few, for the Lord, the God of Israel, has spoken it."

Isaiah 22

1 The burden of the valley of vision. What does it mean to you, then, that each of you have even climbed to the rooftops?

2 Filled with clamor, a busy city, an exultant city: your dead have not been slain by the sword, nor did they die in battle.

3 All your leaders have fled together, and they have been bound by hardship. All who were found were chained together. They have fled far away.

4 For this reason, I said: "Depart from me. I will weep bitterly. Make no attempt to console me, over the devastation of the daughter of my people."

5 For it is a day of death, and of trampling, and of weeping to the Lord, the God of hosts, in the valley of vision: examining the wall and the magnificence above the mountain.

6 And Elam took up the quiver and the chariot of the horseman; and he stripped the wall of the shield.

7 And your elect valleys will be filled with chariots, and the horsemen will position themselves at the gates.

8 And the covering of Judah will be exposed, and in that day, you will see the weaponry of the forest house.

9 And you will see breaches in the city of David, for these have been multiplied. But you have gathered together the waters of the lower fish-pool.

10 And you have numbered the houses of Jerusalem. And you have destroyed the houses in order to fortify the wall.

11 And you have made a pit between two walls for the waters of the ancient fish-pool. But you have not gazed upward to him who made it, and you have not considered, even from a distance, its Maker.

12 And in that day, the Lord, the God of hosts, will call to weeping and mourning, to baldness and the wearing of sackcloth.

13 But behold: gladness and rejoicing, the killing of calves and the slaughter of rams, the eating of meat and the drinking of wine: "Let us eat and drink, for tomorrow we will die."

14 And the voice of the Lord of hosts was revealed in my ears: "Surely this iniquity will not be forgiven you, until you die," says the Lord, the God of hosts.

15 Thus says the Lord, the God of hosts: Go forth and enter to him who lives in the tabernacle, to Shebna, who is in charge of the temple, and you shall say to him:

16 "What are you here, or who are you claiming to be here? For you have hewn a sepulcher for yourself here. You have diligently hewn a memorial in a rock, as a tabernacle to yourself.

17 Behold, the Lord will cause you to be carried away, like a domesticated rooster, and he will remove you, like an outer garment.

18 He will crown you with a crown of tribulation. He will toss you like a ball into a broad and spacious land. There you will die, and there the chariot of your glory will be, for it is a shame to the house of your Lord."

19 And I will expel you from your station, and I will depose you from your ministry.

20 And this shall be in that day: I will call my servant Eliakim, the son of Hilkiah.

21 And I will clothe him with your vestment, and I will strengthen him with your belt, and I will give your authority to his hand. And he shall be like a father to the inhabitants of Jerusalem and to the house of Judah.

22 And I will place the key of the house of David upon his shoulder. And when he opens, no one will close. And when he closes, no one will open.

23 And I will fasten him like a peg in a trustworthy place. And he will be upon a throne of glory in the house of his father.

24 And they will suspend over him all the glory of his father's house: various kinds of vessels and every little article, from the vessels of bowls even to every instrument of music.

25 In that day, says the Lord of hosts, the peg which was fastened in a trustworthy place shall be taken away. And he will be broken, and he will fall, and he will perish, along with all that had depended upon him, because the Lord has spoken it.

Isaiah 23

1 The burden of Tyre. Wail, you ships of the sea! For the house, from which they were accustomed to go forth, has been laid waste. From the land of Kittim, this has been revealed to them.

2 Be silent, you inhabitants of the island! The merchants of Sidon, crossing over the sea, have filled you.

3 The offspring of the Nile is in the midst of many waters. The harvest of the river is her crop. And she has become the marketplace of the nations.

4 Be ashamed, O Sidon! For the sea speaks, the strength of the sea, saying: "I have not been in labor, and I have not given birth, and I have not raised young men, nor have I promoted the development of virgins."

5 When it has been heard in Egypt, they will be in anguish, when they hear of Tyre.

6 Cross over the seas. Wail, you inhabitants of the island!

7 Is this not your place, which from its earliest days has gloried in its antiquity? Her feet will lead her to a sojourn far away.

8 Who has made this plan against Tyre, which formerly was crowned, whose merchants were leaders, whose traders were illustrious on the earth?

9 The Lord of hosts has planned this, so that he may tear down the arrogance of all glory, and may bring disgrace to all the illustrious of the earth.

10 Cross through your land, as through a river, O daughter of the sea. You no longer have a belt.

11 He has extended his hand over the sea. He has stirred up kingdoms. The Lord has given an order against Canaan, so that he may crush its strong.

12 And he said: "You shall no longer increase so as to glory, while enduring calumny, O virgin daughter of Sidon. Rise up and set sail for Kittim; in that place, too, there will be no rest for you."

13 Behold, the land of the Chaldeans: never before was there such a people! Assur founded it. They have led away its strong ones into captivity. They have dug under its houses. They have left it in ruins.

14 Wail, you ships of the sea! For your strength has been devastated.

15 And this shall be in that day: you, O Tyre, will be forgotten for seventy years, like the days of one king. Then, after seventy years, there will be, for Tyre, something like the canticle of a harlot.

16 Take up a stringed instrument. Circulate through the city, you harlot who had been forgotten. Sing many canticles well, so that you may be remembered.

17 And this shall be after seventy years: the Lord will visit Tyre, and he will lead her back to her profits. And she will fornicate again with all the kingdoms of the world upon the face of the earth.

18 And her businesses and her profits will be sanctified to the Lord. They will not be locked away and they will not be stored. For her business will be for those who will live in the presence of the Lord, so that they may eat until satisfied, and may be well-clothed even into old age.

Isaiah 24

1 Behold, the Lord will lay waste to the earth, and he will strip it, and he will afflict its surface, and he will scatter its inhabitants.

2 And this shall be: as with the people, so with the priest; and as with the servant, so with his master; as with the handmaid, so with her mistress; as with the buyer, so with the seller; as with the lender, so with the borrower; as with the creditor, so with the debtor.

3 The earth will be utterly devastated and utterly plundered. For the Lord has spoken this word.

4 The earth mourned, and slipped away, and languished. The world slipped away; the loftiness of the people of the earth was weakened.

5 And the earth was corrupted by its inhabitants. For they have transgressed the laws, they have changed the ordinance, they have dissipated the everlasting covenant.

6 Because of this, a curse will devour the earth, and its inhabitants will sin. And for this reason, its caretakers will become crazed, and few men will be left behind.

7 The vintage has mourned. The vine has languished. All those who were rejoicing in their hearts have groaned.

8 The gladness of the drums has ceased. The sound of rejoicing has quieted. The sweetness of stringed instruments has been silenced.

9 They will not drink wine with a song. The drink will be bitter to those who drink it.

10 The city of vanity has been worn away. Every house has been closed up; no one enters.

11 There will be a clamor for wine in the streets. All rejoicing has been abandoned. The gladness of the earth has been carried away.

12 Solitude is what remains in the city, and calamity will overwhelm its gates.

13 For so shall it be in the midst of the earth, in the midst of the people: it is as if the few remaining olives are being shaken from the olive tree, and it is like a few clusters of grapes, when the grape harvest has already ended.

14 These few shall lift up their voice and give praise. When the Lord will have been glorified, they will make a joyful noise from the sea.

15 Because of this, glorify the Lord in doctrine: the name of the Lord, the God of Israel, in the islands of the sea.

16 From the ends of the earth, we have heard the praises of the glory of the Just One. And I said: "My secret is for myself! My secret is for myself! Woe to me! Those who would betray us have betrayed us, and they have betrayed us with the betrayal of transgression."

17 Dread, and the pit, and the snare are over you, O inhabitant of the earth!

18 And this shall be: whoever will flee from the voice of dread will fall into the pit. And whoever will extricate himself from the pit will be caught in the snare. For the floodgates from above have been opened, and the foundations of the earth will be shaken.

19 The earth will be utterly broken! The earth will be utterly crushed! The earth will be utterly shaken!

20 The earth will stagger greatly, like a drunken man, and will be carried away, like the tent of a single night. And its iniquity will be heavy upon it, and it will fall and not rise up again.

21 And this shall be: in that day, the Lord will visit upon the armies of the sky above, and upon the kings of the earth who are on the ground.

22 And they will be gathered together like the gathering of one bundle into a pit. And they will be enclosed in that place, as in a prison. And after many days, they will be visited.

23 And the moon will be ashamed, and the sun will be confounded, when the Lord of hosts will reign on mount Zion and in Jerusalem, and when he will have been glorified in the sight of his elders.

Isaiah 25

1 O Lord, you are my God! I will exalt you, and I will confess your name. For you have accomplished miracles. Your plan, from antiquity, is faithful. Amen.

2 For you have appointed a city as a tomb, a strong city for ruination, a house of foreigners: so that it may not be a city, and so that it may not be rebuilt forever.

3 Concerning this, a strong people will praise you; a city with a robust people will fear you.

4 For you have been the strength of the poor, the strength of the indigent in his tribulation, a refuge from the whirlwind, a shadow from the heat. For the spirit of the mighty is like a whirlwind striking against a wall.

5 You will bring low the uprising of foreigners, just as heat brings thirst. And like heat under a torrential cloud, you will cause the offshoot of the strong to wither away.

6 And the Lord of hosts will cause all the peoples on this mountain to feast on fatness, to feast on wine, a fatness full of marrow, a purified wine.

7 And he will cast down violently, on this mountain, the face of the chains, with which all peoples had been bound, and the net, with which all nations had been covered.

8 He will violently cast down death forever. And the Lord God will take away the tears from every face, and he will take away the disgrace of his people from the entire earth. For the Lord has spoken it.

9 And they will say in that day: "Behold, this is our God! We have waited for him, and he will save us. This is the Lord! We have endured for him. We will exult and rejoice in his salvation."

10 For the hand of the Lord will rest upon this mountain. And Moab will be trampled under him, just as stubble is worn away by a wagon.

11 And he will extend his hands under him, like a swimmer extending his hands to swim. And he will bring down his glory with a clap of his hands.

12 And the fortifications of your sublime walls will fall, and be brought low, and be torn down to the ground, even to the dust.

Isaiah 26

1 In that day, this canticle will be sung in the land of Judah. Within it will be set the city of our strength: Zion, a savior, a wall with a bulwark.

2 Open the gates, and let the just people who guard the truth enter.

3 The old error has gone away. You will serve peace: peace, for we have hoped in you.

4 You have trusted in the Lord for all eternity, in the Lord God almighty forever.

5 For he will bend down those living in the heights. He will bring low the lofty city. He will lower it, even to the ground. He will tear it down, even to the dust.

6 The foot will tread it down: the feet of the poor, the steps of the indigent.

7 The path of the just is upright; the difficult path of the just is right to walk in.

8 And in the path of your judgments, O Lord, we have endured for you. Your name and your remembrance are the desire of the soul.

9 My soul has desired you in the night. But I will also watch for you with my spirit, in my inmost heart, from the morning. When you accomplish your judgments upon the earth, the inhabitants of the world will learn justice.

10 Let us take pity on the impious one, but he will not learn justice. In the land of the holy ones, he has done iniquity, and so he will not see the glory of the Lord.

11 Lord, let your hand be exalted, and let them not see it. May the envious people see and be confounded. And may fire devour your enemies.

12 Lord, you will give us peace. For all our works have been wrought for us by you.

13 O Lord our God, other lords have possessed us apart from you, but in you alone let us remember your name.

14 Let not the dead live; let not the giants rise up again. For this reason, you have visited and destroyed them, and you have perished all remembrance of them.

15 You have been lenient to the people, O Lord, lenient to the people. But have you been glorified? You have removed all the limits of the earth.

16 Lord, they have sought you in anguish. Your doctrine was with them, amid the tribulation of murmuring.

17 Like a woman who has conceived and is approaching the time for delivery, who, in anguish, cries out in her pains, so have we become before your face, O Lord.

18 We have conceived, and it is as if we were in labor, but we have given birth to wind. We have not brought forth salvation on the earth. For this reason, the inhabitants of the earth have not fallen.

19 Your dead shall live. My slain will rise again. Be awakened, and give praise, you who live in the dust! For your dew is the dew of the light, and you shall be dragged down to the land of the giants, to ruination.

20 Go, my people! Enter your chambers. Close your doors behind you. Conceal yourselves for a very brief time, until the indignation has passed over you.

21 For behold, the Lord will go forth from his place, so that he may visit the iniquity of each inhabitant of the earth against him. And the earth will reveal its blood, and it will no longer cover its slain.

Isaiah 27

1 In that day, the Lord will visit, with his harsh and great and strong sword, against Leviathan, the barred serpent, and against Leviathan, the twisted serpent, and he will slay the whale that is in the sea.

2 In that day, the vineyard of pure wine will sing to them.

3 I am the Lord, who watches over it. I will suddenly give drink to it. I will watch over it, night and day, lest perhaps someone visit against it.

4 Indignation is not mine. Who will be a thorn and a brier to me in battle? I will advance against them. I set them on fire together.

5 Or will he, instead, take hold of my strength? Will he make peace with me? Will she make peace with me?

6 As they advance with violence against Jacob, Israel will flourish and spring forth, and they will fill the face of the world with offspring.

7 Has he struck him with the scourge that he himself used to strike others? Or has he killed in the manner that he himself used to kill his victims?

8 You will judge this by comparing one measure to another, when he has been cast out. He has decided this, by his stern spirit, for the day of heat.

9 Therefore, concerning this, the iniquity of the house of Jacob will be forgiven. And this is the reward of all: that their sin be taken away, when he will have made all the stones of the altar to be like crushed cinders. For the sacred groves and the shrines shall not stand.

10 For the fortified city will be desolate. The shining city will be abandoned and will be left behind like a desert. In that place, the calf will pasture, and in that place, he will lie down, and he will feed from its summits.

11 Its harvest will be crushed by dryness. Women will arrive and teach it, for it is not a wise people. Because of this, he who made it will not take pity on it, and he who formed it will not spare it.

12 And this shall be: in that day, the Lord will strike, from the channel of the river, even to the torrent of Egypt. And you shall be gathered together, one by one, O sons of Israel.

13 And this shall be: in that day, a noise will be made with a great trumpet. And those who had been lost will approach from the land of the Assyrians, with those who had been outcasts in the land of Egypt. And they will adore the Lord, on the holy mountain, in Jerusalem.

Isaiah 28

1 Woe to the crown of arrogance, to the inebriated of Ephraim, and to the falling flower, the glory of his exultation, to those who were at the top of the very fat valley, staggering from wine.

2 Behold, the Lord is powerful and steadfast, like a storm of hail, like a crushing whirlwind, like the force of many waters, inundating, sent forth over a spacious land.

3 The arrogant crown of the inebriated of Ephraim will be trampled under foot.

4 And the falling flower, the glory of his exultation, who is at the summit of the fat valley, will be like a premature fruit before the ripeness of autumn, which, when the onlooker beholds it, as soon he takes it in his hand, he will devour it.

5 In that day, the Lord of hosts will be the crown of glory and the wreath of exultation for the remnant of his people.

6 And he will be the spirit of judgment for those who sit in judgment, and the strength of those who return from war to the gates.

7 Yet truly, these also have been ignorant due to wine, and they have gone astray due to inebriation. The priest and the prophet have been ignorant because of inebriation. They have been absorbed by wine. They have staggered in drunkenness. They have not known the One who sees. They have been ignorant of judgment.

8 For all the tables have been filled with vomit and filth, so much so that there was no place left.

9 To whom will he teach knowledge? And to whom will he grant an understanding of what is heard? To those who have been weaned from the milk, who have been pulled away from the breasts.

10 So then: command, and command again; command, and command again; expect, and expect again; a little here, and a little there.

11 For with the speech of lips and with a different language, he will speak to this people.

12 He said to them: "This is my rest. Refresh the weary," and, "This is my refreshment." And yet they were unwilling to listen.

13 And so, the word of the Lord to them will be: "Command, and command again; command, and command again; expect, and expect again; a little here, and a little there," so that they may go forward and fall backward, and so that they may be broken and ensnared and captured.

14 Because of this, listen to the word of the Lord, you mocking men, who lord it over my people who are at Jerusalem.

15 For you have said: "We struck a deal with death, and we formed a pact with Hell. When the inundating scourge passes through, it will not overwhelm us. For we have placed our hope in lies, and we are protected by what is false."

16 For this reason, thus says the Lord God: Behold, I will set a stone within the foundations of Zion, a tested stone, a cornerstone, a precious stone, which has been established in the foundation: whoever trusts in him need not hurry.

17 And I will establish judgment in weights, and justice in measures. And a hailstorm will overturn hope in what is false; and waters will inundate its protection.

18 And your deal with death will be abolished, and your pact with Hell will not stand. When the inundating scourge passes through, you will be trampled down by it.

19 Whenever it passes through, it will take you away. For, at first light of morning, it will pass through, in the day and in the night, and vexation alone will make you understand what you hear.

20 For the bed has been narrowed, so much so that one alone would fall out, and the short blanket is not able to cover two.

21 For the Lord will stand, just as at the mountain of divisions. He will be angry, just as in the valley which is in Gibeon, so that he may accomplish his work, his strange work, so that he may complete his work, his work which is foreign even to him.

22 And now, do not be willing to mock, lest your chains be tightened. For I have heard, from the Lord, the God of hosts, about the consummation and the abridgement concerning the entire earth.

23 Pay close attention, and listen to my voice! Attend and hear my eloquence!

24 Would the plowman, after plowing all day so that he may sow, instead cut open and hoe his soil?

25 Will he not, when he has made the surface level, sow coriander, and scatter cumin, and plant wheat in rows, and barley, and millet, and vetch in their places?

26 For he will be instructed in judgment; his God will teach him.

27 For coriander cannot be threshed with a saw, and a cartwheel cannot revolve over cumin. Instead, coriander is shaken out with a stick, and cumin with a staff.

28 But grain for bread must be crushed. Truly, the thresher cannot thresh it unceasingly, and the cartwheel can neither disrupt it, nor break it with its surface.

29 And this has gone forth from the Lord, the God of hosts, so that he may accomplish his miraculous plan and magnify justice.

Isaiah 29

1 Woe to Ariel, to Ariel the city against which David fought: year has been added to year, the solemnities have unfolded.

2 And I will surround Ariel with siege works, and it will be in sorrow and mourning, and it will be like Ariel to me.

3 And I will surround you like a sphere all around you, and I will raise up a rampart against you, and I will set up fortifications to blockade you.

4 You will be brought low. You will speak from the ground, and your eloquence will be heard from the dirt. And, from the ground, your voice will be like that of the python, and your eloquence will mumble from the dirt.

5 And the multitude of those who fan you will be like fine dust. And the multitude of those who have prevailed against you will be like embers fading away.

6 And this will happen suddenly and swiftly. It will be visited from the Lord of hosts with thunder and earthquakes, and with the great noise of a whirlwind and a storm, and with a flame of devouring fire.

7 And the multitude of all the nations that have struggled against Ariel will be like the dream of a vision by night, along with all who have battled, and besieged, and prevailed against it.

8 And it will be like one who is hungry and dreams of eating, but, when he has been awakened, his soul is empty. And it will be like one who is thirsty and dreams of drinking, but, after he has been awakened, he still languishes in thirst, and his soul is empty. So shall the multitude of all the nations be, who have struggled against Mount Zion.

9 Be stupefied and in wonder! Shake and quiver! Be inebriated, but not from wine! Stagger, but not from drunkenness!

10 For the Lord has mixed for you a spirit of deep sleep. He will close your eyes. He will cover your prophets and leaders, who see visions.

11 And the vision of all will be to you like the words of a sealed book, which, when they have given it to someone who knows how to read, they will say, "Read this," but he will respond, "I cannot; for it has been sealed."

12 But if the book is given to someone who does not know how to read, and it is said to him, "Read," then he will respond, "I do not know how to read."

13 And the Lord said: Since this people have drawn near to me only with their mouth, and their lips glorify me while their heart is far from me, and their fear of me is based on the commandments and doctrines of men,

14 for this reason, behold, I will proceed to accomplish a wonder for this people, a great and mystifying miracle. For wisdom will perish from their wise, and the understanding of their prudent will be concealed.

15 Woe to you who use the depths of the heart, so that you may hide your intentions from the Lord. Their works are done in darkness, and so they say: "Who sees us?" and "Who knows us?"

16 This intention of yours is perverse. It is as if the clay were to plan against the potter, or as if the work were to say to its maker: "You did not make me." Or it is as if what has been formed were to say to the one who formed it, "You do not understand."

17 In not more than a little while and a brief time, Lebanon will be turned into a fruitful field, and a fruitful field will be considered to be a forest.

18 And in that day, the deaf will hear the words of a book, and out of darkness and obscurity the eyes of the blind will see.

19 And the meek will increase their rejoicing in the Lord, and the poor among men will exult in the Holy One of Israel.

20 For the one who was prevailing has failed, the one who was mocking has been consumed, and all those who were standing guard over iniquity have been cut down.

21 For they caused men to sin by a word, and they supplanted him who argued against them at the gates, and they turned away from justice in vain.

22 Because of this, thus says the Lord, he who has redeemed Abraham, to the house of Jacob: From now on, Jacob will not be confounded; from now on his countenance will not blush with shame.

23 Instead, when he sees his children, they will be the work of my hands in his midst, sanctifying my name, and they will sanctify the Holy One of Jacob, and they will preach the God of Israel.

24 And those who had gone astray in spirit will know understanding, and those who had murmured will learn the law.

Isaiah 30

1 "Woe to the sons of apostasy!" says the Lord. For you would take advice, but not from me. And you would begin to weave, but not by my spirit. Thus do you add sin upon sin!

2 You are walking so as to descend into Egypt, and you have not sought answers from my mouth, instead hoping for assistance from the strength of Pharaoh and placing trust in the shadow of Egypt.

3 And so, the strength of Pharaoh will be your confusion, and trust in the shadow of Egypt will be your disgrace.

4 For your leaders were at Tanis, and your messengers have traveled even as far as Hanes.

5 They have all been confounded because of a people who were not able to offer profit to them, who were not of assistance, nor of other usefulness, except to offer confusion and reproach.

6 The burden of the beasts in the south. In a land of tribulation and anguish, from which go forth the lioness and the lion, the viper and the flying king snake, they carry their riches upon the shoulders of beasts of burden, and their valuables upon the humps of camels, to a people who are not able to offer profit to them.

7 For Egypt will offer assistance, but without purpose or success. Therefore, concerning this, I cried out: "It is only arrogance! Remain calm."

8 Now, therefore, enter and write for them upon a tablet, and note it diligently in a book, and this shall be a testimony in the last days, and even unto eternity.

9 For they are a people who provoke to wrath, and they are lying sons, sons unwilling to listen to the law of God.

10 They say to the seers, "Do not see," and to those who behold: "Do not behold for us the things that are right. Speak to us of pleasing things. See errors for us.

11 Take me from the way. Avert me from the path. Let the Holy One of Israel cease from before our face."

12 Because of this, thus says the Holy One of Israel: Since you have rejected this word, and you have hoped in calumny and rebellion, and since you have depended upon these things,

13 for this reason, this iniquity will be to you like a breach that has fallen, and like a gap in a high wall. For its destruction will happen suddenly, when it is not expected.

14 And it will be crushed, just as the earthen vessel of a potter is destroyed by a sharp blow. And not even a fragment of its earthenware will be found, which might carry a little fire from the hearth, or which might draw a little water from a hollow.

15 For thus says the Lord God, the Holy One of Israel: If you return and are quiet, you shall be saved. Your strength will be found in silence and in hope. But you are not willing!

16 And you have said: "Never! Instead, we will flee by horseback." For this reason, you will be put to flight. And you have said, "We will climb upon swift ones." For this reason, those who pursue you will be even swifter.

17 A thousand men will flee in terror from the face of one, and you will flee in terror from the face of five, until you who have been left behind are like the mast of a ship at the top of a mountain, or like a sign on a hill.

18 Therefore, the Lord waits, so that he may take pity on you. And therefore, he will be exalted for sparing you. For the Lord is the God of judgment. Blessed are all those who wait for him.

19 For the people of Zion will live in Jerusalem. Bitterly, you will not weep. Mercifully, he will take pity on you. At the voice of your outcry, as soon as he hears, he will respond to you.

20 And the Lord will give you thick bread and accessible water. And he will not cause your teacher to fly away from you anymore. And your eyes will behold your instructor.

21 And your ears will listen to the word of one admonishing you behind your back: "This is the way! Walk in it! And do not turn aside, neither to the right, nor to the left."

22 And you will defile the plates of your silver graven images and the vestment of your gold molten idols. And you will throw these things away like the uncleanness of a menstruating woman. You will say to it, "Go away!"

23 And wherever you sow seed upon the earth, rain will be given to the seed. And bread from the grain of the earth will be very plentiful and full. In that day, the lamb will pasture in the spacious land of your possession.

24 And your bulls, and the colts of the donkeys that work the ground, will eat a mix of grains like that winnowed on the threshing floor.

25 And there will be, on every lofty mountain, and on every elevated hill, rivers of running water, in the day of the slaughter of many, when the tower will fall.

26 And the light of the moon will be like the light of the sun, and the light of the sun will be sevenfold, like the light of seven days, in the day when the Lord will bind the wound of his people, and when he will heal the stroke of their scourge.

27 Behold, the name of the Lord arrives from far away. His fury is burning and heavy to bear. His lips have been filled with indignation, and his tongue is like a devouring fire.

28 His Spirit is like a torrent, inundating, even as high as the middle of the neck, in order to reduce the nations to nothing, along with the bridle of error that was in the jaws of the people.

29 There will be a song for you, as in the night of a sanctified solemnity, and a joy of heart, as when one travels with music to arrive at the mountain of the Lord, to the Strong One of Israel.

30 And the Lord will cause the glory of his voice to be heard, and, with a threatening fury and a devouring flame of fire, he will reveal the terror of his arm. He will crush with the whirlwind and with hailstones.

31 For at the voice of the Lord, Assur will dread being struck with the staff.

32 And when the passage of the staff has been begun, the Lord will cause it to rest upon him, with timbrels and harps. And with special battles, he will fight against them.

33 For a burning place, deep and wide, has been prepared from yesterday, prepared by the King. Its nourishment is fire and much wood. The breath of the Lord, like a torrent of brimstone, kindles it.

Isaiah 31

1 Woe to those who descend into Egypt for assistance, hoping in horses, and putting their trust in four-horse chariots because they are many, and in horsemen because they are exceedingly strong. And they have not believed in the Holy One of Israel, and they have not sought the Lord.

2 Therefore, being wise, he has permitted harm, and he has not removed his words, and he will rise up against the house of the wicked and against those who assist the workers of iniquity.

3 Egypt is man, and not God. And their horses are flesh, and not spirit. And so, the Lord will reach down his hand, and the helper will fall, and the one who was being helped will fall, and they will all be consumed together.

4 For the Lord says this to me: In the same way that a lion roars, and a young lion is over his prey, and though a multitude of shepherds may meet him, he will not dread their voice, nor be afraid of their number, so will the Lord of hosts descend in order to battle upon mount Zion and upon its hill.

5 Like birds flying, so will the Lord of hosts protect Jerusalem, protecting and freeing, passing over and saving.

6 Be converted to the same depth that you have drawn away, O sons of Israel.

7 For in that day, a man will cast away his idols of silver and his idols of gold, which your hands have made for you unto sin.

8 And Assur will fall by a sword not of man, and a sword not of man will devour him. And he will not flee from the face of the sword, and his young men will be subject to a penalty.

9 And his strength will pass away in terror, and his princes will flee in fear. The Lord has said it. His fire is in Zion, and his furnace is at Jerusalem.

Isaiah 32

1 Behold, the king will reign in justice, and the princes will rule in judgment.

2 And a man will be like someone hidden from the wind, who conceals himself from a storm, or like rivers of waters in a time of thirst, or like the shadow of a rock that juts out in a desert land.

3 The eyes of those who see will not be obscured, and the ears of those who hear will listen closely.

4 And the heart of the foolish will understand knowledge, and the tongue of those with impaired speech will speak quickly and plainly.

5 He who is foolish will no longer be called leader, nor will the deceitful be called greater.

6 For a foolish man speaks foolishness and his heart works iniquity in order to accomplish deception. And he speaks to the Lord deceitfully, so as to empty the soul of the hungry and to take away drink from the thirsty.

7 The tools of the deceitful are very wicked. For they have concocted plans to destroy the meek by lying words, though the poor speak judgment.

8 Yet truly, the prince will plan things that are worthy of a prince, and he will stand above the rulers.

9 You opulent women, rise up and listen to my voice! O confident daughters, play close attention to my eloquence!

10 For after a year and some days, you who are confident will be disturbed. For the vintage has been completed; the gathering will no longer occur.

11 Be stupefied, you opulent women! Be disturbed, O confident ones! Strip yourselves, and be confounded; gird yourselves at the waist.

12 Mourn over your breasts, over the delightful country, over the fruitful vineyard.

13 Thorn and brier will rise up, over the soil of my people. How much more over all the houses of gladness, over the city of exultation?

14 For the house has been forsaken. The multitude of the city has been abandoned. A darkness and a covering have been placed over its dens, even unto eternity. It will be the gladness of wild donkeys and the pasture of flocks,

15 until the Spirit is poured over us from on high. And the desert will be a fruitful field, and the fruitful field will be considered as a forest.

16 And judgment will live in solitude, and justice will be seated in a fruitful place.

17 And the work of justice will be peace. And the service of justice will be quiet and secure, forever.

18 And my people will be seated in the beauty of peacefulness, and in the tabernacles of faithfulness, and in the opulence of restfulness.

19 But hail will be in the descent of the forest, and the city will be brought exceedingly low.

20 Blessed are you who sow over any waters, sending the feet of the ox and the donkey there.

Isaiah 33

1 Woe to you who plunder! Will you yourselves not also be plundered? And woe to you who despise! Will you yourselves not also be despised? When you will have completed your plundering, you will be plundered. When, out of fatigue, you will have ceased acting with contempt, you will be treated with contempt.

2 O Lord, take pity on us. For we have waited for you. Be our arm in the morning and our salvation in the time of tribulation.

3 From the voice of the Angel, the people fled. And from your exultation, the nations were scattered.

4 And your spoils will be gathered together, just as the locusts are collected when the ditches have become filled with them.

5 The Lord has been magnified, because he has lived on high. He has filled Zion with judgment and justice.

6 And there will be faith in your times: the riches of salvation, wisdom and knowledge. For the fear of the Lord is his treasure.

7 Behold, outside, those who see will cry out. The Angels of peace will weep bitterly.

8 The roads have become desolate. Travelers have ceased along the paths. The covenant has been nullified. He has tossed aside cities. He has disregarded men.

9 The earth has mourned and languished. Lebanon has been confounded and desecrated. And Sharon has become like a desert. And Bashan and Carmel have been struck together.

10 "Now, I will rise up!" says the Lord. "Now I will be exalted! Now I will lift myself up!"

11 You will conceive heat. You will give birth to stubble. Your own spirit will devour you like fire.

12 And the people will be like the ashes from a fire. They will be consumed by fire like a bundle of thorns.

13 "You who are far away, listen to what I have done! And you who are near, acknowledge my strength!"

14 The sinners in Zion are terrified; trembling has taken hold of the hypocrites. Who among you is able to live with a devouring fire? Who among you will live with an everlasting flame?

15 The one who walks in justice and speaks the truth, who casts out avarice with oppression and shakes all bribes from his hands, who blocks his ears so that he may not listen to blood, and closes his eyes so that he may not see evil.

16 Such a one will live on high; the fortification of rocks will be his lofty place. Bread has been given to him; his waters are reliable.

17 His eyes will see the king in his elegance; they will discern the land from far away.

18 Your heart will meditate on fear. Where are the learned? Where are those who ponder the words of the law? Where are the teachers of little ones?

19 You will not look upon a shameless people, a people of exalted words. For you are not able to understand the dissertation of a tongue in which there is no wisdom.

20 Look with favor upon Zion, the city of our solemnity. Your eyes will behold Jerusalem: an opulent habitation, a tabernacle that can never be taken away. Its stakes will not be taken away forever, nor will any of its cords be broken.

21 For only in that place has our Lord been magnified. It is a place of rivers, very broad and open. No ship with oars will cross through it, nor will the great Greek ship pass through it.

22 For the Lord is our judge. The Lord is our lawgiver. The Lord is our king. He himself will save us.

23 Your ropes have become loose, and they will not prevail. Your mast will be such that you will not be able to unfurl a flag. Then the spoils of much plunder will be divided. The lame will seize the spoils.

24 He who is nearby will not say: "I am too weak." The people who live in it will have their iniquity taken away from them.

Isaiah 34

1 O nations and peoples: draw near, and listen, and pay attention! Let the earth and its fullness hear, the entire world and all its offspring.

2 For the indignation of the Lord is over all the nations, and his fury is over all their armies. He has put them to death, and he has given them over to slaughter.

3 Their slain will be cast out, and from their carcasses a foul odor will rise up. The mountains will languish because of their blood.

4 And the entire army of the heavens will languish, and the heavens will be folded like a book. And their entire army will fall away, as a leaf falls from the vine or from the fig tree.

5 "For my sword in heaven has been inebriated. Behold, it will descend upon Idumea, and upon the people of my slaughter, unto judgment."

6 The sword of the Lord has been filled with blood. It has been thickened by the blood of lambs and he-goats, by the innermost blood of rams. For the victim of the Lord is in Bozrah, and a great slaughter is in the land of Edom.

7 And the single-horned beasts will descend with them, and the bulls along with the mighty. Their land will be inebriated by blood, and their ground by the fat of their lazy ones.

8 For this is the day of the vengeance of the Lord, the year of retribution for the judgment of Zion.

9 And its torrents will be turned into tar, and its soil into sulfur. And its land will become burning tar.

10 Night and day, it will not be extinguished; its smoke will rise up without ceasing. From generation to generation it will remain desolate. No one will pass through it, forever and ever.

11 The pelican and the hedgehog will possess it. And the ibis and the raven will live in it. And a measuring line will be extended over it, so that it may be reduced to nothing, and a plumb line, unto desolation.

12 Its nobles will not be in that place. Instead, they will call upon the king, and all its leaders will be as nothing.

13 And thorns and nettles will rise up in its houses, and the thistle in its fortified places. And it will be the lair of serpents and the pasture of ostriches.

14 And demons and monsters will meet, and the hairy ones will cry out to one another. There, the ogress has lain down and found rest for herself.

15 In that place, the hedgehog has kept its den, and has raised its young, and has dug around them, and has kept them warm in its shadow. In that place, the birds of prey have joined together, one to another.

16 Search and read diligently in the book of the Lord. Not one of them was lacking; not one has sought for the other. For what has proceeded from my mouth, he has commanded, and his very Spirit has gathered them.

17 And he has cast lots over them. And his hand has distributed this to them by measure. They will possess it, even unto eternity. From generation to generation, they will dwell in it.

Isaiah 35

1 The desolate and impassable land will rejoice, and the place of solitude will exult, and it will flourish like the lily.

2 It will spring up and blossom, and it will exult with rejoicing and praising. The glory of Lebanon has been given to it, with the beauty of Carmel and Sharon. These will see the glory of the Lord and the beauty of our God.

3 Strengthen the lax hands, and confirm the weak knees!

4 Say to the fainthearted: "Take courage and fear not! Behold, your God will bring the vindication of retribution. God himself will arrive to save you."

5 Then the eyes of the blind will be opened, and the ears of the deaf will be cleared.

6 Then the disabled will leap like a buck, and the tongue of the mute will be untied. For the waters have burst forth in the desert, and torrents in solitary places.

7 And the land that was dry will have a pond, and the thirsty land will have fountains of water. In the hollows where the serpents lived before, there will rise up the greenery of reed and bulrush.

8 And there shall be a path and a road in that place. And it will be called the Holy Way. The defiled will not pass through it. For this will be an upright path for you, so much so that the foolish will not wander along it.

9 There will be no lions in that place, and harmful wild animals will neither climb up to it, nor be found there. Only those who have been freed will walk in that place.

10 And the redeemed of the Lord will be converted, and they will return to Zion with praising. And everlasting joy will be upon their heads. They will obtain gladness and rejoicing. For pain and sorrow will flee away.

Isaiah 36

1 And it happened that, in the fourteenth year of king Hezekiah, Sennacherib, the king of the Assyrians, went up against all the fortified cities of Judah, and he seized them.

2 And the king of the Assyrians sent Rabshakeh from Lachish into Jerusalem, to king Hezekiah, with a great force, and he stood near the aqueduct of the upper pool, at the road to the fuller's field.

3 And those who went to him were Eliakim, son of Hilkiah, who was over the house, and Shebna, the scribe, and Joah, son of Asaph, the historian.

4 And Rabshakeh said to them: "Tell Hezekiah: Thus says the great king, the king of the Assyrians: What is this faith in which you believe?

5 And by what counsel or strength would you prepare to rebel? In whom do you have faith, so much so that you would withdraw from me?

6 Behold, you are trusting in Egypt, in that broken staff of a reed. But if a man were to lean against it, it would enter his hand and pierce it. So is Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, to all who trust in him.

7 But if you answer me by saying: 'We trust in the Lord our God.' Is it not his high places and altars that Hezekiah has taken away? And he has said to Judah and to Jerusalem, 'You shall worship before this altar.'

8 And now, hand yourselves over to my lord, the king of the Assyrians, and I will give you two thousand horses, and you will not be able to find riders for them on your own.

9 So how will you withstand the face of the ruler of even one place, of even the least of my lord's subordinates? But if you trust in Egypt, in four-horse chariots and in horsemen:

10 do I intend to go up against this land to destroy it without the Lord? But the Lord said to me, 'Go up against this land, and destroy it.' "

11 And Eliakim, and Shebna, and Joah said to Rabshakeh: "Speak to your servants in the Syrian language. For we understand it. Do not speak to us in the Jewish language, in the hearing of the people, who are upon the wall."

12 And Rabshakeh said to them: "Has my lord sent me to your lord and to you in order to speak all these words, and not even more so to the men who are sitting on the wall, so that they may eat their own dung and drink their own urine with you?"

13 Then Rabshakeh stood up, and he cried out with a loud voice in the Jewish language, and he said: "Listen to the words of the great king, the king of the Assyrians.

14 Thus says the king: Do not let Hezekiah deceive you. For he will not be able to rescue you.

15 And do not let Hezekiah cause you to trust in the Lord, saying: 'The Lord will rescue and free us. This city will not be given into the hands of the king of the Assyrians.'

16 Do not listen to Hezekiah. For the king of the Assyrians says this: Act with me to your own benefit, and come out to me. And let each one eat from his own vine, and each one from his own fig tree. And let each one drink water from his own well,

17 until I arrive and take you away to a land which is like your own: a land of grain and of wine, a land of bread and of vineyards.

18 But you should not let Hezekiah disturb you, saying, 'The Lord will deliver us.' Have any of the gods of each of the nations delivered their land from the hand of the king of the Assyrians?

19 Where is the god of Hamath and of Arpad? Where is the god of Sepharvaim? Have they freed Samaria from my hand?

20 Who is there, among all the gods of these lands, who has rescued his land from my hand, so that the Lord would rescue Jerusalem from my hand?"

21 And they remained silent and did not answer a word to him. For the king had commanded them, saying, "You shall not respond to him."

22 And Eliakim, son of Hilkiah, who was over the house, and Shebna, the scribe, and Joah, son of Asaph, the historian, entered to Hezekiah with their garments rent, and they reported to him the words of Rabshakeh.

Isaiah 37

1 And it happened that, when king Hezekiah had heard this, he rent his garments, and he wrapped himself in sackcloth, and he entered the house of the Lord.

2 And he sent Eliakim, who was over the house, and Shebna, the scribe, and the elders of the priests, covered with sackcloth, to Isaiah, the son of Amoz, the prophet.

3 And they said to him: "Thus says Hezekiah: This day is a day of tribulation, and of rebuke, and of blasphemy. For the sons have arrived at the time for birth, but there is not enough strength to bring them forth.

4 Perhaps, somehow, the Lord your God will hear the words of Rabshakeh, whom the king of the Assyrians, his lord, has sent to blaspheme the living God, and will rebuke the words that the Lord your God has heard. Therefore, lift up your prayers on behalf of the remnant which has been left behind."

5 And so the servants of king Hezekiah went to Isaiah.

6 And Isaiah said to them: "You shall say this to your lord: Thus says the Lord: Do not be afraid to face the words that you have heard, by which the servants of the king of the Assyrians blasphemed me.

7 Behold, I will send a spirit to him, and he will hear a message, and he will return to his own land. And I will cause him to fall by the sword, in his own land."

8 Then Rabshakeh returned, and he found the king of the Assyrians fighting against Libnah. For he had heard that he had set out from Lachish.

9 And he heard from Tirhakah, the king of Ethiopia: "He has gone forth so that he may fight against you." And when he had heard this, he sent messengers to Hezekiah, saying:

10 "You shall say this to Hezekiah, the king of Judah, saying: Do not let your God, in whom you trust, deceive you by saying: 'Jerusalem will not be given into the hands of the king of the Assyrians.'

11 Behold, you have heard about all that the kings of the Assyrians have done to all the lands that they have conquered, and so, how can you be delivered?

12 Have the gods of the nations rescued those whom my fathers have conquered: Gozan, and Haran, and Rezeph, and the sons of Eden who were at Telassar?

13 Where is the king of Hamath and the king of Arpad, or the king of the city of Sepharvaim, or of Hena and Ivvah?"

14 And Hezekiah took the letter from the hand of the messengers, and he read it, and he went up to the house of the Lord, and Hezekiah spread it out in the sight of the Lord.

15 And Hezekiah prayed to the Lord, saying:

16 "O Lord of hosts, the God of Israel who sits upon the Cherubim: you alone are God of all the kingdoms of the earth. You have made heaven and earth.

17 O Lord, incline your ear and listen. O Lord, open your eyes and see. And hear all the words of Sennacherib, which he has sent to blaspheme the living God.

18 For truly, O Lord, the kings of the Assyrians have laid waste to countries and territories.

19 And they have cast their gods into the fire. For these were not gods, but the works of men's hands, of wood and of stone. And they broke them into pieces.

20 And now, O Lord our God, save us from his hand. And let all the kingdoms of the earth acknowledge that you alone are Lord."

21 And Isaiah, the son of Amoz, sent to Hezekiah, saying: "Thus says the Lord, the God of Israel: Because of what you have prayed to me about Sennacherib, the king of the Assyrians,

22 this is the word that the Lord has spoken over him: The virgin daughter of Zion has despised you and mocked you. The daughter of Jerusalem has shaken her head at you.

23 Whom have you insulted? And whom have you blasphemed? And against whom have you lifted up your voice and raised up your eyes on high? Against the Holy One of Israel!

24 By the hand of your servants, you have reproached the Lord. And you have said: 'With a multitude of my four-horse chariots, I have ascended the heights of the mountains adjoining Lebanon. And I will cut down its lofty cedars and its choice pine trees. And I will reach the top of its summit, to the forest of its Carmel.

25 I dug deep, and I drank water, and I dried up all the river banks with the sole of my foot.'

26 Have you not heard what I have done to it in past times? In ancient times, I formed it. And now I have brought it forth. And it has been made so that the hills and the fortified cities would fight together, unto its destruction.

27 Their inhabitants had unsteady hands. They trembled and were confused. They became like the plants of the field, and the grass of the pastures, and like the weeds on the rooftops, which wither before they are mature.

28 I know your habitation, and your arrival, and your departure, and your madness against me.

29 When you became angry against me, your arrogance rose up to my ears. Therefore, I will place a ring in your nose, and a bit between your lips. And I will turn you back on the road by which you arrived.

30 But this shall be a sign for you: Eat, in this year, whatever springs up on its own. And in the second year, eat fruits. But in the third year, sow and reap, and plant vineyards, and eat their fruit.

31 And what will be saved from the house of Judah, and what is left behind, will form deep roots, and will bear high fruits.

32 For from Jerusalem, a remnant shall go forth, and salvation from mount Zion. The zeal of the Lord of hosts will accomplish this.

33 For this reason, thus says the Lord about the king of the Assyrians: He will not enter this city, nor shoot an arrow into it, nor overtake it with a shield, nor dig a rampart all around it.

34 He will return on the road by which he arrived. And into this city, he will not enter, says the Lord.

35 And I will protect this city, so that I may save it for my own sake, and for the sake of David, my servant."

36 Then the Angel of the Lord went forth and struck down, in the camp of the Assyrians, one hundred eighty-five thousand. And they arose in the morning, and behold, all these were dead bodies.

37 And Sennacherib, the king of the Assyrians, departed and went away. And he returned and lived at Nineveh.

38 And it happened that, as he was adoring his god in the temple of Nisroch, his sons, Adramelech and Sharezer, struck him with the sword. And they fled into the land of Ararat. And Esarhaddon, his son, reigned in his place.

Isaiah 38

1 In those days Hezekiah became ill and was near death. And so, Isaiah, the son of Amoz, the prophet, entered to him, and he said to him: "Thus says the Lord: Put your house in order, for you shall die, and you shall not live."

2 And Hezekiah turned his face toward the wall, and he prayed to the Lord.

3 And he said: "I beg you, Lord, I beseech you, to remember how I walked before you in truth and with a whole heart, and that I have done what is good in your sight." And Hezekiah wept with a great weeping.

4 And the word of the Lord came to Isaiah, saying:

5 "Go and say to Hezekiah: Thus says the Lord, the God of David, your father: I have heard your prayer, and I have seen your tears. Behold, I will add fifteen years to your days.

6 And I will rescue you and this city from the hand of the king of the Assyrians, and I will protect it.

7 And this will be a sign for you from the Lord, that the Lord will do this word, which he has spoken:

8 Behold, I will cause the shadow of the lines, which has now descended on the sundial of Ahaz, to move in reverse for ten lines." And so, the sun moved backward by ten lines, through the degrees by which it had descended.

9 The writing of Hezekiah, the king of Judah, after he had fallen ill and had recovered from his sickness:

10 "I said: In the middle of my days, I will go to the gates of Hell. So I sought the remainder of my years.

11 I said: I will not see the Lord God in the land of the living. I will no longer behold man, nor the habitation of rest.

12 My longevity has been taken away; it has been folded up and taken from me, like the tent of a shepherd. My life has been cut off, as if by a weaver. While I was still beginning, he cut me off. From morning until evening, you have marked out my limits.

13 I hoped, even until morning. Like a lion, so has he crushed all my bones. From morning until evening, you have marked my limits.

14 I will cry out, like a young swallow. I will meditate, like a dove. My eyes have been weakened by gazing upward. O Lord, I suffer violence! Answer in my favor.

15 What can I say, or what would he answer me, since he himself has done this? I will acknowledge to you all my years, in the bitterness of my soul.

16 O Lord, if such is life, and if the life of my spirit is of such a kind, may you correct me and may you cause me to live.

17 Behold, in peace my bitterness is most bitter. But you have rescued my soul, so that it would not perish. You have cast all my sins behind your back.

18 For Hell will not confess to you, and death will not praise you. Those who descend into the pit will not hope for your truth.

19 The living, the living, these will give praise to you, as I also do this day! The father will make the truth known to the sons.

20 O Lord, save me! And we will sing our psalms, all the days of our life, in the house of the Lord."

21 Now Isaiah had ordered them to take a paste of figs, and to spread it like plaster over the wound, so that he would be healed.

22 And Hezekiah said, "What will be the sign that I may go up to the house of the Lord?"

Isaiah 39

1 At that time, Merodach Baladan, the son of Baladan, the king of Babylon, sent letters and gifts to Hezekiah. For he had heard that he had fallen ill and had recovered.

2 And Hezekiah rejoiced over them, and he showed them the storehouses of his aromatic spices, and of the silver and gold, and of the perfumes and precious ointments, and all the repositories for his belongings, and all the things that were found in his treasures. There was nothing in his house, nor in all his dominion, that Hezekiah did not show them.

3 Then Isaiah the prophet entered before king Hezekiah, and he said to him, "What did these men say, and from where did they come to you?" And Hezekiah said, "They came to me from a far away land, from Babylon."

4 And he said, "What did they see in your house?" And Hezekiah said: "They have seen all the things that are in my house. There was nothing that I did not show them among my treasures."

5 And Isaiah said to Hezekiah: "Hear the word of the Lord of hosts:

6 Behold, the days are coming when all that is in your house, and all that your fathers have stored up, even to this day, will be taken away to Babylon. There will be nothing left behind, says the Lord.

7 And your children, who will issue from you, whom you will produce, they will be taken away. And they will become eunuchs in the palace of the king of Babylon."

8 And Hezekiah said to Isaiah, "The word of the Lord which he has spoken is good." And he said, "But let there be peace and truth in my days."

Isaiah 40

1 "Be consoled, be consoled, O my people!" says your God.

2 Speak to the heart of Jerusalem, and call out to her! For her malice has reached its end. Her iniquity has been forgiven. She has received double for all her sins from the hand of the Lord.

3 The voice of one crying out in the desert: "Prepare the way of the Lord! Make straight the paths of our God, in a solitary place.

4 Every valley will be exalted, and every mountain and hill will be brought low. And the crooked will be straightened, and the uneven will become level ways.

5 And the glory of the Lord will be revealed. And all flesh together will see that the mouth of the Lord has spoken."

6 The voice of one saying, "Cry out!" And I said, "What should I cry out?" "All flesh is grass, and all its glory is like the flower of the field.

7 The grass has dried up, and the flower has fallen. For the Spirit of the Lord has blown over it. Truly, the people are like grass.

8 The grass has dried up, and the flower has fallen. But the Word of our Lord remains for eternity."

9 You who evangelize Zion, climb a high mountain! You who evangelize Jerusalem, lift up your voice with strength! Lift it up! Do not be afraid! Say to the cities of Judah: "Behold, your God!"

10 Behold, the Lord God will arrive in strength, and his arm will rule. Behold, his reward is with him, and his work is before him.

11 He will pasture his flock like a shepherd. He will gather together the lambs with his arm, and he will lift them up to his bosom, and he himself will carry the very young.

12 Who has measured the waters in the hollow of his hand, and who has weighed the heavens with his palm? Who has suspended the mass of the earth with three fingers, and who has weighed the mountains on a balance and the hills on a scale?

13 Who has assisted the Spirit of the Lord? Or who has been his counselor and has revealed things to him?

14 With whom has he consulted? And who has instructed him, and taught him the path of justice, and guided him to knowledge, and revealed the way of understanding to him?

15 Behold, the nations are like a drop of water in a bucket, and they are considered as the smallest grain on a balance. Behold, the islands are like a little dust.

16 And Lebanon will not be sufficient to start a fire, and its animals will not be sufficient for a burnt offering.

17 All the nations in his sight are as if they did not exist, and they are considered by him as if they were nothingness and emptiness.

18 Therefore, to whom would you liken God? Or with what image would you replace him?

19 Should the workman cast a statue? Or has the goldsmith formed it with gold, or the silversmith with plates of silver?

20 He has chosen strong wood that will not decay. The skillful artisan seeks a way to set up an idol that cannot be moved.

21 Do you not know? Have you not heard? Has it not been announced to you from the beginning? Have you not understood the foundations of the earth?

22 He is the One who sits upon the globe of the earth, and its inhabitants are like locusts. He extends the heavens as if they were nothing, and he spreads them out like a tent, in which to dwell.

23 He has brought those who examine what is secret to nothingness. He has brought the judges of the earth to emptiness.

24 And certainly, their stalk was neither planted, nor sown, nor rooted in the ground. He has suddenly blown them across them, and they have withered, and a whirlwind will carry them away like chaff.

25 "And to whom would you compare me or equate me?" says the Holy One.

26 Lift up your eyes on high, and see who has created these things. He leads forth their army by number, and he calls them all by name. Because of the fullness of his strength and robustness and virtue, not one of them was left behind.

27 Why do you say this, O Jacob, and why do you speak this way, O Israel? "My way has been hidden from the Lord, and my judgment escaped notice by my God."

28 Do you not know, or have you not heard? The Lord is the eternal God, who has created the limits of the earth. He does not diminish, and he does not struggle. Neither is his wisdom searchable.

29 It is he who gives strength to the weary, and it is he who increases fortitude and strength in those who are failing.

30 Servants will struggle and fail, and young men will fall into infirmity.

31 But those who hope in the Lord will renew their strength. They will take up wings like eagles. They will run and not struggle. They will walk and not tire.

Isaiah 41

1 Let the islands be silent before me, and let the nations take new strength. Let them draw near, and then speak. Let us apply for judgment together.

2 Who has raised up a just man from the east, and has called him to follow him? He will place the nations under his gaze, and he will rule over kings. He will cause them to be like dust before his sword, like chaff driven by the wind before his bow.

3 He will pursue them. He will pass by in peace. No trace will appear after his feet.

4 Who has worked and accomplished these things, calling to the generations from the beginning? "It is I, the Lord! I am the first and the last."

5 The islands saw it and were afraid. The ends of the earth were stupefied. They drew near and arrived.

6 Each one will help his neighbor and will say to his brother, "Be strengthened."

7 The coppersmith striking with the mallet encouraged him who was forging at that time, saying, "It is ready for soldering." And he strengthened it with nails, so that it would not be moved.

8 But you, O Israel, are my servant, O Jacob, whom I have chosen, the offspring of my friend Abraham.

9 For his sake, I have taken you from the ends of the earth, and I have called you from its distant places. And I said to you: "You are my servant. I have chosen you, and I have not cast you aside."

10 Do not be afraid, for I am with you. Do not turn away, for I am your God. I have strengthened you, and I have assisted you, and the right hand of my just one has upheld you.

11 Behold, all who fight against you shall be confounded and ashamed. They will be as if they did not exist, and the men who contradict you will perish.

12 You will seek them, and you will not find them. The men who rebel against you will be as if they did not exist. And the men who make war against you will be like something that has been consumed.

13 For I am the Lord your God. I take you by your hand, and I say to you: Do not be afraid. I have helped you.

14 Fear not, O worm of Jacob, you who are dead within Israel. I have helped you, says the Lord, your Redeemer, the Holy One of Israel.

15 I have established you like a new threshing cart, having serrated blades. You will thresh the mountains and crush them. And you will turn the hills into chaff.

16 You will winnow them, and the wind will blow them away, and the whirlwind will scatter them. And you shall exult in the Lord; you shall rejoice in the Holy One of Israel.

17 The indigent and the poor are seeking water, but there is none. Their tongue has been dried up by thirst. I, the Lord, will heed them. I, the God of Israel, will not abandon them.

18 I will open rivers in the high hills, and fountains in the midst of the plains. I will turn the desert into pools of water, and the impassable land into streams of water.

19 I will plant the cedar in a deserted place, with the thorn, and the myrtle, and the olive tree. In the desert, I will plant the pine, and the elm, and the box tree together,

20 so that they may see and know, acknowledge and understand, together, that the hand of the Lord has accomplished this, and that the Holy One of Israel has created it.

21 Bring your case forward, says the Lord. Bring it here, if you have anything to allege, says the King of Jacob.

22 Let them approach and announce to us the things that will occur. Announce to us the things that were before. And we will apply our heart to them, and we will know their end. And so, reveal to us the things that will occur.

23 Announce the things that will occur in the future, and we will know that you are gods. Likewise, accomplish good or evil, if you are able, and let us speak of it and see it together.

24 Behold, you exist out of nothing, and your work is from what does not exist; he who has chosen you is an abomination.

25 I have raised up one from the north, and he will arrive from the rising of the sun. He will call upon my name, and he will reduce magistrates to mud, like a potter working with clay.

26 Who has announced this from its rising, so that we may know it, or from its beginning, so that we may say, "You are just." There is no one who either announces, or predicts, or hears your words.

27 The first one will say to Zion: "Behold, they are here," and to Jerusalem, "I will present an evangelist."

28 And I saw, and there was no one among any of them to consult, or who, when I asked, could answer a word.

29 Behold, they are all unjust, and their works are empty. Their idols are wind and emptiness.

Isaiah 42

1 Behold my servant, I will uphold him, my elect, with him my soul is well-pleased. I have sent my Spirit upon him. He will offer judgment to the nations.

2 He will not cry out, and he will not show favoritism to anyone; neither will his voice be heard abroad.

3 The bruised reed he will not break, and the smoldering wick he will not extinguish. He will lead forth judgment unto truth.

4 He will not be saddened or troubled, until he establishes judgment on earth. And the islands will await his law.

5 Thus says the Lord God, who created the heavens and expanded it, who formed the earth and all that springs from it, who gives breath to the people in it, and spirit to those walking on it.

6 I, the Lord, have called you in justice, and I have taken your hand and preserved you. And I have presented you as a covenant of the people, as a light to the Gentiles,

7 so that you may open the eyes of the blind, and lead out the prisoner from confinement and those sitting in darkness from the house of incarceration.

8 I am the Lord; this is my name. I will not give my glory to another, nor my praise to graven things.

9 The things that were first, behold, they have arrived. And I also announce what is new. Before these things arise, I will cause you to hear about them.

10 Sing to the Lord a new canticle, sing his praise from the ends of the earth, you who descend into the sea and all its fullness, the islands and their inhabitants.

11 Let the desert and its cities be lifted up. Kedar will dwell in houses. O inhabitants of the rock, give praise! They will cry out from the top of the mountains.

12 They will give glory to the Lord, and they will announce his praise to the islands.

13 The Lord will go forth like a strong man; like a man of battle, he will stir up zeal. He will shout and cry out. He will prevail against his enemies.

14 I have always been quiet; I have been silent; I have been patient. I will speak like a woman giving birth. I will destroy and consume, all at once.

15 I will desolate the mountains and the hills, and I will wither all their grass. And I will turn rivers into islands, and I will dry up the pools of water.

16 And I will lead the blind along a way which they do not know. And I will cause them to walk along paths with which they were unfamiliar. I will turn darkness into light before them, and crooked into straight. These things I have done for them. For I have not abandoned them.

17 They have been converted again. Let those who trust in graven idols be greatly confounded, for they say to a molten thing, "You are our god."

18 You who are deaf, hear! You who are blind, turn your gaze and see!

19 Who is blind, except my servant? Who is deaf, except the one to whom I have sent my messengers? Who is blind, except the one who has been sold? And who is blind, except the servant of the Lord?

20 You who see many things, will you not keep them? You who have open ears, will you not listen?

21 And the Lord was willing to sanctify him, and to magnify the law, and to exalt him.

22 But this same people has robbed and laid waste. All their youth are a snare, and they have been hidden in houses of confinement. They have become victims; there is no one who may rescue them. They have been plundered; there is no one who may say, "Restore."

23 Who is there among you who will hear this, who will listen closely and heed this in the future?

24 Who has handed over Jacob into plunder, and Israel into devastation? It is not the Lord himself, against whom we have sinned? And they were not willing to walk in his ways, and they have not listened to his law.

25 And so, he poured out over him the indignation of his fury and a strong battle. And he burned him all around, and he did not realize it. And he set him on fire, and he did not understand it.

Isaiah 43

1 And now thus says the Lord who created you, O Jacob, and who formed you, O Israel: Do not be afraid. For I have redeemed you, and I have called you by your name. You are mine.

2 When you pass through the waters, I will be with you, and the rivers will not cover you. When you walk through fire, you will not be burned, and the flames will not scorch you.

3 For I am the Lord your God, the Holy One of Israel, your Saviour. I have presented Egypt as your atonement, Ethiopia and Seba on your behalf.

4 Since then, you have become honorable in my eyes, and glorious. I have loved you, and I will present men on behalf of you, and people on behalf of your life.

5 Fear not, for I am with you. I will lead your offspring from the East, and I will gather you from the West.

6 I will say to the North, "Release him," and to the South, "Do not turn him away." Bring my sons from far away, and my daughters from the ends of the earth.

7 And each one who calls upon my name, I have created for my glory. I have formed him, and I have made him.

8 Lead forth the people who are blind and have eyes, who are deaf and have ears.

9 All the nations have been assembled together, and the tribes have been collected. Who among you will announce this, and who will cause us to listen to the things that are first? Let them present their witnesses. Let them act justly, and listen, and say: "It is true."

10 You are my witnesses, says the Lord, and you are my servant, whom I have chosen, so that you may know, and may believe in me, and so that you may understand that I am the same. Before me, there was no god formed, and after me there will be none.

11 I am. I am the Lord. And there is no savior apart from me.

12 I have announced, and I have saved. I have caused it to be heard. And there was no stranger among you. You are my witnesses, says the Lord, and I am God.

13 And from the beginning, I am the same. And there is no one who can rescue from my hand. I act, and who can turn it aside?

14 Thus says the Lord, your Redeemer, the Holy One of Israel: For your sake, I sent to Babylon, and tore down all their bars, with the Chaldeans who glory in their ships.

15 I am the Lord, your Holy One, the Creator of Israel, your King.

16 Thus says the Lord, who gave you a way through the sea and a path through the torrent of waters,

17 who led out the chariot and the horse, the column of robust troops. They went to sleep together, and they will not arise. They have been crushed like flax, and they have been extinguished.

18 You need not call to mind the past, nor consider the things of antiquity.

19 Behold, I am accomplishing new things. And presently, they will spring forth. With certainty, you will know them. I will make a way in the desert, and rivers in an impassible place.

20 The wild beasts of the field will glorify me, with the serpents and the ostriches. For I have brought waters to the desert, rivers to inaccessible places, in order to give drink to my people, to my elect.

21 This is the people whom I have formed for myself. They will speak my praise.

22 But you have not called upon me, O Jacob, nor have you struggled for me, O Israel.

23 You have not offered me the ram of your holocaust, and you have not glorified me with your victims. I have not burdened you with oblations, nor have I wearied you with incense.

24 You have bought me no sweet cane with money, and you have not inebriated me with the fat of your victims. Yet truly, you have burdened me with your sins; you have wearied me with your iniquities.

25 I am. I am the very One who wipes away your iniquities for my own sake. And I will not remember your sins.

26 Call me to mind, and let us go to judgment together. If you have anything to justify yourself, explain it.

27 Your first father sinned, and your interpreters have betrayed me.

28 And so, I have defiled the holy leaders. I have handed over Jacob to slaughter, and Israel to calumny.

Isaiah 44

1 And now, listen, Jacob, my servant, and Israel, whom I have chosen.

2 Thus says the Lord, who made and formed you, your Helper from the womb: Do not be afraid, Jacob, my servant and my most righteous, whom I have chosen.

3 For I will pour out waters upon the thirsty ground, and rivers upon the dry land. I will pour out my Spirit upon your offspring, and my benediction upon your stock.

4 And they will spring up among the plants, like willows beside running waters.

5 This one will say, "I am the Lord's," and that one will call himself by the name of Jacob, and yet another will write with his hand, "For the Lord," and he will take the name Israel.

6 Thus says the Lord, the King and Redeemer of Israel, the Lord of hosts: I am the first, and I am the last, and there is no God apart from me.

7 Who is like me? Let him call out and announce it. And let him explain to me the order of things, since it is I who appointed the ancient people. The things of the near and the distant future, let him announce them.

8 Do not be afraid, and do not be disturbed. From the time when I caused you to listen, I also announced it. You are my witnesses. Is there another God beside me, also a Maker, whom I have not known?

9 All of those who create idols are nothing, and their most beloved things will not benefit them. These are their witnesses, for they do not see, and they do not understand, so that they might be confounded.

10 Who has formed a god or cast a molten image, which is useful for nothing?

11 Behold, all those who partake in this will be confounded. For these makers are men. They will all assemble together. They will stand and be terrified. And they will be confounded together.

12 The maker of iron has wrought with his file. With coals and hammers, he has formed it, and he has wrought with the strength of his arm. He will hunger and grow faint. He will not drink water, and he will become weary.

13 The maker of wood has extended his ruler. He has formed it with a plane. He has made it with corners, and he has smoothed its curves. And he has made the image of a man, a seemingly beautiful man, dwelling in a house.

14 He has cut down cedars; he has taken the evergreen oak, and the oak that stood among the trees of the forest. He has planted the pine tree, which the rain has nourished.

15 And it is used by men for fuel. He took from it and warmed himself. And he set it on fire and baked bread. But from the remainder, he made a god, and he adored it. He made an idol, and he bowed down before it.

16 Part of it, he burned with fire, and with part of it, he cooked meat; he boiled food and was filled. And he was warmed, and so he said: "Ah, I am warm. I have gazed at the fire."

17 But from its remainder, he made a god and a graven image for himself. He bowed down before it, and he adored it, and he prayed to it, saying: "Free me! For you are my god."

18 They have neither known nor understood. For their eyes are obscured, lest they see with their eyes and understand with their heart.

19 They do not consider in their mind, nor do they know, nor do they think to say: "I have burned part of it in the fire, and I have baked bread upon its coals. I have cooked flesh and I have eaten. And from its remainder, should I make an idol? Should I fall prostrate before the trunk of a tree?"

20 Part of it is ashes. His foolish heart adores it. And he will not liberate his soul, and he will not say, "Perhaps there is a lie in my right hand."

21 Remember these things, O Jacob, O Israel. For you are my servant. I have formed you. You are my servant, Israel. Do not forget me.

22 I have wiped away your iniquities like a cloud, and your sins like a mist. Return to me, because I have redeemed you.

23 Give praise, O heavens! For the Lord has shown mercy. Shout with joy, O ends of the earth! Let the mountains resound with praise, with the forest and all its trees. For the Lord has redeemed Jacob, and Israel will be glorified.

24 Thus says the Lord, your Redeemer, and your Maker from the womb: I am the Lord, who makes all things, who alone extends the heavens, who makes the earth firm. And there is no one with me.

25 I make the signs of the diviners useless, and I turn the seers to madness. I turn the wise backwards, and make their knowledge into foolishness.

26 I lift up the word of my servant, and I fulfill the counsel of my messengers. I say to Jerusalem, "You shall be inhabited," and to the cities of Judah, "You shall be rebuilt," and I will lift up its deserts.

27 I say to the depths, "Be desolate," and, "I will dry up your rivers."

28 I say to Cyrus, "You are my shepherd, and you will accomplish all that I will." I say to Jerusalem, "You shall be built," and to the Temple, "Your foundations shall be laid."

Isaiah 45

1 Thus says the Lord to my anointed Cyrus, whose right hand I hold, so that I may subjugate the nations before his face, and I may turn the backs of kings, and I may open the doors before him, and so that the gates will not be shut.

2 I will go before you. And I will humble the glorious ones of the earth. I will shatter the gates of brass, and I will break apart the bars of iron.

3 And I will give you hidden treasures and the knowledge of secret things, so that you may know that I am the Lord, the God of Israel, who calls your name.

4 For the sake of Jacob, my servant, and Israel, my elect, I have even called you by your name. I have taken you up, and you have not known me.

5 I am the Lord, and there is no one else. There is no god beside me. I girded you, and you have not known me.

6 So may those who are from the rising of the sun, and those who are from its setting, know that there is no one beside me. I am the Lord, and there is no other.

7 I form the light and create the darkness. I make peace and create disaster. I, the Lord, do all these things.

8 Send down dew from above, O heavens, and let the clouds rain down upon the just! Let the earth open and spring forth a savior! And let justice rise up at once! I, the Lord, have created him.

9 Woe to him who contradicts his Maker, a mere shard from an earthen vessel! Should the clay say to the potter, "What are you making?" or, "Your work is not made by your hands?"

10 Woe to him who says to his father, "Why did you conceive?" or to a woman, "Why did you give birth?"

11 Thus says the Lord, the Holy One of Israel, his Maker: Would you question me about the future, concerning my sons, and command me concerning the work of my hands?

12 I made the earth, and I created man upon it. My hand stretched out the heavens, and I have commanded all their hosts.

13 I have raised him up unto justice, and I will direct all his ways. He himself will build my city and release my captives, but not for ransom or gifts, says the Lord, the God of hosts.

14 Thus says the Lord: The labor of Egypt, and the business dealings of Ethiopia, and of the Sabeans, men of stature, will pass to you and will be yours. They will walk behind you. They will travel, bound in irons. And they will adore you and petition you: "In you alone is God, and there is no God apart from you.

15 Truly, you are a hidden God, the God of Israel, the Savior."

16 They have all been confounded and should be ashamed! These fabricators of errors have departed together into confusion!

17 Israel is saved in the Lord by an eternal salvation. You will not be confounded, and you will not be ashamed, even forever and ever.

18 For thus says the Lord, who created the heavens, God himself who formed the earth and made it, the very Molder of it. He did not create it to no purpose. He formed it so that it would be inhabited. I am the Lord, and there is no other.

19 I have not spoken in secret, in a dark place of the earth. I have not said to the offspring of Jacob, "Seek me in vain." I am the Lord, who speaks justice, who announces what is right.

20 Assemble yourselves, and approach, and draw near together, you who have been saved among the Gentiles. They lack knowledge, who lift up the wood of their sculpture, and who petition a god unable to save.

21 Announce it, and approach, and consult together. Who has caused this to be heard from the beginning, and who has foretold it from that time? Is it not I, the Lord? And is there some other god beside me? I am a just God who saves, and there is no one except me.

22 All ends of the earth, be converted to me, and you will be saved. For I am God, and there is no other.

23 I have sworn by myself. The Word of justice will proceed from my mouth, and it will not turn back.

24 For every knee shall bend to me, and every tongue shall swear it.

25 Therefore, he will say, "In the Lord are my justices and my dominion." They will go to him. And all who fight against him will be confounded.

26 In the Lord, all the offspring of Israel will be justified and praised.

Isaiah 46

1 Bel has been broken. Nebo has been crushed. Their idols have been placed upon beasts and cattle, your grievous heavy burdens, even unto exhaustion.

2 They have been melted down, or have been smashed together. They were not able to save the one who carried them, and their life will go into captivity.

3 Listen to me, house of Jacob, all the remnant of the house of Israel, who are carried in my bosom, who were born from my womb.

4 Even to your old age, I am the same. And even with your grey hairs, I will carry you. I have made you, and I will sustain you. I will carry you, and I will save you.

5 To whom would you likened me, or equate me, or compare me, or consider me to be similar?

6 You take gold from a bag, and you weigh silver on a scale, so as to hire a goldsmith to make a god. And they fall prostrate and adore.

7 They carry him on their shoulders, supporting him, and they set him in his place. And he will stand still and will not move from his place. But even when they will cry out to him, he will not hear. He will not save them from tribulation.

8 Remember this, and be confounded. Return, you transgressors, to the heart.

9 Remember the past ages. For I am God, and there is no other god. There is no one like me.

10 From the beginning, I announce the last things, and from the start, the things that have not yet been done, saying: My plan will stand firm, and my entire will shall be done.

11 I call a bird from the east, and from a far away land, the man of my will. And I have spoken it, and I will carry it out. I have created, and I will act.

12 Hear me, you who are hard of heart, who are far from justice!

13 I have brought my justice near. It will not be far away, and my salvation will not be delayed. I will grant salvation in Zion, and my glory in Israel.

Isaiah 47

1 Descend, sit in the dust, O virgin daughter of Babylon! Sit on the ground. There is no throne for the daughter of the Chaldeans. For you shall no longer be called delicate and tender.

2 Take a millstone and grind meal. Uncover your shame, bare your shoulder, reveal your legs, cross the streams.

3 Your disgrace will be revealed, and your shame will be seen. I will seize vengeance, and no man will withstand me.

4 Our Redeemer, the Lord of hosts is his name, the Holy One of Israel.

5 Sit in silence, and enter into darkness, O daughter of the Chaldeans! For you shall no longer be called the noblewoman of kingdoms.

6 I was angry with my people. I have polluted my inheritance, and I have given them into your hand. You have not shown mercy to them. You have greatly increased the burden of your yoke upon the elders.

7 And you have said: "I will be a noblewoman forever." You have not set these things upon your heart, and you have not remembered your end.

8 And now, hear these things, you who are delicate and have confidence, who say in your heart: "I am, and there is no one greater than me. I will not sit as a widow, and I will not know barrenness."

9 These two things will suddenly overwhelm you in one day: barrenness and widowhood. All things shall overwhelm you, because of the multitude of your sorceries and because of the great cruelty of your enchantments.

10 And you have trusted in your malice, and you have said: "There is no one who sees me." Your wisdom and your knowledge, these have deceived you. And you have said in your heart: "I am, and beside me there is no other."

11 Evil will overwhelm you, and you will not notice its rising. And calamity will fall violently over you, and you will not be able to avert it. You will suddenly be overwhelmed by a misery such as you have never known.

12 Stand with your incantations, and with the multitude of your sorceries, in which you have labored from your youth, as if somehow it might benefit you, or as if it were able to make you stronger.

13 You have failed in the multitude of your plans! Let the seers stand and save you, those who were contemplating the stars, and figuring the months, so that from these they might announce to you the things to come.

14 Behold, they have become like stubble. Fire has consumed them. They will not free themselves from the power of the flames. These are not coals by which they may be warmed, nor is this a fire which they may sit beside.

15 So have all these things, in which you have labored, become to you. Your merchants from your youth, each one has erred in his own way. There is no one who can save you.

Isaiah 48

1 Listen to these things, O house of Jacob, you who are called by the name of Israel, and who went forth from the waters of Judah. You swear by the name of the Lord and you call to mind the God of Israel, but not in truth, and not in justice.

2 For they have been called from the holy city, and they have been founded upon the God of Israel. The Lord of hosts is his name.

3 From that time, I announced the former things. They went forth from my mouth, and I have caused them to be heard. I wrought these things suddenly, and they were fulfilled.

4 For I knew that you are stubborn, and that your neck is like an iron sinew, and that your forehead is like brass.

5 From that time, I foretold to you. Before these things happened, I revealed them to you, lest you say: "My idols have accomplished these things, and my graven and molten images have commanded them."

6 See all the things that you have heard. But were you the ones who announced them? From that time, I caused you to hear about new things, and you do not know how these were preserved.

7 They are created now, and not in that time. And even before today, you did not hear of them; otherwise, you might say, "Behold, I knew them."

8 You have neither heard, nor known, nor were your ears open in that time. For I knew that you would transgress greatly, and so I called you a transgressor from the womb.

9 For the sake of my name, I will take the face of my fury far away. And for the sake of my praise, I will bridle you, lest you perish.

10 Behold, I have refined you, but not like silver. I have chosen you for the furnace of poverty.

11 For my sake, for my own sake, I will do it, so that I may not be blasphemed. For I will not give my glory to another.

12 Listen to me, O Jacob, and Israel whom I call. I am the same, I am the first, and I am the last.

13 Also, my hand has founded the earth, and my right hand has measured the heavens. I will call them, and they will stand together.

14 Gather together, all of you, and listen. Who among them has announced these things? The Lord has loved him; he will do his will with Babylon, and his arm is upon the Chaldeans.

15 I am, I have spoken, and I have called him. I have led him forward, and his way has been straight.

16 Draw near to me, and listen to this. From the beginning, I have not spoken in secret. From the time before it happened, I was there. And now, the Lord God has sent me, and his Spirit.

17 Thus says the Lord, your Redeemer, the Holy One of Israel: I am the Lord, your God, who teaches you beneficial things, who guides you in the way that you walk.

18 If only you had paid attention to my commandments! Your peace would have been like a river, and your justice would have been like the waves of the sea,

19 and your offspring would have been like the sand, and the stock from your loins would have been like its stones. His name would not have passed away, nor would it have been worn away before my face.

20 Depart from Babylon! Flee from the Chaldeans! Announce it with a voice of exultation. Cause it to be heard, and carry it even to the ends of the earth. Say: "The Lord has redeemed his servant Jacob."

21 They did not thirst in the desert, when he led them out. He produced water from the rock for them. For he split the rock, and the waters flowed out.

22 "There is no peace for the impious," says the Lord.

Isaiah 49

1 Pay attention, you islands, and listen closely, you far away peoples. The Lord has called me from the womb; from the womb of my mother, he has been mindful of my name.

2 And he has appointed my mouth as a sharp sword. In the shadow of his hand, he has protected me. And he has appointed me as an elect arrow. In his quiver, he has hidden me.

3 And he has said to me: "You are my servant, Israel. For in you, I will glory."

4 And I said: "I have labored toward emptiness. I have consumed my strength without purpose and in vain. Therefore, my judgment is with the Lord, and my work is with my God."

5 And now, says the Lord, who formed me from the womb as his servant, so that I may bring back Jacob to him, for Israel will not be gathered together, but I have been glorified in the eyes of the Lord and my God has become my strength,

6 and so he has said: "It is a small thing that you should be my servant so as to raise up the tribes of Jacob, and so as to convert the dregs of Israel. Behold, I have offered you as a light for the Gentiles, so that you may be my salvation, even to the furthest regions of the earth."

7 Thus says the Lord, the Redeemer of Israel, his Holy One, to a contemptible soul, to an abominable nation, to the servant of lords: The kings will see, and the princes will rise up, and they will adore, because of the Lord. For he is faithful, and he is the Holy One of Israel, who has chosen you.

8 Thus says the Lord: In a pleasing time, I have heeded you, and in the day of salvation, I have assisted you. And I have preserved you, and I have presented you as a covenant of the people, so that you would lift up the earth, and possess the scattered inheritances,

9 so that you would say to those who are bound, "Go forth!" and to those who are in darkness, "Be released!" They will pasture along the roads, and their pastures will be in every open place.

10 They will not hunger or thirst, nor will the heat of the sun beat down upon them. For the one who takes pity on them will rule them, and he will give them to drink from fountains of waters.

11 And I will make all my mountains into a road, and my paths will be exalted.

12 Behold, some will come from far away, and behold, others from the north and from the sea, and still others from the land of the south.

13 Give praise, O heavens! And exult, O earth! Let the mountains give praise with jubilation! For the Lord has consoled his people, and he will take pity on his poor ones.

14 And Zion said: "The Lord has abandoned me, and the Lord has forgotten me."

15 Can a woman forget her infant, so as not to take pity on the child of her womb? But even if she would forget, still I shall never forget you.

16 Behold, I have engraved you on my hands. Your walls are always before my eyes.

17 Your builders have arrived. Those who would tear you down and destroy you, they will depart from you.

18 Lift up your eyes all around, and see: all these have been gathered together; they have come to you. As I live, says the Lord, you shall be clothed with all these things, as if with an ornament. And like a bride, you shall wrap these things all around you.

19 For your deserts, and your solitary places, and the land of your ruination will now be too narrow, because of all the inhabitants. And those who devoured you will be chased far away.

20 Even the children of your barrenness will say in your ears: "This place is too narrow for me. Make me a spacious place in which to dwell."

21 And you will say in your heart: "Who has conceived them? I was barren and unable to give birth. I was taken away and held captive. And so, who has raised them? I was destitute and alone. And so, where have they been?"

22 Thus says the Lord God: Behold, I will lift up my hand to the Gentiles, and I will exalt my sign before the peoples. And they will carry your sons in their arms, and they will bear your daughters on their shoulders.

23 And kings will be your caretakers, and queens will be your nursemaids. They will reverence you with their face to the ground, and they will lick the dust at your feet. And you will know that I am the Lord. For those who hope in him will not be confounded.

24 Can prey be taken from the strong? Or is anything taken captive by the powerful able to be saved?

25 For thus says the Lord: Certainly, even the captives will be taken away from the strong, even what has been taken by the powerful will be saved. And truly, I will judge those who have judged you, and I will save your children.

26 And I will feed your enemies their own flesh. And they will be inebriated with their own blood, as with new wine. And all flesh will know that I am the Lord, who saves you, and your Redeemer, the Strong One of Jacob.

Isaiah 50

1 Thus says the Lord: What is this bill of divorce for your mother, by which I have dismissed her? Or who is my creditor, to whom I have sold you? Behold, you were sold by your iniquities, and I have dismissed your mother for your wickedness.

2 For I arrived, and there was no man. I called out, and there was no one who would hear. Has my hand been shortened and become small, so that I am unable to redeem? Or is there no power in me to deliver? Behold, at my rebuke, I will make the sea into a desert. I will turn rivers into dry land. The fish will rot for lack of water and will die of thirst.

3 I will clothe the heavens in darkness, and I will make sackcloth their covering.

4 The Lord has given me a learned tongue, so that I would know how to uphold with a word, one who has weakened. He rises in the morning, he rises to my ear in the morning, so that I may heed him like a teacher.

5 The Lord God has opened my ear. And I do not contradict him. I have not turned back.

6 I have given my body to those who strike me, and my cheeks to those who plucked them. I have not averted my face from those who rebuked me and who spit on me.

7 The Lord God is my helper. Therefore, I have not been confounded. Therefore, I have set my face like a very hard rock, and I know that I will not be confounded.

8 He who justifies me is near. Who will speak against me? Let us stand together. Who is my adversary? Let him approach me.

9 Behold, the Lord God is my helper. Who is the one who would condemn me? Behold, they will all be worn away like a garment; the moth will devour them.

10 Who is there among you who fears the Lord? Who hears the voice of his servant? Who has walked in darkness, and there is no light in him? Let him hope in the name of the Lord, and let him lean upon his God.

11 Behold, all you who kindle a fire, wrapped in flames: walk in the light of your fire and in the flames that you have kindled. This has been done to you by my hand. You will sleep in anguish.

Isaiah 51

1 Listen to me, you who follow what is just and who seek the Lord. Pay attention to the rock from which you have been hewn, and to the walls of the pit from which you have been dug.

2 Pay attention to Abraham, your father, and to Sarah, who bore you. For I called him alone, and I blessed him, and I multiplied him.

3 Therefore, the Lord will console Zion, and he will console all its ruins. And he will turn her desert into a place of delights, and her wilderness into a garden of the Lord. Gladness and rejoicing will be found in her, thanksgiving and a voice of praise.

4 Pay attention to me, my people, and listen to me, my tribes. For a law will go forth from me, and my judgment will rest as a light for the nations.

5 My just one is near. My savior has gone forth. And my arms will judge the people. The islands will hope in me, and they will patiently wait for my arm.

6 Lift up your eyes to heaven, and look down to the earth below. For the heavens will vanish like smoke, and the earth will be worn away like a garment, and its inhabitants will pass away in like manner. But my salvation will be forever, and my justice will not fail.

7 Listen to me, you who know what is just, my people who have my law in their heart. Do not be afraid of disgrace among men, and do not dread their blasphemies.

8 For the worm will consume them like a garment, and the moth will devour them like wool. But my salvation will be forever, and my justice will be from generation to generation.

9 Rise up, Rise up! Clothe yourself in strength, O arm of the Lord! Rise up as in the days of antiquity, as in generations long past. Have you not struck the arrogant one and wounded the dragon?

10 Have not you dried up the sea, the waters of the great abyss, and turned the depths of the sea into a road, so that the delivered could cross over it?

11 And now, those who have been redeemed by the Lord will return. And they will arrive in Zion, praising. And everlasting rejoicing will be upon their heads. They will take hold of gladness and rejoicing. Anguish and mourning will flee away.

12 It is I, I myself, who will console you. Who are you that you would be afraid of a mortal man, and of a son of man, who will wither like the grass?

13 And have you forgotten the Lord, your Maker, who extended the heavens, and who founded the earth? And have you been in constant dread, all day long, at the face of his fury, of the one who afflicted you and who had prepared to destroy you? Where is the fury of the oppressor now?

14 Advancing quickly, he will arrive to be revealed, and he will not kill unto utter destruction, nor will his bread fail.

15 But I am the Lord, your God, who stirs up the sea, and who makes the waves swell. The Lord of hosts is my name.

16 I have placed my words in your mouth, and I have protected you in the shadow of my hand, so that you might plant the heavens, and found the earth, and so that you might say to Zion, "You are my people."

17 Lift up, Lift up! Arise, O Jerusalem! You drank, from the hand of the Lord, the cup of his wrath. You drank, even to the bottom of the cup of deep sleep. And you were given to drink, all the way to the dregs.

18 There is no one who can uphold her, out of all the sons whom she has conceived. And there is no one who would take her by the hand, out of all the sons whom she has raised.

19 There are two things which have happened to you. Who will be saddened over you? There is devastation and destruction, and famine and sword. Who will console you?

20 Your sons have been cast out. They have slept at the head of all the roads, and they have been ensnared like a gazelle. They have been filled by the indignation of the Lord, by the rebuke of your God.

21 Therefore, listen to this, O poor little ones, and you who have been inebriated, but not by wine.

22 Thus says your Sovereign, the Lord, and your God, who will fight on behalf of his people: Behold, I have taken the cup of deep sleep from your hand. You shall no longer drink from the bottom of the cup of my indignation.

23 And I will set it in the hand of those who have humiliated you, and who have said to your soul: "Bow down, so that we pass over." And you placed your body on the ground, as a path for them to pass over.

Isaiah 52

1 Rise up, Rise up! Clothe yourself in strength, O Zion! Put on the garments of your glory, O Jerusalem, the city of the Holy One! For the uncircumcised and the unclean will no longer pass through you.

2 Shake yourself from the dust! Arise and sit up, O Jerusalem! Loose the chains from your neck, O captive daughter of Zion!

3 For thus says the Lord: You were sold for nothing, and you will be redeemed without money.

4 For thus says the Lord God: My people descended into Egypt, in the beginning, in order to sojourn there. But the Assyrian oppressed them, without any cause at all.

5 And now, what is left for me here, says the Lord? For my people have been taken away without cause. Their lords treat them unjustly, says the Lord. And my name is being continually blasphemed all day long.

6 Because of this, my people will know my name, in that day. For it is I myself who is speaking. Behold, I am here.

7 How beautiful upon the mountains are the feet of the messenger and the preacher of peace! Announcing good and preaching peace, they are saying to Zion, "Your God will reign!"

8 It is the voice of your watchmen. They have lifted up their voice. They will praise together. For they will see eye to eye, when the Lord converts Zion.

9 Be glad and rejoice together, O deserts of Jerusalem! For the Lord has consoled his people. He has redeemed Jerusalem.

10 The Lord has prepared his holy arm, in the sight of all the Gentiles. And all the ends of the earth will see the salvation of our God.

11 Depart, depart, get out of here! Do not be willing to touch what is polluted. Go out from her midst! Be cleansed, you who bear the vessels of the Lord.

12 For you will not go out in a tumult, nor will you take flight in a hurry. For the Lord will precede you, and the God of Israel will gather you.

13 Behold, my servant will understand; he will be exalted and lifted up, and he will be very sublime.

14 Just as they were stupefied over you, so will his countenance be without glory among men, and his appearance, among the sons of men.

15 He will sprinkle many nations; kings will close their mouth because of him. And those to whom he was not described, have seen. And those who have not heard, have considered.

Isaiah 53

1 Who has believed our report? And to whom has the arm of the Lord been revealed?

2 And he will rise up like a tender plant in his sight, and like a root from the thirsty ground. There is no beautiful or stately appearance in him. For we looked upon him, and there was no aspect, such that we would desire him.

3 He is despised and the least among men, a man of sorrows who knows infirmity. And his countenance was hidden and despised. Because of this, we did not esteem him.

4 Truly, he has taken away our weaknesses, and he himself has carried our sorrows. And we thought of him as if he were a leper, or as if he had been struck by God and humiliated.

5 But he himself was wounded because of our iniquities. He was bruised because of our wickedness. The discipline of our peace was upon him. And by his wounds, we are healed.

6 We have all gone astray like sheep; each one has turned aside to his own way. And the Lord has placed all our iniquity upon him.

7 He was offered up, because it was his own will. And he did not open his mouth. He will be led like a sheep to the slaughter. And he will be mute like a lamb before his shearer. For he will not open his mouth.

8 He was lifted up from anguish and judgment. Who will describe his life? For he has been cut off from the land of the living. Because of the wickedness of my people, I have struck him down.

9 And he will be given a place with the impious for his burial, and with the rich for his death, though he has done no iniquity, nor was deceit in his mouth.

10 But it was the will of the Lord to crush him with infirmity. If he lays down his life because of sin, he will see offspring with long lives, and the will of the Lord will be directed by his hand.

11 Because his soul has labored, he will see and be satisfied. By his knowledge, my just servant will himself justify many, and he himself will carry their iniquities.

12 Therefore, I will allot to him a great number. And he will divide the spoils of the strong. For he has handed over his life to death, and he was reputed among criminals. And he has taken away the sins of many, and he has prayed for the transgressors.

Isaiah 54

1 Give praise, you who are barren and unable to conceive. Sing praise and make a joyful noise, you who have not given birth. For many are the children of the desolate, more so than of her who has a husband, says the Lord.

2 Enlarge the place of your tent and extend the skins of your tabernacles, unsparingly. Lengthen your cords, and strengthen your stakes.

3 For you shall extend to the right and to the left. And your offspring shall inherit the nations, and you shall inhabit the desolate cities.

4 Do not be afraid! For you will not be confounded, and you will not blush. And you will not be put to shame, because you shall forget the confusion of your youth, and you shall no longer remember the disgrace of your widowhood.

5 For the One who made you will rule over you. The Lord of hosts is his name. And your Redeemer, the Holy One of Israel, will be called the God of all the earth.

6 For the Lord has called you, like a woman forsaken and mourning in spirit, and like a wife rejected in her youth, said your God.

7 For a brief moment, I have forsaken you, and with great pities, I will gather you.

8 In a moment of indignation, I have hidden my face from you, for a little while. But with everlasting mercy, I have taken pity on you, said your Redeemer, the Lord.

9 For me, it is just as in the days of Noah, to whom I swore that I would no longer bring in the waters of Noah over the earth. Thus have I sworn not to be angry with you, and not to rebuke you.

10 For the mountains will be moved, and the hills will tremble. But my mercy will not depart from you, and the covenant of my peace will not be shaken, said the Lord, who has compassion on you.

11 O poor little ones, convulsed by the tempest, away from any consolation! Behold, I will set your stones in order, and I will lay your foundation with sapphires,

12 and I will make your ramparts out of jasper, and your gates out of sculpted stones, and all your borders out of desirable stones.

13 All your children will be taught by the Lord. And great will be the peace of your children.

14 And you will be founded in justice. Depart far from oppression, for you will not be afraid. And depart from terror, for it will not approach you.

15 Behold, a settler will arrive, who was not with me, a certain new arrival will be joined to you.

16 Behold, I created the smith who fans the coals of the fire and produces an object by his work, and I have created the slayer who destroys.

17 No object which has been formed to use against you will succeed. And every tongue that resists you in judgment, you shall judge. This is the inheritance of the servants of the Lord, and this is their justice with me, says the Lord.

Isaiah 55

1 All you who thirst, come to the waters. And you who have no money: hurry, buy and eat. Approach, buy wine and milk, without money and without barter.

2 Why do you spend money for what is not bread, and expend your labor for what does not satisfy? Listen very closely to me, and eat what is good, and then your soul will be delighted by a full measure.

3 Incline your ear and draw near to me. Listen, and your soul will live. And I will make an everlasting covenant with you, by the faithful mercies of David.

4 Behold, I have presented him as a witness to the people, as a commander and instructor to the nations.

5 Behold, you will call to a nation that you did not know. And nations that did not know you will rush to you, because of the Lord your God, the Holy One of Israel. For he has glorified you.

6 Seek the Lord, while he is able to be found. Call upon him, while he is near.

7 Let the impious one abandon his way, and the iniquitous man his thoughts, and let him return to the Lord, and he will take pity on him, and to our God, for he is great in forgiveness.

8 For my thoughts are not your thoughts, and your ways are not my ways, says the Lord.

9 For just as the heavens are exalted above the earth, so also are my ways exalted above your ways, and my thoughts above your thoughts.

10 And in the same manner as rain and snow descend from heaven, and no longer return there, but soak the earth, and water it, and cause it to bloom and to provide seed to the sower and bread to the hungry,

11 so also will my word be, which will go forth from my mouth. It will not return to me empty, but it will accomplish whatever I will, and it will prosper in the tasks for which I sent it.

12 For you will go forth rejoicing, and you will be led forward in peace. The mountains and the hills will sing praise before you, and all the trees of the countryside will clap their hands.

13 In place of the shrub, the pine tree will arise, and in place of the nettle, the myrtle tree will grow. And the Lord will be named with an eternal sign, which will not be taken away.

Isaiah 56

1 Thus says the Lord: Preserve judgment, and accomplish justice. For my salvation is close to its arrival, and my justice is close to being revealed.

2 Blessed is the man who does this, and the son of man who holds to this, keeping the Sabbath and not profaning it, guarding his hands and not doing any evil.

3 And let not the son of the new arrival, who adheres to the Lord, speak, saying, "The Lord will divide and separate me from his people." And let not the eunuch say, "Behold, I am a dry tree."

4 For thus says the Lord to the eunuchs: They will keep my Sabbaths, and they will choose the things that I will, and they will hold to my covenant.

5 I will give them a place in my house, within my walls, and a name better than sons and daughters. I will give them an everlasting name, which will never perish.

6 And the sons of the new arrival, who adhere to the Lord so as to worship him and to love his name, shall be his servants: all who keep the Sabbath without profaning it, and who hold to my covenant.

7 I will lead them to my holy mountain, and I will gladden them in my house of prayer. Their holocausts and their victims will be pleasing to me upon my altar. For my house will be called the house of prayer for all peoples.

8 The Lord God, who gathers the dispersed of Israel, says: Even now, I will gather his congregation to him.

9 All beasts of the field, all the beasts of the forest: approach and devour!

10 His watchmen are all blind. They are all ignorant. They are mute dogs without the ability to bark, seeing empty things, sleeping and loving dreams.

11 And these very imprudent dogs have never known satisfaction. The shepherds themselves do not know understanding. All have turned aside in their own way, each one to his own avarice, from the highest even to the least:

12 "Come, let us take wine, and be filled by inebriation. And as it is today, so shall it be tomorrow and for a long time."

Isaiah 57

1 The just man perishes, and there is no one who acknowledges it in his heart; and men of mercy are taken away, for there is no one who understands. For the just man has been taken away before the face of malice.

2 Let peace arrive. Let he who has walked in his righteousness find rest on his bed.

3 But come here, you sons of the prophetess, you offspring of an adulterous man and a fornicating woman.

4 Whom are you mocking? Against whom have you opened your mouth wide and wagged your tongue? Are you not sons of wickedness, a lying offspring,

5 who are being consoled by idols under every leafy tree, immolating little children at the torrents, under the high rocks?

6 Your portion is in the currents of the torrent; this is your lot! And you yourselves have poured out libations to them; you have offered sacrifice. Should I not be angry over these things?

7 Upon a high and lofty mountain, you have placed your bed, and you have ascended to that place to immolate victims.

8 And behind the door, and beyond the post, you have set up your memorial. For you uncovered yourself next to me, and you received an adulterer. You widened your bed, and you formed a pact with them. You loved their bed with an open hand.

9 And you have adorned yourself for the king with ointments, and you have increased your cosmetics. You have sent your representatives to distant places, and you have debased yourself all the way to Hell.

10 You have been wearied by the multitude of your own ways. Yet you did not say, "I will cease." You have found life by your own hand; because of this, you have not prayed.

11 For whose sake have you been anxiously afraid, so that you would lie and not be mindful of me, nor consider me in your heart? For I am silent, and I am like someone who does not see, and so you have forgotten me.

12 I will announce your justice, and your works will not benefit you.

13 When you cry out, let your followers free you. But the wind will carry them all away; a breeze will take them up. But he who has faith in me will inherit the earth and will possess my holy mountain.

14 And I will say: "Make way! Grant passage! Move to the side of the path! Take the obstacles out of the way of my people!"

15 For this is said by the Most High, the Sublime One, who dwells in eternity. And his name is Holy, for he dwells in the exalted and holy place, and he acts with a restrained and humble spirit, to revive the spirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of the contrite.

16 For I will not contend unceasingly, and I will not be angry to the end. For I will exhale my breath, and the Spirit will go forth from my face.

17 Because of the iniquity of his avarice, I was angry, and I struck him down. I concealed my face from you, and I was angry. And he went astray by wandering in his heart.

18 I saw his ways, and I healed him, and I led him back again, and I restored consolations to him and to those who mourn for him.

19 I created the fruit of the lips: peace, peace to him who is far away, and peace to him who is near, said the Lord, and I healed him.

20 But the impious are like the raging sea, which is not able to be quieted, and its waves stir up dirt and mud.

21 There is no peace for the impious, says the Lord God.

Isaiah 58

1 Cry out! Cease not! Exalt your voice like a trumpet, and announce to my people their wicked acts, and to the house of Jacob their sins.

2 For they also seek me, from day to day, and they are willing to know my ways, like a nation which has done justice and has not abandoned the judgment of their God. They petition me for judgments of justice. They are willing to draw near to God.

3 "Why have we fasted, and you have not taken notice? Why have we humbled our souls, and you have not acknowledged it?" Behold, in the day of your fasting, your own will is found, and you petition for payment from all your debtors.

4 Behold, you fast with strife and contention, and you strike with the fist impiously. Do not choose to fast as you have done even to this day. Then your outcry will be heard on high.

5 Is this a fast such as I have chosen: for a man to afflict his soul for a day, to contort his head in a circle, and to spread sackcloth and ashes? Should you call this a fast and a day acceptable to the Lord?

6 Is not this, instead, the kind of fast that I have chosen? Release the constraints of impiety; relieve the burdens that oppress; freely forgive those who are broken; and break apart every burden.

7 Break your bread with the hungry, and lead the destitute and the homeless into your house. When you see someone naked, cover him, and do not despise your own flesh.

8 Then your light will break forth like the morning, and your health will improve quickly, and your justice will go before your face, and the glory of the Lord will gather you up.

9 Then you will call, and the Lord will heed; you will cry out, and he will say, "Here I am," if you take away the chains from your midst, and cease to point your finger and to speak what is not beneficial.

10 When you pour out your life for the hungry, and you satisfy the afflicted soul, then your light will rise up in darkness, and your darkness will be like the midday.

11 And the Lord will give you rest continually, and he will fill your soul with splendor, and he will free your bones, and you will be like a watered garden and like a fountain of water whose waters will not fail.

12 And places that have been desolate for ages will be built up by you. You will raise a foundation for generation after generation. And you will be called the repairer of hedges, who turns the roadways into quiet places.

13 If you restrain your foot on the Sabbath, from doing your own will on my holy day, and if you call the Sabbath delightful, and the Holy of the Lord glorious, and if you glorify him, while you do not act according to your own ways, and your own will is not found, not even to speak a word,

14 then you will find delight in the Lord, and I will take you up, above the heights of the earth, and I will nourish you with the inheritance of Jacob, your father. For the mouth of the Lord has spoken.

Isaiah 59

1 Behold, the hand of the Lord has not been shortened, so that it cannot save, and his ear has not been blocked, so that it cannot hear.

2 But your iniquities have made a division between you and your God, and your sins have concealed his face from you, so that he would not hear.

3 For your hands have been polluted by blood, and your fingers by iniquity. Your lips have spoken lies, and your tongue utters iniquity.

4 There is no one who calls for justice, and there is no one who judges truly. For they trust in nothing, and they speak emptiness. They have conceived hardship, and they have given birth to iniquity.

5 They have ruptured the eggs of asps, and they have woven the webs of spiders. Whoever will eat of their eggs will die. For what has been incubated will hatch into a king snake.

6 Their weavings will not be for clothing, nor will they cover themselves with their handiwork. Their works are useless things, and the work of iniquity is in their hands.

7 Their feet run to evil, and they rush to shed innocent blood. Their thoughts are useless thoughts; devastation and destruction are in their ways.

8 They have not known the way of peace, and there is no judgment in their steps. Their paths have become crooked for them. Anyone who treads in them knows no peace.

9 Because of this, judgment is far from us, and justice will not take hold of us. We waited for light, and behold, darkness; we waited for brightness, and we walked in darkness.

10 We groped for the wall, like one who is blind, and we felt our way, like one without eyes. We stumbled at midday, as if in darkness; and in darkness, as if in death.

11 We will all roar like bears, and we will sigh like despondent doves. We hoped for judgment, and there is none; for salvation, and it is far from us.

12 For our iniquities have been multiplied in your sight, and our sins have answered us. For our wickedness is with us, and we have acknowledged our iniquities:

13 sinning and lying against the Lord. And we have turned away, not so as to go after our God, and so that we were speaking calumny and transgression. We have conceived, and spoken from the heart, words of falsehood.

14 And judgment has been turned backwards, and justice has stood far away. For truth has fallen down in the street, and fairness was not able to enter.

15 And the truth has gone into oblivion. And he who withdraws from evil endures plunder. And the Lord saw this, and it seemed evil in his eyes. For there is no judgment.

16 And he saw that there was no good man. And he was astonished that there was no one to meet him. And his own arm brought salvation to him, and his own justice strengthened him.

17 He clothed himself with justice as with a breastplate, and with a helmet of salvation upon his head. He put on the vestments of vengeance, and he was covered with zeal as with a cloak.

18 This was for vindication, as a repayment of indignation to his adversaries, and as a sudden reversal for his enemies. He will repay the islands in their turn.

19 And those from the west will fear the name of the Lord, and those from the rising of the sun will fear his glory, when he arrives like a violent river, which the Spirit of the Lord urges on.

20 And the Redeemer will arrive in Zion, and to those who return from the iniquity within Jacob, says the Lord.

21 This is my pact with them, says the Lord. My Spirit is within you, and my words, which I have put in your mouth, will not withdraw from your mouth, nor from the mouth of your offspring, nor from the mouth of your offspring's offspring, says the Lord, from this moment, and even forever.

Isaiah 60

1 Rise up to be illuminated, O Jerusalem! For your light has arrived, and the glory of the Lord has risen over you.

2 For behold, darkness will cover the earth, and thick darkness will cover the peoples. Then the Lord will rise above you, and his glory will be seen in you.

3 And the nations will walk in your light, and the kings will walk by the splendor of your rising.

4 Lift up your eyes all around and see! All these have been gathered together; they have arrived before you. Your sons will arrive from far away, and your daughters will rise up from your side.

5 Then you will see, and you will overflow, and your heart will be amazed and expanded. When the multitude of the sea will have been converted to you, the strength of the nations will approach you.

6 A multitude of camels will inundate you: the dromedaries from Midian and Ephah. All those from Sheba will arrive, carrying gold and frankincense, and announcing praise to the Lord.

7 All the flocks of Kedar will be gathered together before you; the rams of Nebaioth will minister to you. They will be offered upon my pleasing altar, and I will glorify the house of my majesty.

8 Who are these ones, who fly like the clouds and like doves to their windows?

9 For the islands await me, and the ships of the sea in the beginning, so that I may lead your sons from far away, their silver and their gold with them, to the name of the Lord your God and to the Holy One of Israel. For he has glorified you.

10 And the sons of sojourners will build up your walls, and their kings will minister to you. For in my wrath, I have struck you. And in my reconciliation, I have taken pity on you.

11 And your gates will be open continually. They will not be closed day or night, so that the strength of the nations may be brought before you, and their kings may be lead in.

12 For the nation and the kingdom that will not serve you will perish. And the Gentiles will be devastated by solitude.

13 The glory of Lebanon will arrive before you, the fir tree and the box tree and the pine tree together, to adorn the place of my sanctification. And I will glorify the place of my feet.

14 And the sons of those who humiliate you will approach and will bow down before you. And all who detract you will reverence the path of your feet. And they will call you the City of the Lord, the Zion of the Holy One of Israel.

15 For though you were forsaken, and held in hatred, and there was no one who would pass near you, I will establish you as an everlasting glory, as a gladness from generation to generation.

16 And you will drink the milk of the Gentiles, and you will be nursed at the breasts of kings, and you will know that I am the Lord, your Saviour and your Redeemer, the Strong One of Jacob.

17 In exchange for brass, I will bring gold; and in exchange for iron, I will bring silver; and for wood, brass; and for stones, iron. And I will make your visitation into peace, and your leaders into justice.

18 Iniquity will no longer be heard in your land, nor devastation and destruction in your borders. And salvation will occupy your walls, and praise will occupy your gates.

19 The sun will no longer be your light by day, nor will the brightness of the moon illuminate you. Instead, the Lord will be an everlasting light for you, and your God will be your glory.

20 Your sun will no longer set, and your moon will not diminish. For the Lord will be an everlasting light for you, and the days of your mourning will be completed.

21 And your people will all be just. They will inherit the earth in perpetuity, the seedling of my planting, the work of my hand, so as to glorify me.

22 The least will become a thousand, and a little one will become a very strong nation. I, the Lord, will accomplish this, suddenly, in its time.

Isaiah 61

1 The Spirit of the Lord is upon me, for the Lord has anointed me. He has sent me to bring good news to the meek, so as to heal the contrite of heart, to preach leniency to captives and release to the confined,

2 and so to proclaim the acceptable year of the Lord and the day of vindication of our God: to console all who are mourning,

3 to take up the mourners of Zion and to give them a crown in place of ashes, an oil of joy in place of mourning, a cloak of praise in place of a spirit of grief. And there, they shall be called the strong ones of justice, the planting of the Lord, unto glorification.

4 And they will rebuild the deserted places of past ages, and they will raise up the ruins of antiquity, and they will repair the desolate cities, which had been dissipated for generation after generation.

5 And foreigners will stand up and will pasture your flocks. And the sons of sojourners will be your farmers and the workers of your vineyards.

6 But you yourselves will be called the priests of the Lord. It will be said to you, "You are the ministers of our God." You will eat from the strength of the Gentiles, and you will pride yourself on their glory.

7 Instead of your double confusion and shame, they will praise their portion. Because of this, they will possess double in their land. Everlasting joy will be for them.

8 For I am the Lord, who loves judgment and who holds hatred for robbery within a burnt offering. And I will turn their work into truth, and I will forge a perpetual covenant with them.

9 And they will know their offspring among the nations, and their progeny in the midst of the peoples. All who see them will recognize them: that these are the offspring whom the Lord has blessed.

10 I will rejoice greatly in the Lord, and my soul will exult in my God. For he has clothed me with the vestments of salvation, and he has wrapped me in the clothing of justice, like a groom arrayed with a crown, and like a bride adorned with her jewels.

11 For as the earth brings forth its seedlings and the garden produces its seeds, so will the Lord God bring forth justice and praise in the sight of all the nations.

Isaiah 62

1 For the sake of Zion, I will not be silent, and for the sake of Jerusalem, I will not rest, until her Just One advances in splendor, and her Savior is kindled like a lamp.

2 And the Gentiles will see your Just One, and all the kings will see your Renown One. And you shall be called by a new name, which the mouth of the Lord will choose.

3 And you shall be a crown of glory in the hand of the Lord, and a royal diadem in the hand of your God.

4 You will no longer called Forsaken. And your land will no longer be called Desolate. Instead, you shall be called My Will within it, and your land shall be called Inhabited. For the Lord has been well pleased with you, and your land will be inhabited.

5 For the young man will live with the virgin, and your children will live with you. And the groom will rejoice over the bride, and your God will rejoice over you.

6 Upon your walls, O Jerusalem, I have stationed watchmen all day and all night unceasingly; they will not be silent. You who are mindful of the Lord, you should not be silent,

7 and you should not grant silence to him, until he makes firm and establishes Jerusalem as a praise upon the earth.

8 The Lord has sworn with his right hand and with the arm of his strength: "Certainly, I will no longer permit your grain to be the food of your enemies. And the sons of foreigners will not drink your wine, for which you have labored."

9 For those who gather it will eat it, and they will praise the Lord. And those who bring it together will drink it in my holy courts.

10 Pass through, pass through the gates! Prepare a way for the people! Make the road level, remove the stones, and lift up a sign for the people!

11 Behold, the Lord has caused it to be heard to the ends of the earth. Tell the daughter of Zion: "Behold, your Saviour approaches! Behold, his reward is with him, and his work before him."

12 And they will call them: The holy people, the redeemed of the Lord. Then you will be called: A city sought, and not forsaken.

Isaiah 63

1 Who is this, who arrives from Edom with dyed garments from Bozrah? This is the Handsome One in his robe, advancing by the fullness of his strength. It is I, the Speaker of Justice, and I am the Fighter for Salvation.

2 So then, why is your garment red, and why are your vestments like the ones of those who tread the winepress?

3 I have trod the winepress alone. And among the nations, there is no man beside me. I have trampled on them in my fury, and I have tread them down in my wrath. And so, their blood has been sprinkled on my vestments, and I have stained all my garments.

4 For the day of vengeance is in my heart. The year of my redemption has arrived.

5 I gazed around, and there was no one to assist. I sought, and there was no one who would help. And so, my own arm has saved for me, and my own wrath itself has assisted me.

6 And I have trampled the peoples in my fury, and I have inebriated them with my indignation, and I have torn down their strength to the ground.

7 I will remember the compassion of the Lord, the praise of the Lord over all that the Lord has bestowed on us, and over the multitude of his good things for the house of Israel, which he has granted to them according to his leniency, and according to the multitude of his mercies.

8 And he said: "Yet truly, these are my people, sons who have not been disowned." And he became their Savior.

9 Throughout all their tribulation, he was not troubled, for the Angel of his presence saved them. With his love, and by his leniency, he has redeemed them, and he has carried them and lifted them up, throughout all the days of the ages.

10 But they themselves provoked to wrath and afflicted his Holy Spirit, and he was turned to be for them like an enemy, and he himself went to war against them.

11 And he remembered the days of ancient times, the days of Moses and his people. Where is he who led them out of the sea, with the shepherds of his flock? Where is he who placed his Holy Spirit in their midst?

12 He led Moses by the right hand, with the arm of his majesty. He split the waters before them, in order to make an everlasting name for himself.

13 He led them through the abyss, like a horse which does not stumble, in the desert.

14 Like an animal who descends to an open field, the Spirit of the Lord was their guide. Thus did you lead your people, in order to make a glorious name for yourself.

15 Gaze down from heaven, and behold from your holy habitation and from your glory. Where is your zeal, and your strength, the fullness of your heart and of your compassion? They have held themselves back from me.

16 For you are our Father, and Abraham has not known us, and Israel has been ignorant of us. You are our Father, O Lord our Redeemer. Your name is beyond all ages.

17 Why have you allowed us to stray from your ways, O Lord? Why have you hardened our heart, so that we do not fear you? Return, for the sake of your servants, the tribes of your inheritance.

18 They have possessed your holy people as if it were nothing. Our enemies have trampled your sanctuary.

19 We have become as we were in the beginning, when you did not rule over us, and when we were not called by your name.

Isaiah 64

1 I wish that you would rend the heavens, and then descend! The mountains would flow away before your face.

2 They would melt, as if thoroughly burned by fire. The waters would burn with fire, so that your name might be made known to your enemies, so that the nations would be stirred up before your face.

3 When you will perform miracles, we will not be able to withstand them. You descended, and the mountains flowed away before your presence.

4 From ages past, they have not heard it, and they have not perceived it with the ears. Apart from you, O God, the eye has not seen what you have prepared for those who await you.

5 You have met with those who rejoice in doing justice. By your ways, they will remember you. Behold, you have been angry, for we have sinned. In this, we have continued, but we will be saved.

6 And we have all become like the unclean. And all our justices are like a rag of menstruation. And we have all fallen away, like a leaf. And our iniquities have carried us away, like the wind.

7 There is no one who calls upon your name, who rises up and holds fast to you. You have concealed your face from us, and you have crushed us with the hand of our own iniquity.

8 And now, O Lord, you are our Father, yet truly, we are clay. And you are our Maker, and we are all the works of your hands.

9 Do not be so angry, O Lord, and no longer call to mind our iniquity. Behold, consider that we are all your people.

10 The city of your sanctuary has become a desert. Zion has become a desert. Jerusalem is desolate.

11 The house of our sanctification and of our glory, where our fathers praised you, has been completely consumed by fire, and all our admirable things have been turned into ruins.

12 Should you restrain yourself, O Lord, concerning these things? Should you remain silent, and afflict us vehemently?

Isaiah 65

1 Those who before were not asking for me have sought me. Those who have not sought me have found me. I said, "Behold, it is I! Behold, it is I!" to a nation which was not invoking my name.

2 I have extended my hands all day long to an unbelieving people, who advance along a way that is not good, following their own thoughts,

3 to a people who provoke me to anger before my face continually, who immolate in the gardens, and who sacrifice upon the bricks.

4 They live in sepulchers, and they sleep in the shrines of idols. They eat the flesh of swine, and a profane elixir is in their vessels.

5 They say: "Depart from me! Do not approach me, for you are unclean!" Such as these will be the smoke in my fury, a fire burning all day long.

6 Behold, it has been written in my sight; I will not be silent. Instead, I will render retribution into their sinews.

7 Your iniquities are joined with the iniquities of your fathers, says the Lord. For they have sacrificed upon the mountains, and they have offended me upon the hills. And so, I will measure back to them, from their first work, into their sinews.

8 Thus says the Lord: In the same way as it is said about a grain found in a cluster, "Do not destroy it, because it is a blessing," so will I act for the sake of my servants, so that I may not destroy the whole.

9 And I will lead forth an offspring from Jacob, and a possessor of my mountains from Judah. And my elect shall inherit it, and my servants shall live there.

10 And the open plains will become sheepfolds for the flocks, and the valley of Achor will become a domicile for the herds, for my people who have sought me.

11 And you who have forsaken the Lord, who have forgotten my holy mountain, who set a table for Fortune, and who offer libations concerning her:

12 I will number you with the sword, and you will all fall by slaughter. For I called and you did not respond; I spoke, and you did not listen. And you did what is evil in my eyes; and what I did not will, you have chosen.

13 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: Behold, my servants will eat, and you will be hungry. Behold, my servants will drink, and you will be thirsty.

14 Behold, my servants will rejoice, and you will be confounded. Behold, my servants will give praise in exultation of heart, and you will cry out in sorrow of heart, and you will wail in contrition of spirit.

15 And you will leave behind your name to my elect as a curse. And the Lord God will put you to death, and he will call his servants by another name.

16 By that name, whoever is blessed on earth, will be blessed in God. Amen! And whoever swears on earth, will swear by God. Amen! For the past anguishes have been delivered into oblivion, and they have been hidden from my eyes.

17 For behold, I create the new heavens and the new earth. And the former things will not be in memory and will not enter into the heart.

18 But you will be glad and exult, even forever, in these things that I create. For behold, I create Jerusalem as an exultation, and its people as a joy.

19 And I will exult in Jerusalem, and I will rejoice in my people. And neither a voice of weeping, nor a voice of outcry, will be heard in her anymore.

20 There will no longer be an infant of only a few days there, nor an elder who does not complete his days. For a mere child dies at a hundred years of age, and a sinner of a hundred years will be accursed.

21 And they will build houses, and will inhabit them. And they will plant vineyards, and will eat their fruits.

22 They will not build, so that another may inhabit. They will not plant, so that another may eat. For according to the days of a tree, so will be the days of my people. And the works of their hands will be long-standing.

23 My elect will not labor in vain, and they will not bring forth in disorder. For they are the offspring of the blessed of the Lord, and their posterity are with them.

24 And this shall be: before they call out, I will perceive; while they are still speaking, I will hear.

25 The wolf and the lamb will pasture together. The lion and the ox will eat hay. And dust will be the food of the serpent. They will not harm, and they will not kill, on all my holy mountain, says the Lord.

Isaiah 66

1 Thus says the Lord: Heaven is my throne, and the earth is my footstool. What is this house that you would build for me? And what is this place of my rest?

2 My hand has made all these things, and all these things have been made, says the Lord. But upon whom will I look with favor, except upon a poor little one, who is contrite in spirit, and who trembles at my words?

3 Whoever immolates an ox, it is as if he slaughters a man. Whoever sacrifices a sheep, it is as if he is smashing the head of a dog. Whoever offers an oblation, it is as if he is offering swine's blood. Whoever makes remembrance with incense, it is as if he is blessing an idol. All these things, they have chosen according to their own ways, and their soul has taken delight in their own abominations.

4 Therefore, I also will choose their illusions, and I will lead over them the things that they feared. For I called, and there was no one who would respond. I have spoken, and they have not listened. And they have done evil in my eyes; and what I did not will, they have chosen.

5 Listen to the word of the Lord, you who tremble at his word. Your brothers, who hate you and who cast you out because of my name, have said: "Let the Lord be glorified, and we will see by your rejoicing." But they themselves will be confounded.

6 A voice of the people from the city! A voice from the temple! The voice of the Lord repaying retribution to his enemies!

7 Before she was in labor, she gave birth. Before her time arrived for delivery, she gave birth to a male child.

8 Who has ever heard of such a thing? And who has seen anything like this? Will the earth give birth in one day? Or will a nation be born all at once? For Zion has been in labor, and she has given birth to her sons.

9 Will I, who causes others to give birth, not also give birth myself, says the Lord? Will I, who bestows generation upon others, be barren myself, says the Lord your God?

10 Rejoice with Jerusalem, and exult in her, all you who love her! Rejoice greatly with her, all you who mourn over her!

11 So may you nurse and be filled, from the breasts of her consolations. So may you receive milk and overflow with delights, from every portion of her glory.

12 For thus says the Lord: Behold, I will turn a river of peace toward her, with an inundating torrent: the glory of the Gentiles, from which you will nurse. You will be carried at the breasts, and they will caress you upon the knees.

13 In the manner of one whom a mother caresses, so will I console you. And you will be consoled in Jerusalem.

14 You will see, and your heart will be glad, and your bones will flourish like a plant, and the hand of the Lord will be known to his servants, and he will be angry with his enemies.

15 For behold, the Lord will arrive with fire, and his four-horse chariots will be like a whirlwind: to render his wrath with indignation, and his rebuke with flames of fire.

16 For the Lord will divide with fire, and with his sword among all flesh, and those slain by the Lord will be many.

17 Those who were sanctified, who thought themselves to be clean in the gardens behind the inner gate, who were eating swine's flesh, and the abomination, and the mouse: they will be consumed all at once, says the Lord.

18 But I know their works and their thoughts. I am arriving, so that I may gather them together with all nations and languages. And they will approach, and they will see my glory.

19 And I will set a sign among them. And I will send some of those who will have been saved to the Gentiles in the sea, to Africa, and to those who draw the bow in Lydia, to Italy and Greece, to islands far away, to those who have not heard of me, and to those who have not seen my glory. And they will announce my glory to the Gentiles.

20 And they will lead all of your brothers from all of the Gentiles as a gift to the Lord, on horses, and in four-horse chariots, and on stretchers, and on mules, and in coaches, to my holy mountain Jerusalem, says the Lord, in the same manner that the sons of Israel would carry an offering in a pure vessel into the house of the Lord.

21 And I will take from them to be priests and Levites, says the Lord.

22 For in like manner as the new heavens and the new earth, which I will cause to stand before me, says the Lord, so will your offspring and your name stand.

23 And there will be month after month, and Sabbath after Sabbath. And all flesh will approach, so as to adore before my face, says the Lord.

24 And they will go out, and they will view the carcasses of the men who have transgressed against me. Their worm will not die, and their fire will not be extinguished. And they will be a sight to all flesh even unto revulsion.

Jeremiah 1

1 The words of Jeremiah, the son of Hilkiah of the priests who were in Anathoth in the land of Benjamin.

2 The word of the Lord, which came to him in the days of Josiah, the son of Amon, king of Judah, in the thirteenth year of his reign,

3 and which came to him in the days of Jehoiakim, the son of Josiah, king of Judah, even until the completion of the eleventh year of Zedekiah, the son of Josiah, king of Judah, even until the transmigration of Jerusalem in the fifth month.

4 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

5 "Before I formed you in the womb, I knew you. And before you went forth from the womb, I sanctified you. And I made you a prophet to the nations."

6 And I said: "Alas, alas, alas, Lord God! Behold, I do not know how to speak, for I am a boy."

7 And the Lord said to me: "Do not choose to say, 'I am a boy.' For you shall go forth to everyone to whom I will send you. And you shall speak all that I will command you.

8 You should not be afraid before their face. For I am with you, so that I may deliver you," says the Lord.

9 And the Lord put forth his hand, and he touched my mouth. And the Lord said to me: "Behold, I have placed my words in your mouth.

10 Behold, today I have appointed you over nations and over kingdoms, so that you may root up, and pull down, and destroy, and scatter, and so that you may build and plant."

11 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying, "What do you see, Jeremiah?" And I said, "I see a staff, keeping watch."

12 And the Lord said to me: "You have seen well. For I will keep watch over my word, so that I may accomplish it."

13 And the word of the Lord came to me a second time, saying, "What do you see?" And I said, "I see a cooking pot upon a fire, and its face is before the face of the north."

14 And the Lord said to me: "From the north, an evil will spread over all the inhabitants of the earth.

15 For behold, I will call together all the close associates of the kingdoms of the north, says the Lord. And they will arrive, and each one of them will place his throne at the entrance to the gates of Jerusalem, and over all its surrounding walls, and over all the cities of Judah.

16 And I will speak my judgments with them, concerning all the wickedness of those who have forsaken me, and who have offered libations to strange gods, and who have adored the work of their own hands.

17 Therefore, you should gird your waist, and rise up, and speak to them everything that I instruct you. You should not have dread before their face. For I will cause you to be unafraid of their countenance.

18 For certainly, this day, I have made you like a fortified city, and an iron pillar, and a brass wall, over all the land, to the kings of Judah, to its leaders, and to the priests, and to the people of the land.

19 And they will make war against you, but they will not prevail. For I am with you, says the Lord, so that I may free you."

Jeremiah 2

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Go, and cry out to the ears of Jerusalem, saying: Thus says the Lord: I have remembered you, taking pity on your youth and on the charity of your betrothal, when you followed me into the desert, into a land which is not sown.

3 Israel is holy to the Lord, the first of his fruits. All those who devour him commit an offense. Evils will overwhelm them, says the Lord."

4 Listen to the word of the Lord, O house of Jacob, and all you families of the house of Israel.

5 Thus says the Lord: "What iniquity have your fathers found in me, that they would draw far away from me, and would walk after emptiness, and would become empty?

6 And they have not said: 'Where is the Lord, who caused us to ascend from the land of Egypt; who led us through the desert, through an uninhabited and impassable land, through a land of drought and of the image of death, through a land in which no one walked and in which no man lived?'

7 And I led you into the land of Carmel, so that you would eat from its fruit and from its excellence. And having entered it, you defiled my land, and you turned my inheritance into an abomination.

8 The priests have not sad: 'Where is the Lord?' And those who held the law did not know me. And the pastors betrayed me. And the prophets prophesied in Baal and followed idols.

9 Because of this, I will still contend in judgment against you, says the Lord, and I will dispute with your sons.

10 Cross over to the isles of Kittim, and gaze. And send to Kedar, and consider diligently. And see if anything like this has ever been done.

11 See if a nation has ever changed their gods, though certainly those are not gods. Yet truly, my people have exchanged their glory for an idol.

12 Be astonished at this, O heavens, and be utterly desolate, O gates of heaven, says the Lord.

13 For my people have done two evils. They have forsaken me, the Fountain of living water, and they have dug for themselves cisterns, broken cisterns that are unable to hold water.

14 Is Israel a servant, or one born into slavery? Then why has he become a prey?

15 The lions have roared over him, and they have uttered their voice. They have set his land in solitude; his cities have been burned up, and there is no one who lives in them.

16 Likewise, the sons of Memphis and of Tahpanhes have defiled you, even to the top of the head.

17 Has this not been done to you because you abandoned the Lord your God, in that time when he was leading you by the way?

18 And now what do you want from the way of Egypt, but to drink their turbid water? And what do you want from the way of the Assyrians, but to drink the water of their river?

19 Your own malice will reprove you, and your own apostasy will rebuke you! But know and perceive this: it is an evil and bitter thing for you to forsake the Lord your God, and to be without my fear within you, says the Lord, the God of hosts.

20 From ancient times, you have broken my yoke; you have torn apart my bonds, and you have said, 'I will not serve.' For on every high hill, and under every leafy tree, you have been debased, O harlot.

21 Yet I planted you as an elect vineyard, with only true seed. Then how have you been turned away from me, toward that which is depraved, O strange vineyard?

22 Even if you wash yourself with soap, and increase your use of herbal soaps, you are still stained by your iniquity in my sight, says the Lord God.

23 How can you say: 'I have not been polluted. I have not walked after Baal?' Consider your ways in the steep valley. Acknowledge what you have done, so that you may be like a swift runner, following his course.

24 A wild donkey accustomed to solitude, out of the desire in his soul, caught the scent of his lover. Now nothing will turn him away from her. All those who seek her will not cease. But they will find her in her menstruation.

25 You should keep your foot from being naked, and your throat from being thirsty. But you have said: 'I have lost hope. I will not do it. For certainly, I have loved strangers, and I will walk after them.'

26 In the same way that a thief is confounded when he has been apprehended, so the house of Israel has been confounded, they and their kings, their leaders and priests and prophets.

27 For they say to a piece of wood, 'You are my father,' and to a stone, 'You have conceived me.' They have turned their back to me, and not their face. But in the time of their affliction, they will say: 'Rise up and deliver us.'

28 Where are your gods that you made for yourselves? Let them rise up and deliver you in the time of your affliction. For certainly, your gods were like the number of your cities, O Judah.

29 Why do you want to contend against me in judgment? You have all forsaken me, says the Lord.

30 I have struck your children to no effect; they have not accepted discipline. Your own sword has devoured your prophets. Your generation is like a raging lion.

31 Consider the word of the Lord. Have I become like a wilderness to Israel, or like a land late to bear fruit? Then why have my people said, 'We are withdrawing; we will no longer approach you'?

32 Can a virgin forget her ornament, or a bride the covering across her breast? Yet truly, my people have forgotten me, for innumerable days.

33 Why are you striving to claim that your way is good, as if to seek my love, when all the while you are also displaying your malice by your own way,

34 and in your armpits there is found the blood of poor and innocent souls? I have found them, not in ditches, but everywhere that I mentioned previously.

35 And you have said: 'I am innocent and without sin. And because of this, let your fury be turned away from me.' Behold, I will contend with you in judgment, because you have said: 'I have not sinned.'

36 How exceedingly vile you have become, repeating your ways again and again! And so, you will be ashamed of Egypt, just as you were ashamed of Assur.

37 For you will also depart from that place, and your hand will be upon your head. For the Lord has crushed your confidence, and you will have nothing prosperous by it."

Jeremiah 3

1 "It is commonly said: 'If a man has divorced his wife, and she departs from him, she will marry another man.' So why would he return to her again? Is not that woman polluted and defiled? But you have fornicated yourself with many lovers. Even so, return to me, says the Lord, and I will accept you.

2 Lift your eyes straight up, and see where you did not debase yourself. You were sitting in the roadways, waiting for them, like a robber in the wilderness. And you have polluted the land by your fornications and by your wickedness.

3 For this reason, the rain showers were withheld, and there were no late season rains. You made your face like that of a promiscuous woman; you were not willing to blush.

4 Therefore, at least from this moment on, call out to me: 'You are my father, the guide of my virginity.'

5 Why should you be angry unceasingly? And will you continue in this to the end? Behold, you have spoken and done evil, for you were able to do so."

6 And, in the days of king Josiah, the Lord said to me: "Have you not seen what the apostate Israel has done? She has brought herself up to every lofty mountain, and she has lain down under every leafy tree, and she has committed fornication there.

7 And when she had done all these things, I said: 'Return to me.' But she did not return. And her deceitful sister Judah saw this:

8 that because the apostate Israel had committed adultery, I had dismissed her and had given her a bill of divorce. Yet her deceitful sister Judah was not afraid. But she, too, went and committed fornication herself.

9 And by the act of her fornication, she defiled the land. For she committed adultery with that which is stone and wood.

10 And after all these things, her deceitful sister Judah has not returned to me with her whole heart, but with lies, says the Lord."

11 And the Lord said to me: "The apostate Israel has justified her own soul by comparing herself to the deceitful Judah.

12 Go, and proclaim these words toward the north, and you shall say: Return, O apostate Israel, says the Lord. For I will not avert my face from you. For I am holy, says the Lord, and I will not be angry forever.

13 So then, truly acknowledge your iniquity, that you have betrayed the Lord your God, and that you have spread your ways to strangers, under every leafy tree, and that you have not listened to my voice, says the Lord.

14 Convert, O rebellious sons, says the Lord. For I am your leader. And so, I will take you, one from a city, and two from a family, and I will lead you into Zion.

15 And I will give you pastors according to my own heart. And they will feed you with knowledge and doctrine.

16 And when you have been multiplied and increased in the land in those days, says the Lord, they will no longer say: 'The Ark of the covenant of the Lord!' And it will not enter into the heart, and they will not call it to mind. It will neither be visited, nor made use of, any longer.

17 In that time, Jerusalem will be called: 'The Throne of the Lord.' And all the nations will be gathered to it, in the name of the Lord, in Jerusalem. And they will not walk after the depravity of their own most wicked heart.

18 In those days, the house of Judah will go to the house of Israel, and they will come from the land of the north, at the same time, to the land that I gave to your fathers.

19 But I said: How shall I place you among the sons, and distribute to you a desirable land, the preeminent inheritance of the host of the Gentiles? And I said: You will call me Father, and you will not cease to walk after me.

20 But, in the same way that a woman spurns her lover, so also has the house of Israel spurned me, says the Lord."

21 A voice has been heard in the highways, the weeping and wailing of the sons of Israel. For they have made their own ways sinful; they have forgotten the Lord their God.

22 "Convert, O rebellious sons! And I will heal your rebelliousness." "Behold, we are returning to you. For you are the Lord our God!

23 Truly, the hills were liars, with the multitude of the mountains. Truly, the salvation of Israel is in the Lord our God.

24 Confusion has devoured the labor of our fathers, from our youth, with their flocks and their herds, with their sons and their daughters.

25 We will sleep in our confusion, and our disgrace will cover us. For we have sinned against the Lord our God: we and our fathers, from our youth, even to this day. And we have not listened to the voice of the Lord our God."

Jeremiah 4

1 "O Israel, if you would return, says the Lord, then be converted to me. If you remove your offense from before my face, then you will not be shaken.

2 And you will swear, 'As the Lord lives,' in truth and in judgment and in justice." And the Gentiles will bless him, and they will praise him.

3 For thus says the Lord to the men of Judah and of Jerusalem: "Break new ground, and do not choose to sow upon thorns.

4 Be circumcised to the Lord, and take away the foreskins from your hearts, O men of Judah, O inhabitants of Jerusalem. Otherwise my indignation may burst forth and flare up like a fire. And then there will be no one who can extinguish it, because of the wickedness of your thoughts.

5 Declare it in Judah, and make it known in Jerusalem! Speak out and sound the trumpet in the land! Cry out strongly and say: 'Gather yourselves! And let us go forth to fortified cities!'

6 Lift up a standard in Zion. Be strengthened! Do not choose to stand still. For I am bringing an evil from the north, with great destruction.

7 The lion has ascended from his den, and the pillager of the nations has lifted himself up. He has gone forth from his place, so that he may set your land in desolation. Your cities will be laid waste, remaining without an inhabitant.

8 Concerning this, wrap yourselves in haircloth, mourn and wail: 'For the wrath of the fury of the Lord has not been turned away from us.'

9 And this shall be in that day, says the Lord: The heart of the king will perish, with the heart of the princes. And the priests will be stupefied, and the prophets will be in consternation."

10 And I said: "Alas, alas, alas, O Lord God! Could it be that you have deceived this people and Jerusalem, saying: 'Peace shall be yours,' while, behold, the sword reaches even to the soul?"

11 "In that time, it will be said to this people and to Jerusalem: 'A burning wind is in the ways that are in the desert, along the way of the daughter of my people, but not to winnow and not to cleanse.'

12 A full spirit from these places will come to me. And now I will speak my judgments over them.

13 Behold, he will ascend like a cloud, and his chariot will ascend like a tempest. His horses are swifter than eagles. 'Woe to us! For we are being devastated!'

14 Wash your heart from malice, O Jerusalem, so that you may be saved. How long will harmful thoughts abide in you?

15 For there is a voice, of someone announcing from Dan, and he is making known the idol from mount Ephraim.

16 Say to the nations: 'Behold, it has been heard in Jerusalem! Guardians are coming from a far away land, to utter their voice against the cities of Judah.'

17 They have been stationed over her, like the guardians of fields, all around. For she has provoked me to wrath, says the Lord.

18 Your ways and your thoughts have brought these things upon you. This is your own wickedness. And it is bitter, because it has touched your heart.

19 I am afflicted in my heart, in my heart. The senses of my heart have been stirred up within me. I will not remain silent. For my soul has heard the voice of the trumpet, the clamor of the battle.

20 Destruction upon destruction has been called forth. And the entire earth has been devastated. My tabernacles have been destroyed suddenly, and my tents in an instant.

21 How long shall I watch those who are fleeing, and listen to the voice of the trumpet?

22 For my foolish people have not known me. They are foolish and mad sons. They are clever in doing evil, but they do not know how to do good.

23 I gazed upon the earth, and behold, it was empty and brought to nothing. And I gazed upon the heavens, but there was no light in them.

24 I watched the mountains, and behold, they trembled, and all the hills were shaken.

25 I looked, and there was no man. And all the flying things of the air had gone away.

26 I gazed, and behold, Carmel was a desert, and all its cities were destroyed before the face of the Lord, and before the face of the wrath of his fury."

27 For thus says the Lord: "All the earth will be desolate, but I will not yet bring about its consummation.

28 The earth will mourn, and the heavens will lament from above. For I have spoken, I have decided, and I have not regretted. Neither will I be turned away from it.

29 Before the voice of the horsemen and of those who send forth arrows, the entire city has fled. They have entered steep places, and they have ascended the cliffs. All of the cities have been abandoned, and no man lives within them.

30 So then, when you have been devastated, what will you do? Though you will clothe yourself with scarlet, though you will adorn yourself with a gold necklace and tint your eyes with cosmetics, you will be dressing yourself up in vain. Your lovers have spurned you; they will be seeking your life.

31 For I have heard a voice, like that of a woman giving birth, during the difficulties of labor. It is the voice of the daughter of Zion, dying, extending her hands: 'Woe to me! For my soul is failing because of those who have been slain!' "

Jeremiah 5

1 "Travel the streets of Jerusalem; and gaze, and consider, and seek, in its wide streets. If you can find a man exercising judgment and seeking faith, then I will be forgiving to them.

2 For even though they say, 'As the Lord lives,' in this, too, they swear falsely."

3 O Lord, your eyes look with favor upon faith. You have struck them, and they have not grieved. You have bruised them, and they have refused to accept discipline. They have hardened their faces more than rock, and they are not willing to return.

4 But I said: Perhaps these are the poor and the senseless, who are ignorant of the way of the Lord, of the judgment of their God.

5 Therefore, I will go to great men, and I will speak with them. For they have known the way of the Lord, the judgment of their God. And behold, these ones have broken the yoke all the more; they have torn apart the bonds.

6 For this reason, a lion from the forest has struck them down, a wolf toward evening has laid waste to them, a leopard lies in wait over their cities. All who go out from there will be taken. For their transgressions have been multiplied; their rebellions have been strengthened.

7 "Over which things am I able to be merciful to you? Your sons have forsaken me, and they swear by those who are not gods. I gave them everything, and they committed adultery, and they indulged themselves in the house of the harlot.

8 They have become like wild horses in heat; each one was neighing after his neighbor's wife.

9 Shall I not visit against these things, says the Lord? And shall my soul not take vengeance on a nation such as this?

10 Scale its walls and tear them down. But do not be willing to bring about its very end. Take away its plantings, for they are not the Lord's.

11 For the house of Israel and the house of Judah have greatly transgressed against me, says the Lord.

12 They have denied the Lord, and they have said, 'It is not him,' and, 'Evil will not overwhelm us. We will not see famine and the sword.'

13 The prophets have spoken into the wind, and there was no answer with them. Therefore, these things will happen to them."

14 Thus says the Lord, the God of hosts: "Since you have spoken this word, behold, I will make my words in your mouth like fire and this people like wood, and it will devour them.

15 Behold, O house of Israel, I will lead over you a far away nation, says the Lord, a robust nation, an ancient nation, a nation whose language you will not know, nor will you understand what they are saying.

16 Their quiver is like an open sepulcher. They are all strong.

17 And they will consume your grain fields and your bread. They will devour your sons and your daughters. They will consume your flocks and your herds. They will consume your vineyards and your figs. And with the sword, they will crush your fortified cities, in which you have placed your trust.

18 Yet truly, in those days, says the Lord, I will not bring the consummation over you.

19 And if they say, 'Why has the Lord our God done all these things to us?' You shall say to them: 'Just as you have abandoned me and have served a strange god in your own land, so will you serve strangers in a land not your own.'

20 Announce this to the house of Jacob, and make it known in Judah, saying:

21 Listen, O foolish people who have no heart! You have eyes, but you do not see, and ears, but you do not hear.

22 So then, will you not fear me, says the Lord. And will you not have sorrow before my face? I have placed the shore as a limit for the sea, as an everlasting precept that it will not transgress. And its waves will crash, but they will not prevail; and its waves will swell, but they will not go across.

23 But the heart of this people has become incredulous and provocative; they have turned away and departed.

24 And they have not said in their heart: 'Let us dread the Lord our God, who gives us the timely and the late rains, in their proper time, who guards the full measure of the yearly harvest for us.'

25 Your iniquities have turned these things away, and your sins have held back good things from you.

26 For the impious are found among my people; they lie in ambush like fowlers setting snares, for they set traps to catch men.

27 Just as a snare is full of birds, so are their houses full of deceit. As a result, they have become exalted and enriched.

28 They have grown stout and fat. And they have transgressed my words most wickedly. They have not judged the case of the widow; they have not given guidance to the case of the orphan; and they have not judged a judgment for the poor.

29 Shall I not visit against these things, says the Lord? Or shall my soul not take vengeance on a nation of this kind?

30 Astonishing and wondrous things have been done upon the earth.

31 The prophets have prophesied lies, and the priests have applauded with their hands, and my people have loved these things. So then, what shall be done at the very end?"

Jeremiah 6

1 "O sons of Benjamin, be strengthened in the midst of Jerusalem, and sound the trumpet in Tekoa, and lift up a banner over the house of Haccherem. For an evil has been seen from the north, with great destruction.

2 I have compared the daughter of Zion to a beautiful and delicate woman.

3 The pastors will come to her with their flocks. They have pitched their tents against her all around. Each one will feed those who are under his hand.

4 'Sanctify a war against her! Rise up together, and let us ascend at midday.' 'Woe to us! For the day has declined; for the shadows of the evening have grown longer.'

5 'Rise up, and let us ascend in the night, and let us destroy her houses.' "

6 For thus says the Lord of hosts: "Cut down her trees, and build a rampart around Jerusalem. This is the city of visitation! Every kind of false claim is in her midst.

7 Just as a cistern makes its water cold, so has she made her wickedness cold. Iniquity and devastation will be heard in her; sickness and wounds will be ever before me.

8 O Jerusalem, accept instruction, lest perhaps my soul may withdraw from you; lest perhaps I may set you in a desert, in an uninhabitable land."

9 Thus says the Lord of hosts: "They will gather the remnant of Israel, even as a single cluster of grapes is gathered from a vine. Direct your hand, as a grape-gatherer directs his hand to the basket.

10 To whom should I speak, and to whom should I testify, so as to be heard? Behold, their ears are uncircumcised, and so they are unable to hear. Behold, for them, the word of the Lord has become a disgrace. And so they will not accept it.

11 For this reason, I have been filled with the fury of the Lord. I labor to bear it. Let it be poured out upon the child outside, or upon a group of young men meeting together. For a man will be taken captive with a woman, an elder will be taken captive with one who is full of days.

12 And their houses will be given over to others, with both their lands and their wives. For I will extend my hand over the inhabitants of the earth, says the Lord.

13 Certainly, from the least of them even to the greatest, all of them practice greed. And from the prophet even to the priest, all of them act with deceit.

14 And they healed the destruction of the daughter of my people with disgrace, by saying: 'Peace, peace.' And there was no peace.

15 They were confounded, because they committed an abomination. Or rather, they were not confounded with shame, because they did not know how to blush. For this reason, they will fall among those who are being destroyed. In the time of their visitation, they will fall, says the Lord."

16 Thus says the Lord: "Stand above the ways, and see and ask, about the ancient paths, as to which is the good way, and then walk in it. And you will find refreshment for your souls. But they said: 'We will not walk.'

17 And I appointed watchers over you, saying: 'Listen for the sound of the trumpet.' And they said: 'We will not listen.'

18 For this reason, hear, O Gentiles, and know, O congregation, how much I will do to them.

19 Hear, O earth! Behold, I will lead evils over this people, as the fruits of their own thoughts. For they have not listened to my words, and they have cast aside my law.

20 For what reason are you bringing me frankincense from Sheba, and sweet smelling reeds from a far away land? Your holocausts are not acceptable, and your sacrifices are not pleasing to me."

21 Therefore, thus says the Lord: "Behold I will bring this people to utter ruin, and they will fall, with their fathers and sons; neighbor and relative will perish together."

22 Thus says the Lord: "Behold, a people is coming from the land of the north, and a great nation will rise up from the ends of the earth.

23 They will take hold of arrow and shield. They are cruel, and they will not take pity. Their voice will roar like the ocean. And they will climb upon horses, for they have been prepared like men for battle, against you, O daughter of Zion.

24 'We have heard of their fame. Our hands have become weakened. Tribulation has overtaken us, like the pains of a woman giving birth.'

25 Do not choose to go out into the fields, and you should not walk along the roadway. For the sword and the terror of the enemy is on every side.

26 Wrap yourself in haircloth, O daughter of my people. And sprinkle yourself with ashes. Make a mourning for yourself, as for an only son, a bitter lamentation: 'for the destroyer will overwhelm us suddenly.'

27 I have presented you as a strong tester among my people. And you will test and know their way.

28 All these leaders who are turning away and walking deceitfully, they are brass and iron; they have all been corrupted.

29 The bellows has failed; the lead has been consumed by fire; the molten metal was melted to no purpose. For their wickedness has not been consumed.

30 Call them: 'Rejected silver.' For the Lord has cast them aside."

Jeremiah 7

1 The word that came to Jeremiah from the Lord, saying:

2 "Stand at the gate to the house of the Lord, and preach this word there, and say: Listen to the word of the Lord, all you of Judah who enter through these gates to adore the Lord.

3 Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: Make your ways and your intentions good, and I will live with you in this place.

4 Do not choose to trust in lying words, saying: 'This is the temple of the Lord! The temple of the Lord! The temple of the Lord!'

5 For if you direct your ways and your intentions well, if you exercise judgment between a man and his neighbor,

6 if you do not act with deceit toward the new arrival, the orphan, and the widow, and if you do not pour out innocent blood in this place, and if you do not walk after strange gods, which is to your own harm,

7 then I will live with you in this place, in the land that I gave to your fathers from the beginning and even forever.

8 Behold, you trust in false words, which will not benefit you,

9 so as to steal, to murder, to commit adultery, to swear falsely, to offer libations to Baal, and to go after strange gods, which you do not know.

10 And you arrived and stood before me in this house, where my name is invoked, and you said: 'We have been freed because we carried out all these abominations.'

11 So then, has this house, where my name has been invoked, become a den of robbers in your eyes? It is I, I am, I have seen, says the Lord.

12 Go to my place in Shiloh, where my name has lived from the beginning, and see what I did to it because of the wickedness of my people Israel.

13 And now, because you have done all these works, says the Lord, and because I have spoken to you from your morning rising, and because I was speaking, but you were not listening, and because I have called you, but you have not responded:

14 I will do to this house, in which my name is invoked, and in which you have confidence, even to this place which I gave to you and to your fathers, just as I have done to Shiloh.

15 And I will cast you away from my face, just as I have cast away all your brothers, the entire offspring of Ephraim.

16 Therefore, you should not pray for this people, nor take up praise and supplication on their behalf. And you should not stand in opposition to me. For then I will not heed you.

17 Have you not seen what they are doing in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem?

18 The sons gather the wood, and the fathers kindle the fire, and the wives spread the grease, so as to make cakes to the queen of heaven and to offer libations to strange gods, and so as to provoke me to anger.

19 But are they provoking me to anger, says the Lord? Are they not provoking themselves, to the confusion of their own faces?"

20 Therefore, thus says the Lord God: "Behold, my fury and my indignation is kindled against this place, over men and over beasts, and over the trees of the countryside and over the fruits of the land, and it will burn and not be extinguished."

21 Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: "Add your holocausts to your sacrifices, and eat the flesh.

22 For concerning the matter of holocausts and sacrifices, I did not speak with your fathers, and I did not instruct them, in the day when I led them away from the land of Egypt.

23 But on this matter I did instruct them, saying: Listen to my voice, and I will be your God, and you will be my people. And walk in the entire way that I have commanded you, so that it may be well with you.

24 But they did not listen, nor did they incline their ear. Instead, they walked by their own will and in the depravity of their own wicked heart. And so, they went backward, and not forward,

25 from the day when their fathers went forth from the land of Egypt, even to this day. And I have sent all my servants, the prophets, to you, throughout the day, rising at first light and sending them.

26 But they have not listened to me, nor have they inclined their ear. Instead, they have stiffened their neck, and they have behaved worse than their fathers did.

27 And so, you will speak to them all these words, but they will not listen to you. And you will call to them, but they will not respond to you.

28 And you will say to them: This is the nation that has not listened to the voice of the Lord their God, nor accepted discipline. Faith has perished and been taken away from their mouth.

29 Cut off your hair, and cast it away. And take up a lamentation on high. For the Lord has cast aside and abandoned this generation of his fury.

30 For the sons of Judah have done evil in my eyes, says the Lord. They have stationed their abominations in the house where my name is invoked, so that they may defile it.

31 And they have built the exalted places of Topheth, which is in the Valley of the son of Hinnom, so that they may burn their sons and their daughters with fire, something I neither instructed, nor thought in my heart.

32 For this reason, behold, the days will arrive, says the Lord, when it will no longer be called Topheth, nor the Valley of the son of Hinnom, but instead the Valley of Slaughter. Yet they will bury in Topheth, because there will be no other place.

33 And the corpses of this people will be food for the birds of the air and for the wild beasts of the land, and there will be no one to drive them away.

34 And from the cities of Judah and the streets of Jerusalem, I will cause the cessation of the voice of gladness and the voice of rejoicing, the voice of the groom and the voice of the bride. For the land will be in utter desolation."

Jeremiah 8

1 "In that time, says the Lord, they will cast out the bones of the kings of Judah, and the bones of its leaders, and the bones of the priests, and the bones of the prophets, and the bones of those who were living in Jerusalem, from their graves.

2 And they will spread them out before the sun and the moon and the entire army of the heavens, which they have loved, and served, and followed, and which they have sought and adored. They will not be collected, and they will not be buried. They will be like manure upon the face of the earth.

3 And they will greatly prefer death to life: all those who will have been left from this wicked kindred, in all the forsaken places to which I will cast them out, says the Lord of hosts.

4 And you will say to them: Thus says the Lord: He who falls, will he not rise again? And he who has been turned away, will he not return?

5 Then why have this people in Jerusalem turned away with a contentious loathing? They have taken hold of what is false, and they are not willing to return.

6 I paid close attention and I listened carefully. No one is speaking what is good. There is no one who does penance for his sin, saying: 'What have I done?' They have all turned to their own course, like a horse rushing with fury into battle.

7 The hawk in the heavens has known her time. The turtledove, and the swallow, and the stork have kept the time of their arrival. But my people have not known the judgment of the Lord.

8 How can you say: 'We are wise, and the law of the Lord is with us?' Truly, the lying pen of the scribes has wrought falsehood.

9 The wise men have been confounded; they were terrified and captured. For they cast aside the word of the Lord, and there is no wisdom in them.

10 Because of this, I will give their wives to outsiders and their fields to others as an inheritance. For from the least, even to the greatest, they all pursue avarice; from the prophet, even to the priest, they all act with deceit.

11 And they healed the destruction of the daughter of my people with disgrace, by saying: 'Peace, peace,' though there was no peace.

12 They have been confounded because they committed abomination. Or rather, they have not been confounded with shame, for they do not know how to blush. For this reason, they will fall among the fallen. In the time of their visitation, they will fall, says the Lord.

13 When gathering, I will gather them together, says the Lord. There are no grapes on the vine, and there are no figs on the fig tree. The leaves have fallen. And I have given them the things that have passed away."

14 "Why are we sitting still? Assemble, and let us enter the fortified city, and let us remain silent there. For the Lord our God has brought us to silence, and he has given us the water of gall as a drink. For we have sinned against the Lord.

15 We expected peace, but there was nothing good. We expected a time of health, and behold, dread."

16 "From Dan, the snorting of his horses was heard; the entire land was shaken by the voice of the neighing of his fighters. And they arrived and devoured the land and its plenitude, the city and its inhabitants.

17 For behold, I will send among you serpents, king snakes, against which there is no charm, and they will bite you, says the Lord.

18 My sorrow is beyond sorrow; my heart mourns within me.

19 Behold, the voice of the daughter of my people from a far away land. Is the Lord not with Zion, and is her king not within her? Then why have they provoked me to wrath by their graven images, and by their strange vanities?

20 The harvest has passed by, the summer is at an end, and we have not been saved.

21 Over the destruction of the daughter of my people, I am contrite and saddened; astonishment has taken hold of me.

22 Is there no balm in Gilead? Or is there no physician there? Then why has the wound of the daughter of my people not been closed?"

Jeremiah 9

1 "Who will provide water for my head, and a fount of tears for my eyes? And then I will weep day and night for the slain of the daughter of my people.

2 Who will provide me, in the wilderness, with a lodging place along the road? And then I will forsake my people, and withdraw from them. For they are all adulterers, a union of transgressors.

3 And they have bent their tongue, like a bow, to send forth lies and not the truth. They have been strengthened upon the earth. And they have gone from one evil to another. But they have not known me, says the Lord.

4 Let each one guard himself against his neighbor, and let him have no trust in any brother of his. For every brother will utterly overthrow, and every friend will advance deceitfully.

5 And a man will deride his brother, and they will not speak the truth. For they have taught their tongue to speak lies; they have labored to commit iniquity.

6 Your habitation is in the midst of deceit. In their deceitfulness, they have refused to know me, says the Lord."

7 Because of this, thus says the Lord of hosts: "Behold, I will refine them, and I will test them. For what else can I do before the face of the daughter of my people?

8 Their tongue is a wounding arrow; it has spoken deceit. With his mouth, he speaks peace with his friend, and then he secretly lies in ambush for him.

9 Shall I not visit upon them concerning these things, says the Lord? Or shall my soul not take vengeance on a nation of this kind?

10 I will take up weeping and lamentation over the mountains, and mourning over the beautiful places in the desert. For they have been scorched because no man is passing through them. And they have not heard the voice of any occupant. From the birds of the air, even to the cattle, they have migrated and withdrawn.

11 And I will make Jerusalem into piles of sand and into a lair for serpents. And I will make the cities of Judah desolate, so much so that there will be no inhabitant.

12 Who is the wise man who understands this, and to whom a word from the mouth of the Lord may be given, so that he may announce this: why the land has perished, and has been scorched like a desert, so much so that no one passes through it?"

13 And the Lord said: "It is because they have abandoned my law, which I gave to them, and they have not listened to my voice, and they have not walked by it.

14 And they have gone after the depravity of their own heart, and after Baal, which they learned from their fathers."

15 For this reason, thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: "Behold, I will feed this people with absinthe, and I will give them the water of gall to drink.

16 And I will disperse them among nations, which they and their fathers have not known. And I will send the sword after them, until they are consumed."

17 Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: "Consider and call upon the women mourners, and let them approach. And send to those women who are wise, and let them hurry.

18 'Let them hasten to take up a lamentation over us. Let our eyes shed tears, and our eyelids run with water.'

19 For a voice of lamentation has been heard from Zion: 'How is it that we have been devastated and greatly confounded? Our tabernacles have been thrown down because we have forsaken the land.' "

20 "Therefore, listen, O women, to the word of the Lord! And let your ears take up the word of his mouth. And teach your daughters to lament. And let each one teach her neighbor to mourn:

21 'For death has climbed through our windows. It has entered our houses to perish the little children from the outdoors, the youths from the streets.' "

22 "Speak: Thus says the Lord: And the corpses of men will fall like manure over the face of the countryside, and like hay behind the back of the reaper, and there will be no one to gather it."

23 Thus says the Lord: "The wise man should not glory in his wisdom, and the strong man should not glory in his strength, and the rich man should not glory in his riches.

24 But he who glories should glory in this: to know me and to know me well. For I am the Lord, who accomplishes mercy and judgment and justice upon the earth. For these things are pleasing to me, says the Lord.

25 Behold, the days are approaching, says the Lord, when I will visit upon all who are uncircumcised:

26 upon Egypt, and upon Judah, and upon Edom, and upon the sons of Ammon, and upon Moab, and upon all who have shaved off their hair, living in the desert. For all the nations are uncircumcised in body, but all the house of Israel is uncircumcised in heart."

Jeremiah 10

1 Listen to the word that the Lord has spoken concerning you, O house of Israel.

2 Thus says the Lord: "Do not choose to learn according to the ways of the Gentiles. And do not be willing to dread the signs of heaven, which the Gentiles fear.

3 For the laws of the people are empty. For the work of the hand of the craftsman has cut a tree from the forest with an axe.

4 He has adorned it with silver and gold. He has put it together with nail and hammer, so that it will not fall apart.

5 They have been fabricated in the likeness of a palm tree, and they will not speak. They must be carried to be moved, because they do not have the ability to walk. Therefore, do not be willing to fear them, for they can do neither evil nor good."

6 O Lord, there is nothing similar to you. You are great, and your name is great in strength.

7 Who will not fear you, O King of the nations? For honor is yours. Among all the wise of the nations, and within all their kingdoms, there is nothing similar to you.

8 Together, they will all be proven to be unwise and foolish. The doctrine of their vanity is made of wood.

9 Rolled silver is brought from Tarshish, and gold from Uphaz. It is the work of a craftsman, and of the hand of a coppersmith. Hyacinth and purple is their clothing. All these things are the work of artists.

10 But the Lord is the true God. He is the living God and the everlasting King. Before his indignation, the earth will shake. And the Gentiles will not be able to withstand his threats.

11 "And so, you shall speak to them in this way: The gods that have not made heaven and earth, let them perish from the earth and from among those places which are under heaven.

12 He made the earth by his power, he prepared the world in his wisdom, and he stretched out the heavens with his understanding.

13 At his voice, he grants a multitude of waters in the heavens, and he lifts up the clouds from the ends of the earth. He causes the lightning with the rain, and he leads forth the wind from his storehouses.

14 Every man has become a fool concerning knowledge; every artist has been confounded by his graven image. For what he has formed is false, and there is no spirit in these things.

15 These things are empty, and they are a work deserving of ridicule. In the time of their visitation, they will perish.

16 Jacob's portion is not like their portion. For his portion is from the One who formed all things. And Israel is the staff of his inheritance. The Lord of hosts is his name.

17 Gather your shame from the earth, you who are living under siege."

18 For thus says the Lord: "Behold, in this turn, I will cast the inhabitants of the land far away. And I will afflict them no matter where they may be found."

19 Woe to me, concerning my destruction! My wound is very grievous. And yet I said: Clearly, this infirmity is mine, and I will carry it.

20 My tent has been destroyed. All my cords have been broken. My sons have gone away from me; they did not remain. There is no one to stretch out my tent any more, nor to set up my curtains.

21 For the pastors have acted foolishly, and they have not sought the Lord. Because of this, they have not understood, and all their flock has been dispersed.

22 Behold, the sound of a voice approaches, a great commotion from the land of the north: so that he may make the cities of Judah into a wilderness and into a dwelling place for serpents.

23 I know, O Lord, that the way of man is not his own. Neither is it given to man to walk and to direct his own steps.

24 Correct me, O Lord, yet truly, do so with judgment, and not in your fury. Otherwise, you will reduce me to nothing.

25 Pour out your indignation upon the nations that have not known you, and upon the provinces that have not invoked your name. For they have fed upon Jacob, and devoured him, and consumed him, and they have utterly destroyed his honor.

Jeremiah 11

1 The word that came from the Lord to Jeremiah, saying:

2 "Listen to the words of this covenant, and speak to the men of Judah and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem.

3 And you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord, the God of Israel: Cursed is the man who will not listen to the words of this covenant,

4 which I commanded to your fathers in the day when I led them away from the land of Egypt, away from the iron furnace, saying: Listen to my voice, and do all that I command you, and then you will be my people and I will be your God.

5 So shall I uphold the oath which I swore to your fathers, that I would give them a land flowing with milk and honey, just as it is this day." And I answered by saying: "Amen, O Lord."

6 And the Lord said to me: "Shout all these words in the cities of Judah, and in the streets of Jerusalem, saying: Listen to the words of the covenant, and do them.

7 For when testing, I tested your fathers in the day when I led them away from the land of Egypt, even until this day. Rising early, I tested them, and I said: Listen to my voice.

8 But they did not listen, nor did they incline their ear. Instead, each one of them walked in the depravity of his own evil heart. And so, I brought over them all the words of this covenant, which I instructed them to do. But they would not do them."

9 And the Lord said to me: "A conspiracy has been found among the men of Judah and among the inhabitants of Jerusalem.

10 They have returned to the former iniquities of their fathers, who refused to listen to my words. And likewise, they have gone after strange gods, so that they may serve them. The house of Israel and the house of Judah have treated as void my covenant, which I made with their fathers.

11 For this reason, thus says the Lord: Behold, I will lead evils over them, from which they will not be able to escape. And they will cry out to me, and I will not heed them.

12 And the cities of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem will go forth, and they will cry out to the gods, to whom they offer libations, and they will not save them in the time of their affliction.

13 For according to the number of your cities, so were your gods, O Judah. And according to the number of the streets of Jerusalem, so did you establish altars of confusion, altars to offer libations to Baal.

14 Therefore, you should not choose to pray for this people, and you should not take up praise and petitioning on their behalf. For I will not heed them in the time of their outcry to me, in the time of their affliction.

15 Why has my beloved wrought great wickedness in my house? How can the holy flesh take away from you your wickedness, in which you have gloried?

16 The Lord has called your name: a beautiful, fruitful, splendid, and productive olive tree. At the voice of a word, a great fire was kindled in it, and its greenery was burned up.

17 And the Lord of hosts, who planted you, has pronounced an evil against you, concerning the evils of the house of Israel and the house of Judah, which they have done to themselves so as to provoke me, by offering libations to Baal."

18 But you, O Lord, have revealed this to me, and I have understood. Then you displayed their efforts to me.

19 And I was like a meek lamb, who is being carried to be a victim. And I did not realize that they had devised plans against me, saying: "Let us place wood upon his bread, and let us eradicate him from the land of the living, and let his name no longer be remembered."

20 But you, O Lord of hosts, who judges justly, and who tests the temperament and the heart, let me see your vengeance against them. For I have revealed my case to you.

21 "Because of this, thus says the Lord to the men of Anathoth, who are seeking your life, and who are saying: 'You shall not prophesy in the name of the Lord, and you shall not die by our hands.'

22 Because of this, thus says the Lord of hosts: Behold, I will visit upon them. Their young men will die by the sword. Their sons and their daughters will die by famine.

23 And there will be nothing left of them. For I will lead an evil over the men of Anathoth: the year of their visitation."

Jeremiah 12

1 Certainly, O Lord, you are just. But if I may contend with you, while still speaking what is just to you: Why does the way of the impious prosper? Why is it well with all those who transgress and act unfairly?

2 You planted them, and they took root. They are prospering and bearing fruit. You are near to their mouths, but far from their hearts.

3 And you, O Lord, have known me well. You have seen me, and you have tested my heart with you. Gather them together like a flock for the sacrifice and sanctify them for the day of slaughter.

4 How long shall the earth mourn? And how long shall the plants of every field whither because of the wickedness of the inhabitants within them? It has consumed the wild animals and the birds. For they said: "He will not see our very end."

5 "If you have struggled to run on foot, how will you be able to compete with horses? And if you have been secure in a land of peace, what will you do about the arrogance of the Jordan?

6 For even your brothers, and the house of your father, even these have fought against you. And they have cried out after you with loud voice: 'You should not believe them, when they speak good things to you.' "

7 "I have abandoned my house. I have disowned my inheritance. I have given my beloved soul into the hand of its enemies.

8 My inheritance has become for me like a lion in the forest. It has uttered a voice against me, therefore, I have hated it.

9 Is my inheritance to me like a discolored bird? Is it like a bird that has entirely changed color? Approach and assemble, all beasts of the earth! Hurry, so that you may devour!

10 Many pastors have demolished my vineyard. They have trampled my portion. They have made my desirable portion into a desert of solitude.

11 They have squandered it, and it has grieved concerning me. The entire earth has become utterly desolate, because there is no one who understands with the heart."

12 The devastators have arrived, over all the ways of the wilderness. For the sword of the Lord will devour, from one end of the earth even to its furthest limits. There is no peace for all that is flesh.

13 They sowed wheat, but they reaped thorns. They received an inheritance, but it will not benefit them. You will be confounded by your own fruits, because of the wrath of the fury of the Lord.

14 Thus says the Lord against all my wicked neighbors, who touch the inheritance that I have distributed to my people Israel: "Behold, I will root them out of their own land, and I will root the house of Judah out of their midst.

15 And when I have rooted them out, I will turn back and take pity on them. And I will lead them back, one man to his inheritance, and another man to his land.

16 And this shall be: if they are taught and they learn the ways of my people, so that they swear by my name, 'As the Lord lives,' just as they had taught my people to swear by Baal, then they will be built up in the midst of my people.

17 But if they will not listen, I will uproot that nation unto utter destruction and perdition, says the Lord."

Jeremiah 13

1 Thus says the Lord to me: "Go, and obtain for yourself a linen waistcloth. And you shall place it over your loins, and you shall not put it into water."

2 And so I obtained a waistcloth, according to the word of the Lord, and I placed it around my loins.

3 And the word of the Lord came to me a second time, saying:

4 "Take the waistcloth, which you obtained, which is around your loins, and, rising up, go to the Euphrates, and hide it there in an opening of the rock."

5 And so I went, and I hid it by the Euphrates, just as the Lord had instructed me.

6 And it happened that, after many days, the Lord said to me: "Rise up, go to the Euphrates, and take from there the waistcloth, which I instructed you to hide there."

7 And so I went to the Euphrates, and I dug up and took the waistcloth from the place where I had hidden it. And behold, the waistcloth had rotted, so that it was not fit for any use.

8 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

9 "Thus says the Lord: In the same way, I will cause the arrogance of Judah and the arrogance of Jerusalem to rot.

10 This most wicked people, they are not willing to listen to my words, for they walk in the depravity of their own heart, and they have gone after strange gods, so as to serve them and to adore them. And so, they will become like this waistcloth, which is not fit for any use.

11 For just as the waistcloth clings to the loins of a man, so have I brought close to me the entire house of Israel and the entire house of Judah, says the Lord, so that they would be to me: a people, and a name, and a praise, and a glory. But they did not listen.

12 Therefore, you shall speak to them this word: Thus says the Lord, the God of Israel: 'Every bottle will be filled with wine.' And they will say to you: 'Are we ignorant that every bottle will be filled with wine?'

13 And you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord: Behold, I will fill all the inhabitants of this land, and the kings from the stock of David who sit upon his throne, and the priests, and the prophets, and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, unto inebriation.

14 And I will scatter them, a man from his brother, and fathers and sons similarly, says the Lord. I will not spare them, and I will not pardon them, and I will not take pity, so as not to destroy them."

15 Hear and pay close attention. Do not choose to lift yourself up, for the Lord has spoken.

16 Give glory to the Lord your God, before darkness falls, and before your feet stumble on the darkened mountains. You will expect light, but he will turn it into the shadow of death and into utter darkness.

17 But if you will not listen to this, then my soul will weep in secret before the face of your pride. It will weep bitterly, and my eyes will flow with tears, because the flock of the Lord has been taken captive.

18 "Say to the king and to the female ruler: Humble yourselves, sit down. For the crown of your glory has gone down from your head.

19 The cities of the south have been closed, and there is no one who may open them. All of Judah has been taken away into complete captivity.

20 Lift up your eyes and see, you who are arriving from the north. Where is the flock that was given to you, your famous cattle?

21 What will you say when he visits upon you? For you have taught them against you, and you have instructed them with your own head. Will not pains take hold of you, as with a woman in labor?

22 But if you say in your heart, 'Why have these things happened to me?' it is because of the greatness of your iniquity that your shame has been uncovered and the soles of your feet have been defiled.

23 If the Ethiopian is able to change his skin, or the leopard is able to change his spots, then you also may be able to do well, though you have learned evil.

24 And I will scatter them like chaff, which is carried away by the wind in the desert.

25 This is your lot, and this is the portion of your measure from me, says the Lord, because you have forgotten me, and you have had confidence in what is false.

26 Therefore, I have even bared your thighs before your face, and your shame has been seen.

27 For I have seen your adulteries, and your neighing for the wickedness of your fornication, and your abominations upon the hills in the field. Woe to you, Jerusalem! How much longer before you will be made clean after me?"

Jeremiah 14

1 The word of the Lord that came to Jeremiah concerning the words of the drought.

2 "Judea has mourned. And its gates have fallen and become hard to discern on the ground. And the outcry of Jerusalem has ascended.

3 The greater ones have sent their lesser ones to the water. They went to draw water; they did not find water; they carried their vessels back empty. They were confounded and afflicted, and so they covered their heads.

4 Because of the devastation of the earth, because rain did not fall upon the earth, the farmers were confounded; they covered their heads.

5 For even the doe has given birth in the field, and then left it behind. For there was no grass.

6 And the wild donkeys stood upon the rocks; like dragons, they drew in the wind, but their eyes failed. For there was no grass."

7 "O Lord, if our iniquities have responded against us, let it be for the sake of your name. For our rebellions are many; we have sinned against you.

8 O Hope of Israel, its Savior in time of tribulation, why would you be like a sojourner in the land, and like a traveler turning aside for lodging?

9 Why would you be like a wandering man, like a strong man who is unable to save? But you, O Lord, are with us, and your name is invoked over us, so do not abandon us!"

10 Thus says the Lord to this people, who have loved to move their feet, and who have not rested, but who have not pleased the Lord: "Now he will remember their iniquities, and now he will visit against their sins."

11 And the Lord said to me: "Do not choose to pray for this people for good.

12 When they will fast, I will not heed their petitions. And if they offer holocausts and victims, I will not accept them. For I will consume them by the sword, and by famine, and by pestilence."

13 And I said: "Alas, alas, alas, O Lord God! The prophets are saying to them: 'You will not see the sword, and there will be no famine among you. Instead, he will give you true peace in this place.' "

14 And the Lord said to me: "The prophets prophesy falsely in my name. I did not send them, and I did not instruct them, and I have not spoken to them. They prophesy to you a lying vision, and a divination, and a fraud, and a seduction from their own heart.

15 For this reason, thus says the Lord about the prophets who prophesy in my name, whom I have not sent, who say: 'Sword and famine will not be in this land.' By sword and famine those prophets will be consumed.

16 And the people, to whom they prophesy, will be cast into the streets of Jerusalem, due to famine and the sword, and there will be no one who may bury them, they and their wives, their sons and daughters, and I will pour out their own evil upon them.

17 And you shall speak this word to them: Let my eyes shed tears throughout the night and day, and let them not cease. For the virgin daughter of my people has been crushed by a great affliction, by a very grievous wound."

18 "If I go out into the fields: behold, those slain by the sword. And if I enter into the city: behold, those weakened by famine. Likewise, the prophet, too, and the priest, have gone into a land that they did not know.

19 Could you have utterly cast out Judah? Or has your soul abhorred Zion? Then why have you struck us, so much so that there is no health for us? We have waited for peace, but there is nothing good, and for the time of healing, and behold, trouble.

20 O Lord, we acknowledge our impieties, the iniquities of our fathers, that we have sinned against you.

21 For the sake of your name, do not give us over into disgrace. And do not dishonor in us the throne of your glory. Remember, do not make void, your covenant with us.

22 Could any of the graven images of the Gentiles send rain? Or are the heavens able to give showers? Have we not hoped in you, the Lord our God? For you have made all these things."

Jeremiah 15

1 And the Lord said to me: "Even if Moses and Samuel were to stand before me, my soul would not be toward this people. Cast them away from my face, and let them depart!

2 And if they say to you, 'Where shall we go?' you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord: Those who go to death, shall go to death. And those who go to the sword, shall go to the sword, and those go to famine, shall go to famine, and those who go to captivity, shall go to captivity.

3 And I will visit against them in four ways, says the Lord: by the sword, to kill; and by dogs, to tear apart; and by the birds of the air and by the beasts of the earth, to devour and to scatter.

4 And I will give them over to the fervor of all the kingdoms of the earth, because of Manasseh, the son of Hezekiah, the king of Judah, because of all that he did in Jerusalem.

5 For who will take pity on you, O Jerusalem? Or who will feel sorrow for you? Or who will go to prayer for the sake of your peace?

6 You have abandoned me, says the Lord. You have gone backwards. And so, I will extend my hand over you, and I will destroy you. I have labored to plead with you.

7 And I will scatter them with a winnowing fan at the gates of the land. I have killed and dispersed my people, and yet they have not turned back from their ways.

8 Their widows have been multiplied by me, more so than the sand of the sea. I have led them against the mother of a youth like an attacker at midday. I have sent a terror suddenly against the cities.

9 She who gave birth to seven has become weak. Her life has faded away. Her sun has set while it was still daytime. She has been confounded and shamed. And the remainder of them I will give over to the sword in the sight of their enemies, says the Lord."

10 "O my mother, woe to me! Why did you conceive me, a man of strife, a man of discord to all the earth? I have not lent money at interest, nor has anyone lent money at interest to me. Yet everyone is cursing me."

11 The Lord says: "Certainly, it will be well with your remnant. Certainly, I will run to meet you, in the time of affliction and in the time of tribulation, against the enemy.

12 But how can iron be joined with the iron from the north or with brass?

13 Your riches and your treasures I will give over to be freely despoiled, because of all your sins, even throughout all your borders.

14 And I will lead in your enemies from a land that you do not know. For a fire has been kindled in my fury; it will burn upon you."

15 "You know me, O Lord. Remember me, and visit me, and watch over me, because of those who persecute me. In your patience, do not choose to let me endure. You know I have suffered reproach because of you.

16 I discovered your words and I consumed them. And your word became to me as the gladness and joy of my heart. For your name has been invoked over me, O Lord, the God of hosts.

17 I did not sit in the company of mockers, nor did I glorify myself before the presence of your hand. I sat alone, because you filled me with threats.

18 Why has my sorrow become never-ending, and why has my wound become so dire that it refuses to be cured? It has become for me like the deception of untrustworthy waters."

19 Because of this, thus says the Lord: "If you will be converted, I will convert you. And you will stand before my face. And you will separate what is precious from what is vile. You will be my mouthpiece. They will be converted to you, but you will not be converted to them.

20 And I will present you to this people as a strong wall of brass. And they will fight against you, and they will not prevail. For I am with you, so as to save you and to rescue you, says the Lord.

21 And I will free you from hand of those who are most wicked, and I will redeem you from the hand of the powerful."

Jeremiah 16

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "You shall not take a wife, and there shall be no sons or daughters for you in this place.

3 For thus says the Lord concerning the sons and daughters who are conceived in this place, and concerning their mothers who give birth to them, and concerning their fathers, from whose stock they have been born in this land:

4 They will die from grievous mortal illnesses. They will not be mourned, and they will not be buried. They will be like manure on the face of the earth. And they will be consumed by sword and by famine. And their dead bodies will be food for the birds of the air and the beasts of the land."

5 For thus says the Lord: "You shall not enter the house of feasting, and you shall not go to mourn or to console them. For I have taken away from this people, says the Lord, my peace, my mercy, and my pity.

6 Both the great and the small will die in this land. They will not be buried, and they will not be mourned. And no one will cut themselves or make themselves bald on their behalf.

7 And they will not break bread among themselves for the sake of him who mourns, so as to console him over the dead. And they will not give them a chalice to drink, so as to console them over their father and mother.

8 And so, you shall not enter the house of feasting, so as to sit with them, and to eat and drink."

9 For thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: "Behold, I will take away from this place, in your sight and in your days, the voice of gladness and the voice of rejoicing, the voice of the groom and the voice of the bride.

10 And when you announce all these words to this people, they will say to you: 'Why would the Lord pronounce all this great evil against us? What is our iniquity and what is our sin that we have committed against the Lord our God?'

11 And you shall say to them: It is because your fathers abandoned me, says the Lord. And they went after strange gods, and they served them and adored them. And they abandoned me, and they did not keep my law.

12 But you have acted even worse than your fathers. For behold, each one walks after the depravity of his own evil heart, so that he does not listen to me.

13 And so, I will cast you out of this land, into a land that you do not know, and that your fathers did not know. And in that place, you will serve, day and night, strange gods who will not give you rest.

14 Therefore, behold, the days are approaching, says the Lord, when it will no longer be said, 'As the Lord lives, who led the sons of Israel away from the land of Egypt,'

15 but instead, 'As the Lord lives, who led the sons of Israel away from the land of the north,' and from all the lands to which I have cast them out. And I will lead them back into their own land, which I gave to their fathers.

16 Behold, I will send many fishermen, says the Lord, and they will fish for them. And after this, I will send many hunters to them, and they will hunt for them on every mountain, and on every hilltop, and in the caverns of the rocks.

17 For my eyes are upon all their ways. They have not been hidden from my face, and their iniquity has not been concealed from my eyes.

18 But first, I will repay their double iniquities and their sins. For they have defiled my land with the dead bodies of their idols, and they have filled my inheritance with their abominations."

19 "O Lord, my strength, and my health, and my refuge in the day of tribulation: the Gentiles will approach you from the ends of the earth, and they will say: 'Truly, our fathers possessed a lie, an emptiness that has not benefited them.'

20 How can man make gods for himself, though these are not gods?"

21 "Concerning this, behold: I will make it clear to them, in this turn. I will reveal to them my hand and my virtue. And they will know that the Lord is my name."

Jeremiah 17

1 "The sin of Judah has been written with a pen of iron and a point of diamond. It has been engraved upon the breadth of their heart and upon the horns of their shrines.

2 And their sons make a remembrance of their shrines, and their sacred groves, and their leafy trees on high mountains,

3 by sacrificing in the field. And so, I will give over your strength and all your treasures to be despoiled, along with your exalted places of sin, within all your borders.

4 And you will be left behind without your inheritance, which I gave to you. And I will cause you to serve your enemies in a land that you do not know. For you have kindled a fire in my fury; it shall burn, even unto eternity."

5 Thus says the Lord: "Cursed is a man who trusts in man, and who establishes what is flesh as his right arm, and whose heart withdraws from the Lord.

6 For he will be like a saltcedar tree in the desert. And he will not perceive it, when what is good has arrived. Instead, he will live in dryness, in a desert, in a land of salt, which is uninhabitable.

7 Blessed is the man who trusts in the Lord, for the Lord will be his confidence.

8 And he will be like a tree planted beside waters, which sends out its roots to moist soil. And it will not fear when the heat arrives. And its leaves will be green. And in the time of drought, it will not be anxious, nor will it cease at any time to bear fruit.

9 The heart is depraved above all things, and it is unsearchable, who can know it?

10 I am the Lord, who examines the heart and tests the temperament, who gives to each one according to his way and according to the fruit of his own decisions.

11 A partridge has hatched eggs that she did not lay; a man has gathered riches, but without judgment. In the midst of his days, he will leave it all behind, and he will be foolish concerning his very end."

12 "A high and glorious throne is the place of our sanctification from the beginning.

13 O Lord, Hope of Israel: all who forsake you will be confounded. Those who withdraw from you will be written into the earth. For they have abandoned the Lord, the Source of living waters.

14 Heal me, O Lord, and I will be healed. Save me, and I will be saved. For you are my praise.

15 Behold, they themselves are saying to me: 'Where is the word of the Lord? Let it come.'

16 But I am not troubled; I am following you as my shepherd. And I have not desired the day of man, as you know. That which has gone forth from my lips has been right in your sight.

17 May you not be a dread to me. You are my hope in the day of affliction.

18 May those who persecute me be confounded, but may I not be confounded. May they be fearful, and may I not be fearful. Lead over them the day of affliction, and crush them with a double destruction."

19 Thus says the Lord to me: "Go, and stand at the gate of the sons of the people, through which the kings of Judah enter and depart, and at all the gates of Jerusalem.

20 And you shall say to them: Listen to the word of the Lord, O kings of Judah, and all of Judah, and all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, who enter through these gates."

21 Thus says the Lord: "Guard your souls, and do not choose to carry heavy things on the day of the Sabbath, nor should you carry these things through the gates of Jerusalem.

22 And do not be willing to cast burdens out of your houses on the day of the Sabbath, nor should you do any work. Sanctify the day of the Sabbath, just as I instructed your fathers.

23 But they did not listen, nor did they incline their ear. Instead, they hardened their neck, lest they listen to me and receive discipline.

24 And this shall be: If you listen to me, says the Lord, so that you do not carry in burdens through the gates of this city on the day of the Sabbath, and if you sanctify the day of the Sabbath, so that you do not do work in it,

25 then there will enter through the gates of this city: kings and princes, sitting on the throne of David, and riding on chariots and horses, they and their princes, the men of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem. And this city will be inhabited forever.

26 And they will arrive from the cities of Judah and from all around Jerusalem, and from the land of Benjamin, and from the plains, and from the mountainous regions, and from the south, carrying holocausts, and victims, and sacrifices, and frankincense. And they will carry an oblation into the house of the Lord.

27 But if you will not listen to me, to sanctify the day of the Sabbath, and not to carry burdens, and not to bring these things through the gates of Jerusalem on the day of the Sabbath, then I will kindle a fire at its gates, and it will devour the houses of Jerusalem, and it will not be extinguished."

Jeremiah 18

1 The word that came to Jeremiah from the Lord, saying:

2 "Rise up and descend into the house of the potter, and there you will hear my words."

3 And I descended into the house of the potter, and behold, he was making a work on the wheel.

4 And the vessel, which he was making with his hands out of clay, broke. And turning away, he made another vessel, for it had been pleasing in his eyes to make it.

5 Then the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

6 "Am I not able to do with you, O house of Israel, just as this potter has done, says the Lord? Behold, like clay in the hand of the potter, so are you in my hand, O house of Israel.

7 Suddenly, I will speak against a nation and against a kingdom, so that I may uproot, and destroy, and scatter it.

8 If that nation, against which I have spoken, will repent from their evil, I too will repent from the evil that I have decided I would do to them.

9 And soon, I will speak about a nation and about a kingdom, so that I may build and plant it.

10 If it does evil in my sight, so as not to listen to my voice, I will repent of the good that I have said I would do to it.

11 Now, therefore, speak to the men of Judah and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem, saying: Thus says the Lord: Behold, I am forming an evil against you, and I am considering a plan against you. Let each one of you return from his evil way, and direct your ways and your intentions well."

12 And they said: "We have lost hope. And so we will follow our own thoughts, and each of us will act according to the depravity of his own evil heart."

13 For this reason, thus says the Lord: "Inquire among the Gentiles. Who has heard of such horrible things as the virgin of Israel has done to excess?

14 Do the snows of Lebanon fail to fall on the rocks of the field? Or are the cold waters, which burst forth and flow down, able to be rooted out?

15 Yet my people have forgotten me, offering useless libations, and stumbling in their ways, in the paths of the world, so that they walk by these on an unmarked route.

16 And so their land has been given over to desolation and to perpetual hissing. Each one who passes by will be astonished and will shake his head.

17 Like a burning wind, I will disperse them in the sight the enemy. I will show them the back, and not the face, in the day of their perdition."

18 And they said: "Come, and let us devise a plan against Jeremiah. For the law will not perish from the priest, nor counsel from the wise, nor a sermon from the prophet. Come, and let us strike him with the tongue, and let us pay no attention to any of his words."

19 Attend to me, O Lord, and hear the voice of my adversaries.

20 Should evil be rendered for good? For they have dug a pit for my soul! Remember that I have stood in your sight, so as to speak on their behalf for good, and to avert your indignation from them.

21 Because of this, give their sons over to famine, and bring them to the hand of the sword. Let their wives be widows without children. And let their husbands be slain by death. Let their youths be stabbed with the sword in battle.

22 Let an outcry be heard from their houses. For you will lead the robber upon them suddenly. For they have dug a pit, so that they may seize me, and they have hidden snares for my feet.

23 But you, O Lord, know all their plans against me unto death. May you not forgive their iniquity, and do not allow their sin be taken away from your face. Let them be thrown down in your sight, in the time of your fury, so that you may destroy them.

Jeremiah 19

1 Thus says the Lord: "Go, and take a potter's earthen bottle from the elders of the people and from the elders of the priests.

2 And go out to the valley of the son of Hinnom, which is near the entrance to the earthen gate, and there you shall proclaim the words that I will speak to you.

3 And you shall say: Listen to the word of the Lord, O kings of Judah, and you inhabitants of Jerusalem. Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: Behold, I will lead an affliction over this place, so much so that it will ring in the ears of all who hear about it.

4 For they have abandoned me, and they have made this place foreign, and they have offered libations in it to foreign gods, whom neither they, nor their fathers, nor the kings of Judah have known. And they have filled this place with the blood of the innocent.

5 And they have built the exalted places of Baal, in order to burn their children with fire as a holocaust to Baal, something that I did not instruct or speak of, nor did it enter into my heart.

6 Because of this, behold, the days are approaching, says the Lord, when this place will no longer be called Topheth, or the valley of the son of Hinnom, but the Valley of Slaughter.

7 And I will scatter the counsel of Judah and of Jerusalem in this place. And I will overthrow them with the sword, in the sight of their enemies and by the hand of those who seek their lives. And I will give their carcasses to the birds of the air and to the beasts of the land as food.

8 And I will set this city amid stupor and hissing. Everyone who passes by it will be stupefied, and they will hiss over all its wounds.

9 And I will feed them with the flesh of their sons and with the flesh of their daughters. And each one of them will eat the flesh of his friend during the blockade and the embargo by which their enemies, and those who seek their lives, will enclose them.

10 And you shall crush the bottle in the sight of the men who will go with you.

11 And you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord of hosts: In the same way, I will crush this people and this city, just as the potter's vessel was crushed and cannot be made whole again. And they will be buried at Topheth, because there will be no other place for burial.

12 So will I do to this place and to its inhabitants, says the Lord. And I will make this city to be like Topheth.

13 And the houses of Jerusalem and the houses of the kings of Judah will be unclean, just like the place of Topheth: all the houses on whose roofs they sacrificed to all the armies of heaven and poured out libations to strange gods."

14 Then Jeremiah arrived from Topheth, where the Lord had sent him to prophesy, and he stood in the atrium of the house of the Lord, and he said to all the people:

15 "Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: Behold, I will lead over this community, and over all its cities, all the evils that I have spoken against it. For they have hardened their necks, so that they would not heed my words."

Jeremiah 20

1 And Pashhur, the son of Immer, the priest who had been appointed leader in the house of the Lord, heard Jeremiah prophesying these words.

2 And Pashhur struck the prophet Jeremiah, and he sent him to the stocks, which were at the upper gate of Benjamin at the house of the Lord.

3 And when it had become light on the next day, Pashhur led Jeremiah from the stocks. And Jeremiah said to him: "The Lord has not called your name: 'Pashhur,' but instead: 'Fear all around.' "

4 For thus says the Lord: "Behold, I will give you over to fear, you and all your friends, and they will fall by the sword of their enemies, and your eyes will see it. And I will give all of Judah into the hand of the king of Babylon. And he will lead them away to Babylon, and he will strike them with the sword.

5 And I will give away the entire substance of this city, and all its labor, and every precious thing. And I will give all the treasures of the kings of Judah into the hands of their enemies. And they will plunder them, and take them away, and lead them into Babylon.

6 But you, Pashhur, and all the inhabitants of your house, will go into captivity. And you will go to Babylon. And there you shall die. And there you shall be buried, you and all your friends, to whom you have prophesied a lie."

7 "You have led me away, O Lord, and I have been led away. You have been stronger than I, and you have prevailed. I have become a derision all day long; everyone mocks me.

8 For I speak now as I have long spoken: crying out against iniquity and proclaiming devastation. And the word of the Lord has been made into a reproach against me and a derision, all day long.

9 Then I said: I will not call him to mind, nor will I speak any longer in his name. And my heart became like a raging fire, enclosed within my bones. And I became weary of continuing to bear it.

10 For I heard the insults of many, and terror all around: 'Persecute him!' and, 'Let us persecute him!' from all the men who had been at peace with me and who had kept watch by my side. 'If only there were some way that he might be deceived, and we might prevail against him and obtain vengeance from him!'

11 But the Lord is with me, like a strong warrior. For this reason, those who persecute me will fall, and they will be ineffective. They will be greatly confounded. For they have not understood the everlasting disgrace that will never be wiped away.

12 And you, O Lord of hosts, the Tester of the just, who sees the temperament and the heart: I beg you to let me see your vengeance upon them. For I have revealed my case to you.

13 Sing to the Lord! Praise the Lord! For he has freed the soul of the poor from the hand of the wicked.

14 Cursed is the day on which I was born! The day on which my mother gave birth to me: let it not be blessed!

15 Cursed is the man who announced it to my father, saying, 'A male child has been born to you,' causing him to rejoice with gladness.

16 Let that man be like the cities that the Lord has overthrown without regret. Let him hear an outcry in the morning, and wailing at the time of midday!

17 So let him be, who did not put me to death from the womb, so that my mother would have been my sepulcher, and her womb would have been my eternal resting place!

18 Why did I depart from the womb, so that I would see hardship and sorrow, and so that my days would be consumed by trouble?"

Jeremiah 21

1 The word that came to Jeremiah from the Lord, when king Zedekiah sent Pashhur, the son of Malchiah, and Zephaniah, the son of Maaseiah, the priest, to him, saying:

2 "Question the Lord on our behalf, for Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, is fighting against us. Perhaps it may be that the Lord will act toward us according to all his wonders, and he may withdraw from us."

3 And Jeremiah said to them: "This is what you shall say to Zedekiah:

4 Thus says the Lord, the God of Israel: Behold, I will turn back the weapons of war that are in your hands, with which you fight against the king of Babylon and the Chaldeans, who besiege you at the surrounding walls. And I will gather these things together in the midst of this city.

5 And I myself will make war against you: with an outstretched hand, and with a strong arm, and in fury, and in indignation, and in great wrath.

6 And I will strike the inhabitants of this city; men and beasts will die from a great pestilence.

7 And afterward, thus says the Lord: I will give Zedekiah, the king of Judah, and his servants, and his people, and those who have been left behind in this city after pestilence and the sword and famine, into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, and into the hand of their enemies, and into the hand of those who seek their lives. And he will strike them with the edge of the sword. And he will not waver, and he will not be lenient, and he will not take pity.

8 And to this people, you shall say: Thus says the Lord: Behold, I set before you the way of life and the way of death.

9 Whoever lives in this city will die by the sword, and by famine, and by pestilence. But whoever will have departed and fled away to the Chaldeans, who besiege you, will live, and his life will be to him like a spoil.

10 For I have set my face against this city for evil, and not for good, says the Lord. It will be given into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he will burn it with fire.

11 And to the house of the king of Judah, you shall say: Listen to the word of the Lord,

12 O house of David! Thus says the Lord: Judge with judgment from early morning, and rescue anyone who is oppressed by violence from the hand of a false accuser. Otherwise, my indignation may go forth like a fire, and may flare up, and there will be no one who can extinguish it, because of the evil of your intentions.

13 Behold, I am against you, O inhabitants of a valley with firm and level ground, says the Lord. And you say: 'Who can strike us? And who can enter into our houses?'

14 But I will visit against you according to the fruit of your intentions, says the Lord. And I will kindle a fire in its forest. And it shall devour everything around it."

Jeremiah 22

1 Thus says the Lord: "Descend to the house of the king of Judah, and there you shall speak this word.

2 And you shall say: Listen to the word of the Lord, O king of Judah, who sits upon the throne of David: you and your servants, and your people, who enter through these gates.

3 Thus says the Lord: Exercise judgment and justice, and free anyone who is oppressed by violence from the hand of a false accuser. And do not be willing to sadden the new arrival, or the orphan, or the widow, nor should you burden them unfairly. And you shall not shed innocent blood in this place.

4 For if you will indeed accomplish this word, then there will enter through the gates of this house kings from the stock of David, sitting on his throne, and riding on chariots and on horses: they, and their servants, and their people.

5 But if you will not listen to these words, I swear by myself, says the Lord, that this house will be in desolation.

6 For thus says the Lord about the house of the king of Judah: You are to me like Gilead, the head of Lebanon. Certainly, I will make you desolate, with uninhabitable cities.

7 And I will sanctify over you the destroying man and his weapons. And they will cut down your select cedars and throw them violently into the fire.

8 And many nations will pass through this city. And each one will say to his neighbor: 'Why has the Lord acted in this way toward this great city?'

9 And they will answer: 'It is because they abandoned the covenant of the Lord their God, and they adored strange gods and served them.'

10 You should not choose to weep for the dead, nor should you mourn over them with tears. Lament for him who is departing, for he will return no more, nor will he see his native land again.

11 For thus says the Lord to Shallum, the son of Josiah, the king of Judah, who reigned in place of his father, who has departed from this place: He will not return here again.

12 Instead, he will die in the place to which I have transferred him, and he will not see this land anymore.

13 Woe to one who builds his house with injustice and his upper rooms without judgment, who oppresses his friend without cause and does not pay him his wages.

14 And he says: 'I will build a broad house for myself, with spacious upper rooms.' He makes windows for himself, and he builds the roof out of cedar, and he paints it with red ocher.

15 Will you reign because you compare yourself to the cedar? Did your father not eat and drink, and act with judgment and justice, so that it would be well with him?

16 He judged the case of the poor and the indigent for their good. Was this not because he knew me, says the Lord?

17 Yet truly, your eyes and your heart are toward avarice and the shedding of innocent blood, and toward false accusations and the pursuit of evil deeds.

18 Because of this, thus says the Lord toward Jehoiakim, the son of Josiah, king of Judah: They will not mourn for him by saying, 'Alas,' to a brother, or, 'Alas,' to a sister. They will not make a noise for him and say, 'Alas,' to a master, or, 'Alas,' to a nobleman.

19 He will be buried with the burial of a donkey, having rotted and been thrown out of the gates of Jerusalem.

20 Ascend to Lebanon and cry out! And utter your voice in Bashan, and cry out to those passing by. For all your lovers have been crushed.

21 I spoke to you in your abundance, and you said, 'I will not listen.' This has been your way from your youth, for you have not listened to my voice.

22 The wind will feed all your shepherds, and your lovers will go into captivity. And then you will be confounded, and you will be ashamed of all your wickedness.

23 You who sit in Lebanon, and who nest in the cedars, in what way did you mourn when suffering came to you, like the suffering of a woman giving birth?

24 As I live, says the Lord, if Jeconiah, the son of Jehoiakim, the king of Judah, were a ring on my right hand, I would remove him from there.

25 And I will deliver you into the hand of those who seek your life, and into the hand of those whose face you dread, and into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, and into the hand of the Chaldeans.

26 And I will send you, and your mother who conceived you, into a foreign land, in which you were not born, and there you shall die.

27 And to the land about which they lift up their mind, thinking to return there, they shall not return.

28 Is this man, Jeconiah, a broken earthenware vessel? Is he a vessel which is entirely unpleasing? Why have they been cast out, he and his offspring, cast out even into a land that they have not known?

29 O earth, O earth, O earth! Listen to the word of the Lord!

30 Thus says the Lord: Write: this man is barren; he is a man who will not prosper in his days. For there will not be a man from among his offspring who will sit upon the throne of David, or have authority in Judah, anymore."

Jeremiah 23

1 "Woe to the shepherds who scatter and tear apart the sheep of my pasture, says the Lord.

2 Because of this, thus says the Lord, the God of Israel, to the shepherds who pasture my people: You have scattered my flock, and you have driven them away, and you have not visited them. Behold, I will visit upon you because of your evil pursuits, says the Lord.

3 And I will gather together the remnant of my flock from the entire earth, from the places to which I had cast them out. And I will return them to their own fields. And they will increase and be multiplied.

4 And I will raise up shepherds over them, and they will pasture them. They will no longer dread, and they will no longer fear. And no one among their number will be seeking more, says the Lord.

5 Behold, the days are approaching, says the Lord, when I will raise up to David a righteous branch. And a king will reign, and he will be wise. And he will exercise judgment and justice upon the earth.

6 In those days, Judah will be saved, and Israel will live in confidence. And this is the name that they will call him: 'The Lord, our Just One.'

7 Because of this, behold, the days are approaching, says the Lord, when they will no longer say, 'As the Lord lives, who led the sons of Israel away from the land of Egypt,'

8 but instead, 'As the Lord lives, who led away and brought back the offspring of the house of Israel from the land of the north and from the entire earth,' from the places to which I had cast them out. And they will live in their own land."

9 To the prophets: "My heart is crushed within me. All my bones are trembling. I have become like an inebriated man, and like a man maddened by wine, before the face of the Lord, and before the face of his holy words.

10 For the earth is full of adulterers! And the earth has mourned before the face of evil talk. The plains of the desert have dried up, and their course has become hazardous, and their firmness has become uneven."

11 "For both the prophet and the priest have become polluted, and I have found their wickedness within my own house, says the Lord.

12 For this reason, their way will be like a slippery path in the dark. For they will be impelled forward, and they will fall in it. For I will bring evils over them, in the year of their visitation, says the Lord.

13 And I have seen the foolishness of the prophets of Samaria. They have prophesied in Baal, and they have deceived my people Israel.

14 And in the prophets of Jerusalem, I have seen the likeness of adulterers and the path of falsehood. And they have strengthened the hands of the wicked, so that each one would not convert from his malice. They have all become to me like Sodom, and its inhabitants have become like Gomorrah."

15 Because of this, thus says the Lord of hosts to the prophets: "Behold, I will feed them absinthe, and I will give them gall to drink. For from the prophets of Jerusalem corruption has gone forth over the entire earth."

16 Thus says the Lord of hosts: "Do not choose to listen to the words of the prophets who prophesy to you and deceive you. They speak a vision from their own heart, and not from the mouth of the Lord.

17 To those who blaspheme me, they say: 'The Lord has said: You shall have peace.' And to every one who walks in the depravity of his own heart, they have said: 'No evil will overwhelm you.' "

18 For who has been present in the counsel of the Lord, and who has seen and heard his word? Who has considered his word and heard it?

19 Behold, the whirlwind of the Lord's indignation will go forth, and a tempest will break out; it will overwhelm the head of the impious.

20 The fury of the Lord will not return until it succeeds, and until it completes the plan of his heart. In the last days, you will understand this counsel.

21 "I did not send these prophets, yet they hurry forward. I was not speaking to them, yet they were prophesying.

22 If they had stood in my counsel, and if I had made my words known to my people, certainly I would have turned them away from their evil ways and from their most wicked plans.

23 Do you not realize that I am a God close by, says the Lord, and not a God far away?

24 If a man is hidden in concealed places, do I not see him, says the Lord? Do I not fill up heaven and earth, says the Lord?

25 I have heard what the prophets have said, prophesying falsehoods in my name, and also saying: 'I have dreamed! I have dreamed!'

26 How long will this be in the heart of the prophets who predict what is false, and who prophesy deceptions from their own heart?

27 They want to cause my people to forget my name, by means of their dreams, which each of them describes to his neighbor, just as their fathers forgot my name for the sake of Baal.

28 The prophet who has had a dream, let him describe the dream. And he who receives my word, let him speak my word in truth. For what has the chaff to do with the wheat, says the Lord?

29 Are not my words like a fire, says the Lord, and like a hammer crushing rock?

30 Therefore, behold: I am against the prophets, says the Lord, who steal my words, each one from his neighbor.

31 Behold, I am against the prophets, says the Lord, who take up their tongues and say: 'The Lord says it.'

32 Behold, I am against the prophets, who dream what is false, says the Lord; who explain and so seduce my people with their falsehoods and with their miracles, though I did not send them, nor did I command them. They have offer nothing beneficial to this people, says the Lord.

33 Therefore, if this people, or a prophet, or a priest questions you, saying, 'What is the burden of the Lord?' you shall say to them, 'You are the burden. And certainly I will cast you away, says the Lord.'

34 And as for the prophet, and the priest, and the people who say, 'The burden of the Lord!' I will visit upon that man and upon his house.

35 And then you will speak in this way, each one to his neighbor and to his brother: 'What has the Lord answered? And what has the Lord said?'

36 And the burden of the Lord will be no longer be called to mind. For each one's own word will be a burden. For you have perverted the words of the living God, of the Lord of hosts, our God.

37 And then you will speak in this way to the prophet: 'What has the Lord answered you? And what has the Lord spoken?'

38 But if you say, 'The burden of the Lord!' then because of this, thus says the Lord: Since you have spoken this word, 'The burden of the Lord!' though I sent to you telling you not to say: 'The burden of the Lord,'

39 because of this, behold, I will take you away, like a burden, and I will forsake you, as well as the city that I gave to you and to your fathers, before my face.

40 And I will give you over to an everlasting reproach and an eternal disgrace, which shall never be wiped away into oblivion."

Jeremiah 24

1 The Lord revealed to me, and behold, two baskets full of figs were set before the temple of the Lord, after Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, carried away Jeconiah, the son of Jehoiakim, king of Judah, and his leaders, and the craftsmen and engravers of Jerusalem, and led them into Babylon.

2 One basket had exceedingly good figs, like the figs usually found early in the season, and the other basket had exceedingly bad figs, which could not be eaten because they were so bad.

3 And the Lord said to me: "What do you see, Jeremiah?" And I said: "Figs: the good figs are very good, and the bad figs are very bad and cannot be eaten because they are so bad."

4 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

5 "Thus says the Lord, the God of Israel: Just like these good figs, so will I regard as good the captives of Judah, whom I have sent from this place into the land of the Chaldeans.

6 And I will set my eyes upon them, so as to be pleased. And I will lead them back into this land. And I will build them up, and I will not tear them down. And I will plant them, and I will not uproot them.

7 And I will give them a heart, so that they may know me, that I am the Lord. And they will be my people, and I will be their God. For they shall return to me with their whole heart.

8 And just like the very bad figs, which cannot be eaten because they are so bad, thus says the Lord: so will I regard Zedekiah, the king of Judah, and his leaders, and the rest of Jerusalem, those who have remained in this city, and those who are living in the land of Egypt.

9 And I will give them over, with upheaval and affliction, to all the kingdoms of the earth: to be a disgrace, and a parable, and a proverb, and a curse in all the places to which I have cast them out.

10 And I will send among them the sword, and famine, and pestilence: until they have been worn away from the land, which I gave to them and to their fathers."

Jeremiah 25

1 The word that came to Jeremiah about all the people of Judah, in the fourth year of Jehoiakim, the son of Josiah, the king of Judah. The same is the first year of Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon.

2 And the prophet Jeremiah spoke to all the people of Judah, and to all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, saying:

3 "From the thirteenth year of Josiah, the son of Amon, the king of Judah, even until this day, which is the twenty-third year, the word of the Lord has been given to me, and I have spoken to you, rising while it was still night, and speaking, and yet you have not listened.

4 And the Lord has sent to you all his servants, the prophets, rising at first light, and sending, and yet you have not listened, and you have not inclined your ears, so that you would hear,

5 when he said: Return, each one from his evil way, and from your wicked thoughts. And you shall dwell in the land, which the Lord has given to you and to your fathers, from ancient times and even forever.

6 And do not choose to go after strange gods, so that you would serve them and adore them. And do not provoke me to wrath by the works of your hands. And then I will not afflict you.

7 And yet you have not listened to me, says the Lord, and so you have provoked me to anger with the works of your hands, to your own harm."

8 Because of this, thus says the Lord of hosts: "Since you have not listened to my words,

9 behold, I will send for and take all the associates of the north, says the Lord, and Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, my servant, and I will lead them over this land, and over its inhabitants, and over all the nations that are around it. And I will destroy them, and I will set them in the midst of stupor and hissing, and continual desolations.

10 And I will perish from them the voice of gladness and the voice of rejoicing, the voice of the groom and the voice of the bride, the sound of the millstone and the light of the lamp.

11 And this entire land will be in desolation and in stupor. And all these nations will serve the king of Babylon, for seventy years.

12 And when the seventy years have been completed, I will visit their iniquity upon the king of Babylon, and upon that nation, and upon the land of the Chaldeans, says the Lord. And I will set it in continual desolations.

13 And I will lead over that land all my words, which I have spoken against it, all that has been written in this book, everything whatsoever that Jeremiah has prophesied against all the nations.

14 For they have served them, though these were populous nations and great kings. And I will repay them according to their works and according to the deeds of their hands."

15 For thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: "Take the chalice of the wine of this fury from my hand. And you shall cause all the nations, to which I will send you, to drink from it.

16 And they will drink, and be stirred up, and become maddened, before the face of the sword that I will send among them."

17 And I received the chalice from the hand of the Lord, and I caused all the nations, to which the Lord has sent me, to drink from it:

18 Jerusalem, and the cities of Judah, and its kings, and its leaders, so that I gave them over to desolation, and stupor, and hissing, and a curse, just as it is this day.

19 "But as for Pharaoh, the king of Egypt, and his servants, and his leaders, and all his people,

20 and the entire populace in general: all the kings of the land of the south, and all the kings of the land of the Philistines, and Ashkelon, and Gaza, and Ekron, and the remnant of Ashdod,

21 and Idumea, and Moab, and the sons of Ammon,

22 and all the kings of Tyre, and all the kings of Sidon, and the kings of the land of the islands that are across the sea,

23 and Dedan, and Tema, and Buz, and all those who have shaved off their hair,

24 and all the kings of Arabia, and all the kings of the west, who live in the desert,

25 and all the kings of Zimri, and all the kings of Elam, and all the kings of Media,

26 and likewise, all the kings of the north from near to far, each one facing his brother, and all the kingdoms upon the face of the earth, and the king of Sesac: all these shall drink after them.

27 And you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: Drink, and be inebriated, and vomit, and fall down. And you shall not rise up before the face the sword that I will send among you.

28 And if they refuse to receive the cup from your hand and to drink, you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord of hosts: Certainly, you shall drink!

29 For behold, I am beginning to afflict the city in which my name has been invoked, and will you be innocent and immune? You will not be immune! For I will call the sword over all the inhabitants of the earth, says the Lord of hosts.

30 And you shall prophesy to them all these words, and you shall say to them: The Lord will roar from on high, and he will utter his voice from his holy habitation. When roaring, he will roar over the place of his beauty. He will call out, like those who chant in rhythm as they trample the grapes, against all the inhabitants of the earth.

31 The sound of it will penetrate even to the ends of the earth. For the Lord is entering into judgment with the nations. He himself is entering into judgment with all flesh. I have delivered the impious to the sword, says the Lord."

32 Thus says the Lord of hosts: "Behold, an affliction will go forth from nation to nation, and a great whirlwind will go forth from the ends of the earth.

33 And the slain of the Lord will be, on that day, from one end of the earth, even to the other end. They will not be mourned, and they will not be gathered, and they will not be buried. They will lie upon the face of the earth like dung.

34 Wail, O shepherds, and cry out! And sprinkle yourselves with ashes, O nobles of the flock! For the days have been completed that lead to your slaughter and your destruction. And you will fall like precious vessels.

35 And escape will flee from the shepherds, and safety will flee from the nobility of the flock."

36 There is a voice of outcry from the shepherds, and a wailing among the nobles among the flock! For the Lord has laid waste to their pastures.

37 And the fields of peace have been silenced before the face of the fury of the Lord.

38 He has abandoned those he sheltered like a lion. For the earth has become a desolation before the face of the anger of the dove, and before the face of the fury of the Lord.

Jeremiah 26

1 In the beginning of the reign of Jehoiakim, the son of Josiah, the king of Judah, this word came from the Lord, saying:

2 "Thus says the Lord: Stand in the atrium of the house of the Lord, and speak to all the cities of Judah, from which they come to adore in the house of the Lord, all the words that I have commanded you to speak to them. Do not choose to subtract any word.

3 So may they hear and be converted, each one from his evil way. And then I may repent of the evil that I plan to do to them because of the wickedness of their pursuits.

4 And you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord: If you will not listen to me, so that you walk in my law, which I have given to you,

5 so that you listen to the words of my servants, the prophets, whom I have sent to you, who arise while it is still night, and though they give guidance, you do not listen,

6 then I will make this house like Shiloh, and I will make this city into a curse for all the nations of the earth."

7 And the priests, and the prophets, and all the people heard Jeremiah speaking these words in the house of the Lord.

8 And when Jeremiah had completed speaking all that the Lord had instructed him to speak to all the people, then the priests, and the prophets, and all the people apprehended him, saying: "You shall be put to death."

9 "Why has he prophesied in the name of the Lord, saying: 'Like Shiloh, so shall this house be,' and, 'This city shall be made desolate, even without an inhabitant?' " And all the people were gathered together against Jeremiah in the house of the Lord.

10 And the leaders of Judah heard these words. And they ascended from the house of the king to the house of the Lord, and they sat at the entrance by the new gate of the house of the Lord.

11 And the priests and the prophets spoke to the leaders and to all the people, saying: "A judgment of death is for this man. For he has prophesied against this city, just as you have heard with your own ears."

12 And Jeremiah spoke to all the leaders and to the entire people, saying: "The Lord has sent me to prophesy, about this house and about this city, all the words that you have heard.

13 Now, therefore, make your ways and your intentions good, and heed the voice of the Lord your God. And then the Lord will repent of the evil that he has spoken against you.

14 But as for me, behold, I am in your hands. Do to me what is good and right in your eyes.

15 Yet truly, know and understand this: if you kill me, you will be bringing innocent blood against yourselves, and against this city and its inhabitants. For in truth, the Lord sent me to you, so as to speak all these words in your hearing."

16 And then the leaders and all the people said to the priests and to the prophets: "There is no judgment of death against this man. For he has spoken to us in the name of the Lord our God."

17 Then some of the elders of the land rose up. And they spoke to the entire assembly of the people, saying:

18 "Micah from Moresheth was a prophet in the days of Hezekiah, the king of Judah, and he spoke to all the people of Judah, saying: 'Thus says the Lord of hosts: Zion will be ploughed like a field. And Jerusalem will be a pile of stones. And the mountain of the house will be like the forests of high places.'

19 Did the king of Judah, Hezekiah, with all of Judah, condemn him to death? Did they not fear the Lord, and petition the face of the Lord? And so the Lord repented of the evil that he had spoken against them. Therefore, we are committing a great evil against our own souls.

20 Likewise, there was a man prophesying in the name of the Lord: Uriah, the son of Shemaiah, of Kiriath-jearim. And he prophesied against this city and against this land, in accord with all the words of Jeremiah.

21 And king Jehoiakim, with all his warriors and leaders, heard these words. And so the king sought to put him to death. And Uriah heard, and was afraid, and fled, and he entered into Egypt.

22 And king Jehoiakim sent men into Egypt: Elnathan, the son of Achbor, and the men who went with him into Egypt.

23 And they led Uriah out of Egypt. And they brought him to king Jehoiakim, and he struck him down with the sword. And he cast his dead body among the graves of the common people."

24 But the hand of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, was with Jeremiah, so that he would not be delivered into the hands of the people, and so that they would not put him to death.

Jeremiah 27

1 In the beginning of the reign of Jehoiakim, the son of Josiah, the king of Judah, this word came to Jeremiah from the Lord, saying:

2 "Thus says the Lord to me: Make bands and chains for yourself. And you shall place them on your neck.

3 And you shall send them to the king of Edom, and to the king of Moab, and to the king of the sons of Ammon, and to the king of Tyre, and to the king of Sidon, by the hand of the messengers who came to Jerusalem, to Zedekiah, the king of Judah.

4 And you shall instruct them to say to their masters: Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: You shall say these things to your masters:

5 I made the earth, and the men and beasts which are upon the face of the earth, by my great strength and by my outstretched arm. And I have given it to whomever it was pleasing in my eyes.

6 And now, therefore, I have given all these lands into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, my servant. Moreover, I have given to him also the beasts of the field, so that they may serve him.

7 And all the nations will serve him, and his son, and his son's son. Many nations and great kings will serve him, until the time arrives for him and his land.

8 But the nation or kingdom that will not serve Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, and whoever will not bend his neck under the yoke of the king of Babylon, I will visit upon that nation with the sword, and with famine, and with pestilence, says the Lord, until I consume them by his hand.

9 Therefore, you should not choose to listen to your own prophets, and diviners, and dreamers, and soothsayers, and sorcerers, who say to you: 'You shall not serve the king of Babylon.'

10 For they prophesy lies to you, so that they may cause you to be far from your own country, and may cast you out, and may cause you to perish.

11 Furthermore, the nation which will bend its neck under the yoke of the king of Babylon, and which will serve him, I will permit them to remain in their own land, says the Lord. And they will cultivate it, and they will live in it."

12 And I spoke to Zedekiah, the king of Judah, according to all these words, saying: "Subject your necks under the yoke of the king of Babylon, and serve him and his people, and you will live.

13 Why should you suffer death, you and your people, by the sword, and famine, and pestilence, just as the Lord has spoken against any nation that refuses to serve the king of Babylon?

14 Do not choose to listen to the words of the prophets, saying to you: 'You will not serve the king of Babylon.' For they are speaking a lie to you.

15 For I have not sent them, says the Lord. And they prophesy falsely in my name, so that they may cast you out, and so that you may perish, both you and the prophets who make predictions for you."

16 I spoke also to the priests and to this people, saying: "Thus says the Lord: Do not choose to listen to the words of your prophets, who prophesy to you, saying: 'Behold, the vessels of the Lord will now quickly be returned from Babylon.' For they are prophesying to you a lie.

17 Therefore, do not choose to listen to them, but instead, serve the king of Babylon, so that you may live. Why should this city be given over into desolation?

18 But if they are prophets, and if the word of the Lord is in them, then let them intercede before the Lord of hosts, so that the vessels that were left behind in the house of the Lord, and in the house of the king of Judah, and in Jerusalem, may not go to Babylon.

19 For thus says the Lord of hosts to the pillars, and to the sea of brass, and to the bases, and to the remainder of the vessels that have been left behind in this city,

20 which Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, did not take when he carried away Jeconiah, the son of Jehoiakim, the king of Judah, from Jerusalem into Babylon, with all the nobility of Judah and Jerusalem:

21 For thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel, to the vessels that were left behind in the house of the Lord and in the house of the king of Judah and Jerusalem:

22 They shall be carried away to Babylon, and there they shall be, until the day of their visitation, says the Lord. And then I will cause them to be carried back, and to be restored to this place.

Jeremiah 28

1 And it happened in that year, in the beginning of the reign of Zedekiah, the king of Judah, in the fourth year, in the fifth month, that Hananiah, the son of Azur, the prophet from Gibeon, spoke to me, in the house of the Lord, in the sight of the priests and all the people, saying:

2 "Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: I have broken the yoke of the king of Babylon.

3 There are still two years of days, and then I will cause to be carried back to this place all the vessels of the house of the Lord that Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, took from this place and carried away to Babylon.

4 And I will return to this place: Jeconiah, the son of Jehoiakim, the king of Judah, and all those taken captive from Judah, who were brought into Babylon, says the Lord. For I will crush the yoke of the king of Babylon."

5 And Jeremiah the prophet spoke to Hananiah the prophet, before the eyes of the priests and before the eyes of all the people who were standing in the house of the Lord.

6 And Jeremiah the prophet said: "Amen, may the Lord accomplish this; may the Lord act upon your words, which you have prophesied, so that the vessels may be carried back to the house of the Lord, and so that all those taken captive may return from Babylon to this place.

7 Yet truly, listen to this word, which I am speaking to your ears and to the ears of all the people.

8 The prophets, who were before me and before you, from the beginning, have prophesied over many lands and over great kingdoms, about war, and about affliction, and about famine.

9 The prophet who has predicted peace, if his word will occur, then the prophet will be known as one whom the Lord has sent in truth."

10 And Hananiah the prophet took the chain from the neck of Jeremiah the prophet, and he broke it.

11 And Hananiah spoke in the sight of all the people, saying: "Thus says the Lord: So shall I break the yoke of Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, after two years of days, from the neck of all the people."

12 And Jeremiah the prophet went his own way. And after Hananiah the prophet had broken the chain from the neck of Jeremiah the prophet, the word of the Lord came to Jeremiah, saying:

13 "Go, and you shall say to Hananiah: Thus says the Lord: You have broken chains of wood, and so you will make for them chains of iron.

14 For thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: I have placed a yoke of iron on the neck of all these nations, so that they may serve Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon. And they shall serve him. Moreover, I have given to him even the beasts of the earth."

15 And Jeremiah the prophet said to Hananiah the prophet: "Listen, Hananiah! The Lord has not sent you, and so you have caused this people to trust in a lie.

16 For this reason, thus says the Lord: Behold, I will send you away from the face of the earth. This year, you shall die. For you have spoken against the Lord."

17 And Hananiah the prophet died in that year, in the seventh month.

Jeremiah 29

1 And these are the words of the letter which Jeremiah, the prophet, sent from Jerusalem to the remnant of the elders of the transmigration, and to the priests, and to the prophets, and to all the people, whom Nebuchadnezzar had led away from Jerusalem to Babylon,

2 after king Jeconiah, with the queen, and the eunuchs, and the leaders of Judah and of Jerusalem, and the craftsmen and engravers, had departed from Jerusalem.

3 It was sent by the hand of Elasah, the son of Shaphan, and by Gemariah, the son of Hilkiah, whom Zedekiah, the king of Judah, sent to Babylon to Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, saying:

4 "Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel, to all who have been taken away, whom I have caused to be transferred from Jerusalem to Babylon:

5 Build houses and live in them. And plant gardens, and eat from their fruit.

6 Take wives, and conceive sons and daughters. And give wives to your sons, and give your daughters to husbands, and let them bear sons and daughters. And be multiplied there, and do not choose to be few in number.

7 And seek the peace of the city, to which I have caused you to be taken away, and pray to the Lord on its behalf. For your peace will be in its peace.

8 For thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: Do not allow your prophets and your diviners, who are in your midst, to seduce you. And you should pay no attention to your dreams, which you are dreaming.

9 For they prophesy falsely to you in my name, and I have not sent them, says the Lord.

10 For thus says the Lord: When the seventy years will begin to be completed in Babylon, I will visit you. And I will raise up over you my good word, so that I may lead you back to this place.

11 For I know the thoughts that I think over you, says the Lord: thoughts of peace and not of affliction, so that I may give you patience and an end.

12 And you shall call upon me, and you shall go forth. And you shall pray to me, and I will heed you.

13 You shall seek me. And you will find me, when you have sought me with your whole heart.

14 And I will be found by you, says the Lord. And I will lead you back from your captivity. And I will gather you from all the nations and all the places, to which I have expelled you, says the Lord. And I will return you from the place to which I sent you into captivity.

15 For you have said: 'The Lord has raised up prophets for us in Babylon.'

16 For thus says the Lord, to the king who sits upon the throne of David, and to all the people who live in this city, to your brothers who have not departed with you in the transmigration:

17 Thus says the Lord of hosts: Behold, I will send among them the sword, and famine, and pestilence. And I will make them like the bad figs, which cannot be eaten, because they are very bad.

18 And I will pursue them with the sword, and with famine, and with pestilence. And I will give them over to affliction, amid all the kingdoms of the earth: as a curse, and in stupor, and with hissing, and as a disgrace among all the nations to which I have driven them out.

19 For they have not listened to my words, says the Lord, which I sent to them through my servants, the prophets, rising while it was still night, and sending. But you have not listened, says the Lord.

20 Therefore, listen to the word of the Lord, all you of the transmigration, whom I have sent away from Jerusalem into Babylon.

21 Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel, to Ahab, the son of Kolaiah, and to Zedekiah, the son of Maaseiah, who prophesy falsely to you in my name: Behold, I will deliver them into the hands of Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, and he will strike them down before your eyes.

22 And a curse will be taken up about them, by all the captives of Judah that are in Babylon, saying: 'May the Lord make you like Zedekiah, and like Ahab, whom the king of Babylon fried in the fire!'

23 For they have acted foolishly in Israel, and they have committed adultery with the wives of their friends, and they have spoken lying words in my name, which I did not command them. I am the Judge and the Witness, says the Lord.

24 And to Shemaiah of Nehelam, you shall say:

25 Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: Similarly, you have sent letters in your name to all the people that are in Jerusalem, and to Zephaniah, the son of Maaseiah, the priest, and to all the priests, saying:

26 'The Lord has made you priest in place of Jehoiada, the priest, so that you would be the ruler in the house of the Lord over every man who raves and prophesies, to send him to the stocks and to prison.

27 And now why have you not rebuked Jeremiah of Anathoth, who prophesies to you?

28 For about this, he has sent to us in Babylon, saying: It is a long time. Build houses and live in them. And plant gardens, and eat from their fruits.' "

29 Thus, Zephaniah, the priest, read this letter, in the hearing of Jeremiah the prophet.

30 And the word of the Lord came to Jeremiah, saying:

31 "Send to all those of the transmigration, saying: Thus says the Lord to Shemaiah of Nehelam: Because Shemaiah has prophesied to you, though I did not send him, and because he has caused you to trust in a lie:

32 For this reason, thus says the Lord: Behold, I will visit upon Shemaiah of Nehelam, and upon his offspring. There will not be, for him, even one man sitting in the midst of this people. And he will not see the good that I will accomplish for my people, says the Lord. For he has spoken a betrayal against the Lord."

Jeremiah 30

1 This is the word that came to Jeremiah from the Lord, saying:

2 "Thus says the Lord, the God of Israel, saying: You shall write in a book all the words that I have spoken to you.

3 For behold, the days are approaching, says the Lord, when I will convert the turning away of my people, Israel and Judah, says the Lord. And I will return them to the land which I gave to their fathers, and they will possess it."

4 And these are the words which the Lord has spoken to Israel and to Judah:

5 For thus says the Lord: 'We have heard a voice of terror. There is dread, and there is no peace.'

6 Inquire and see, does a male give birth? Then why have I seen every man with his hand on his lower back, like a woman bearing a child? And why have all of their faces turned pale?

7 Woe! For that day is great, and there is nothing like it. For it is the time of tribulation for Jacob, but he will be saved from it.

8 And this shall be in that day, says the Lord of hosts: I will crush his yoke from your neck, and I will break open his bands. And strangers will no longer rule over him.

9 Instead, they will serve the Lord their God, and David their king, whom I will raise up for them.

10 Therefore, O my servant Jacob, you should not be afraid, says the Lord, and you should not be frightened, O Israel. For behold, I will save you from a far away land, and your offspring from the land of their captivity. And Jacob will return and have rest, and he shall flow with every good thing. And there will be no one for him to dread.

11 For I am with you, says the Lord, so that I may save you. For I will bring about the consummation of all the nations, among which I have scattered you. But I will not bring about your consummation. Instead, I will chastise you in judgment, so that you will not seem innocent to yourself."

12 For thus says the Lord: "Your fracture is incurable; your wound is very serious.

13 There is no one who may judge your judgment, so as to bandage it; there is no useful treatment for you.

14 All your lovers have forgotten you, and they will not seek you. For I have wounded you with the strike of an enemy, with a cruel chastisement. Your sins have become hardened because of the multitude of your iniquities.

15 Why do you cry out over your affliction? Your pain is incurable. I have done these things to you because of the multitude of your iniquity and because of your hardened sins.

16 Because of this, all those who devour you, will be devoured. And all your enemies will be led into captivity. And those who devastate you, will be devastated. And all those who prey upon you, I will offer as a prey.

17 For I will close up your scar, and I will heal you of your wounds, says the Lord. For they have called you an outcast, O Zion: 'This is she who has no one asking for her.' "

18 Thus says the Lord: "Behold, I will turn back the turning away of the tabernacles of Jacob, and I will take pity on his roofs. And the city will be built up in her heights, and the temple will be founded according to its order.

19 And praise will go forth from them, with the voice of those who play. And I will multiply them, and they will not be lessened. And I will glorify them, and they will not be weakened.

20 And their sons will be as in the beginning. And their assembly will remain in my sight. And I will visit against all those who trouble them.

21 And their ruler will one of their own. And their prince will be led forward from their midst. And I will draw him near, and he will cling to me. For who is the one who applies his heart, so that he may draw near to me, says the Lord?

22 And you shall be my people, and I will be your God."

23 Behold the whirlwind of the Lord, his fury going forth, a destroying storm! It will rest upon the head of the impious.

24 The Lord will not turn back the wrath of his indignation, until he has accomplished and completed the plan of his heart. In the last days, you shall understand these things.

Jeremiah 31

1 "In that time, says the Lord, I will be the God of all the families of Israel, and they will be my people."

2 Thus says the Lord: "The people who had remained after the sword, found grace in the desert. Israel will go to his rest."

3 The Lord appeared to me from a distance: "And I have loved you in perpetual charity. Therefore, showing pity, I have drawn you.

4 And I will build you up again. And you shall be built up, O virgin of Israel. Still shall you be adorned with your timbrels, and still shall you go forth to the singing of those who play.

5 Still shall you plant vineyards on the mountains of Samaria. The planters will plant, and they will not gather the vintage until the time arrives.

6 For there will be a day on which the guardians on mount Ephraim will cry out: 'Arise! And let us ascend on Zion to the Lord our God!' "

7 For thus says the Lord: "Exult in the joy of Jacob, and neigh before the head of the Gentiles. Shout, and sing, and say: 'O Lord, save your people, the remnant of Israel!'

8 Behold, I will lead them from the land of the north, and I will gather them from the ends of the earth. Among them will be the blind and the lame, she who is with child, together with she who is giving birth: a great assembly returning to this place.

9 They will approach with weeping. And I will lead them back with mercy. And I will lead them through the torrents of water, by an upright way, and they will not stumble in it. For I have become Father to Israel, and Ephraim is my firstborn."

10 Listen to the word of the Lord, O Gentiles, and announce it amid the islands that are far away, and say: "Whoever has scattered Israel will gather him, and he will guard him as a shepherd guards his flock."

11 For the Lord has redeemed Jacob, and he has freed him from the hand of one more powerful.

12 And they will arrive and give praise on Mount Zion. And they will flow together, to the good things of the Lord, over grain, and wine, and oil, and the offspring of cattle and herds. And their soul will be like an irrigated garden, and they will no longer be hungry.

13 Then the virgin will rejoice with singing, the young and the old together, and I will turn their mourning into gladness, and I will console them and gladden them after their sorrow.

14 And I will inebriate the soul of the priests with fatness, and my people will be filled with my good things, says the Lord."

15 Thus says the Lord: "A voice has been heard on high: of lamentation, mourning, and weeping; of Rachel crying for her sons and refusing to be consoled over them, because they are not."

16 Thus says the Lord: "Let your voice cease from crying and your eyes from tears. For there is a reward for your work, says the Lord. And they will return from the land of the enemy.

17 And there is hope for your very end, says the Lord. And the sons will return to their own borders.

18 Listening, I heard Ephraim going into captivity: 'You have chastised me, and I was instructed, like a young untamed bull. Convert me, and I shall be converted. For you are the Lord my God.

19 For after you converted me, I did penance. And after you revealed to me, I struck my thigh. I am confounded and ashamed. For I have endured the disgrace of my youth.'

20 Certainly, Ephraim is an honorable son to me; surely, he is a tender child. For I will still remember him, as in the time when I first spoke about him. Because my heart is stirred up over him, surely I will take pity on him, says the Lord.

21 Establish a watchtower for yourself. Place yourself in bitterness. Direct your heart into the upright way, in which you used to walk. Return, return, O virgin of Israel, to these your cities!

22 How long will you be absorbed in delights, O wandering daughter? For the Lord has created something new upon the earth: a woman will encompass a man."

23 Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: "Still they will speak this word in the land of Judah, and in its cities, when I will convert their captivity: 'May the Lord bless you, the beauty of justice, the holy mountain.'

24 And they will live in it: Judah together with all its cities, the farmer and those who drive the flocks.

25 For I have inebriated the weary soul, and I have satisfied every hungry soul.

26 Over this, I was awakened, as if from a deep sleep. And I saw, and my sleep became sweet to me.

27 Behold, the days are approaching, says the Lord, when I will sow the house of Israel and the house of Judah with the offspring of men and with the offspring of cattle.

28 And just as I have watched over them, so that I may root up, and tear down, and scatter, and destroy, and afflict, so will I watch over them, so that I may build and plant them, says the Lord.

29 In those days, they will no longer say: 'The fathers ate a bitter grape, and the teeth of the sons have been affected.'

30 Instead, each one will die for his own iniquity. Each man who will have eaten a bitter grape, his own teeth will be affected.

31 Behold, the days are approaching, says the Lord, when I will form a new covenant with the house of Israel and with the house of Judah,

32 not according to the covenant which I made with their fathers, in the day when I took them by the hand, so as to lead them away from the land of Egypt, the covenant which they nullified, though I was the ruler over them, says the Lord.

33 But this will be the covenant that I will form with the house of Israel, after those days, says the Lord: I will give my law to their inner most being, and I will write it upon their heart. And I will be their God, and they shall be my people.

34 And they will no longer teach, a man his neighbor, and a man his brother, saying: 'Know the Lord.' For all will know me, from the littlest of them even to the greatest, says the Lord. For I will forgive their iniquity, and I will no longer remember their sin.

35 Thus says the Lord, who gives the sun as the light of the day, who puts the moon and the stars in order as the light of the night, who stirs up the sea and makes its waves roar: the Lord of hosts is his name.

36 If these laws fail in my sight, says the Lord, then the offspring of Israel will also fail, so that they will not be a people in my sight for all time."

37 Thus says the Lord: "If the heavens above are able to be measured, and if the foundations of the earth beneath can be examined, I also will cast aside all the offspring of Israel, because of all that they have done, says the Lord.

38 Behold, the days are approaching, says the Lord, when a city will be built for the Lord from the tower of Hananel, even to the Gate of the Corner;

39 and the measuring line will go on even further in his sight, over the hill of Gareb, and it will encircle Goah

40 and the entire Valley of dead bodies and ashes, and the entire region of death, even to the torrent of Kedron, and to the corner of the Horse Gate to the east. All this will be the holy place of the Lord. It will not be rooted up, and it will not be torn down, anymore, forever."

Jeremiah 32

1 The word that came to Jeremiah from the Lord in the tenth year of Zedekiah, the king of Judah. The same is the eighteenth year of Nebuchadnezzar.

2 It was then that the army of the king of Babylon besieged Jerusalem. And Jeremiah, the prophet, was confined to the atrium of the prison, which was in the house of the king of Judah.

3 For Zedekiah, the king of Judah, had confined him, saying: "Why do you make predictions, saying: 'Thus says the Lord: Behold, I will give this city into the hand of the king of Babylon, and he will capture it?

4 And Zedekiah, the king of Judah, will not escape from the hand of the Chaldeans. Instead, he will be delivered into the hands of the king of Babylon. And he will speak to him, mouth to mouth, and he will see him, eye to eye.

5 And he will lead Zedekiah to Babylon. And he will be there until I visit him, says the Lord. So then, if you contend against the Chaldeans, you will have no success.' "

6 And Jeremiah said: "The word of the Lord came to me, saying:

7 Behold, Hanamel, the son of Shallum, your cousin, will come to you, saying: 'Buy for yourself my field, which is in Anathoth. For it is your right, as next of kin, to buy it.'

8 And in accord with the word of the Lord, Hanamel, the son of my uncle, came to me, to the entrance of the prison, and he said to me: 'Take possession of my field, which is in Anathoth in the land of Benjamin. For the right of inheritance is yours, and as the next of kin you may possess it.' Then I understood that this was the word of the Lord.

9 And I bought the field, which is in Anathoth, from Hanamel, the son of my uncle. And I weighed out the money to him, seven small coins and ten pieces of silver.

10 And I wrote it in a book and signed it, and I summoned witnesses. And I weighed out the silver on a scale.

11 And I received the signed deed of possession, and the stipulations, and the ratifications, with the exterior seals.

12 And I gave the deed of possession to Baruch, the son of Neriah, the son of Mahseiah, in the sight of Hanamel, the son of my uncle, in the sight of the witnesses who had been recorded in the book of the purchase, and in the sight of all the Jews who were sitting in the atrium of the prison.

13 And I instructed Baruch, in their sight, saying:

14 Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: 'Take these writings, this sealed deed of purchase, and this deed which is open, and place them in an earthen vessel, so that they will be preserved for many days.'

15 For thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: 'Houses, and fields, and vineyards will be possessed still, in this land.'

16 And after I had delivered the deed of possession to Baruch, the son of Neri, I prayed to the Lord, saying:

17 Alas, alas, alas, O Lord God! Behold, you have made heaven and earth, by your great strength and by your outstretched arm. No word is difficult for you.

18 You act with mercy a thousand-fold, but you repay the iniquity of the fathers into the sinews of their sons after them. The Lord of hosts is your name: most strong, great, and powerful!

19 You are great in counsel and incomprehensible in thought. Your eyes are open upon all the ways of the sons of Adam, so that you may repay each one according to his ways and according to the fruit of his intentions.

20 You caused signs and portents in the land of Egypt, and in Israel, and among men, even until this day. And you have made a name for yourself, just as in this day.

21 And you have led your people Israel away from the land of Egypt, with signs and portents, and with a robust hand and an outstretched arm, and with great terror.

22 And you have given them this land, which you swore, to their fathers, that you would give to them, a land flowing with milk and honey.

23 And they entered it and possessed it. But they did not obey your voice, and they did not walk in your law. And they did not do all of the things that you commanded them to do. And so, all of these evils have happened to them.

24 Behold, fortifications were built against the city, so as to capture it. And the city was given into the hands of the Chaldeans, who fight against it, before the face of the sword, and of famine, and of pestilence. And what you have spoken has occurred, just as you yourself discern.

25 So why, O Lord God, are you saying to me: 'Buy a field with money, and summon witnesses,' while the city is being given into the hands of the Chaldeans?"

26 And the word of the Lord came to Jeremiah, saying:

27 "Behold, I am the Lord God; I am above all flesh. Can any word be difficult for me?

28 Therefore, thus says the Lord: Behold, I will deliver this city into the hands of the Chaldeans, and into the hands of the king of Babylon, and they will capture it.

29 And the Chaldeans fighting against this city will advance, and set fire to it, and burn it, along with the houses on whose roofs they were offering sacrifice to Baal and were pouring out libations to strange gods, so that they provoked me to wrath.

30 For the sons of Israel and the sons of Judah, from their youth, have continually done evil in my eyes. The sons of Israel, even until now, have been provoking me with the work of their hands, says the Lord.

31 For this city has been a cause of fury and indignation to me, from the day when they built it, until this day, in which it will be taken away from my sight,

32 because of all the wickedness of the sons of Israel and the sons of Judah, which they have done, provoking me to wrath, they and their kings, their leaders and their priests and their prophets, the men of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem.

33 And they have turned their backs to me, and not their faces. And though I taught them and instructed them, rising at first light, they were not willing to listen, so that they would receive discipline.

34 And they have placed their idols in the house where my name is invoked, so that they defiled it.

35 And they have built the exalted places of Baal, which are in the valley of the son of Hinnom, so that they may initiate their sons and their daughters into Molech, though I did not command, nor did it enter into my heart, that they should do this abomination, and so lead Judah into sin.

36 And now, because of these things, thus says the Lord, the God of Israel, to this city, about which you say that it will be delivered into the hands of the king of Babylon by the sword, and by famine, and by pestilence:

37 Behold, I will gather them together from all the lands to which I have cast them out in my fury, and in my wrath, and in my great indignation. And I will lead them back to this place, and I will cause them to live in confidence.

38 And they will be my people, and I will be their God.

39 And I will give to them one heart and one way, so that they may fear me all their days, and so that it may be well with them, and with their sons after them.

40 And I will form an everlasting covenant with them, and I will not cease to do good for them. And I will put my fear into their heart, so that they do not withdraw from me.

41 And I will rejoice over them, while I do good for them. And I will plant them in this land, in truth, with my whole heart and with my whole soul.

42 For thus says the Lord: Just as I have led over this people all this great evil, so will I lead over them all the good that I am speaking to them now.

43 And fields will be possessed in this land, about which you say that it is desolate because there remains neither man nor beast, and because it has been given into the hands of the Chaldeans.

44 Fields will be bought for money, and deeds will be written and signed, and witnesses will be summoned, in the land of Benjamin and all around Jerusalem, in the cities of Judah, and in the cities on the mountains, and in the cities on the plains, and in the cities that are toward the south. For I will convert their captivity, says the Lord."

Jeremiah 33

1 And the word of the Lord came to Jeremiah a second time, while he was still confined to the atrium of the prison, saying:

2 "Thus says the Lord, who will prepare, and form, and accomplish it; the Lord is his name.

3 Cry out to me and I will heed you. And I will announce to you great things, things that are certain, though you do not know them.

4 For thus says the Lord, the God of Israel, to the houses of this city, and to the houses of the king of Judah, which have been destroyed, and to the fortifications, and to the sword

5 of those who have arrived, so that they may fight with the Chaldeans, and so that they may have their fill of the dead bodies of the men whom I have struck down in my fury and in my indignation, concealing my face from this city, because of all their wickedness:

6 Behold, I will lead over them scars and health, and I will cure them. And I will reveal to them an invocation of peace and truth.

7 And I will convert the turning away of Judah and the turning away of Jerusalem. And I will build them up, just as from the beginning.

8 And I will cleanse them from all their iniquity, by which they have sinned against me. And I will forgive all their iniquities, by which they have offended against me and have despised me.

9 And this will be for me: a name, and a joy, and a praise, and an exultation, among all the nations of the earth who will hear about all the good things that I will accomplish for them. And they will be afraid and troubled over all these good things, and over all the peace, that I will accomplish for them.

10 Thus says the Lord: Still shall there be heard in this place, (which you say is desolate, because there is neither man nor beast,) and in the cities of Judah and outside of Jerusalem, (which are desolate, without man, and without an inhabitant and without cattle,)

11 the voice of gladness and the voice of rejoicing, the voice of the groom and the voice of the bride, the voice of those who will say: 'Confess to the Lord of hosts! For the Lord is good! For his mercy is eternal!' and the voice of those fulfilling their vows in the house of the Lord. For I will lead back the turning away of the land, just as from the beginning, says the Lord."

12 Thus says the Lord of hosts: "Still shall there be in this place, (which is desolate without man and without beast,) and in all of its cities: a habitation for the shepherds giving rest to their flocks.

13 For even in the cities on the mountains, and in the cities on the plains, and in the cities that are toward the south, and in the land of Benjamin, and all around Jerusalem, and in the cities of Judah, still shall the flocks travel by the hand of him who numbers them, says the Lord.

14 Behold, the days are approaching, says the Lord, when I will fulfill the good word that I have spoken to the house of Israel and to the house of Judah.

15 In those days and at that time, I will cause the seedling of justice to spring up from David, and he will accomplish judgment and justice upon the earth.

16 In those days, Judah will be saved, and Jerusalem will live in confidence. And this is the name that they will call him: 'The Lord, our Just One.'

17 For thus says the Lord: There shall not cease to be a man from David sitting upon the throne of the house of Israel.

18 And there shall not cease to be a man from the priests and from the Levites before my face, who offers holocausts, and burns sacrifices, and kills victims, for days without end."

19 And the word of the Lord came to Jeremiah, saying:

20 "Thus says the Lord: If my covenant with the day is able to be nullified, or my covenant with the night, such that there would be no day and no night in their time,

21 then, too, my covenant with David, my servant, may be nullified, such that he would not have a son who reigns upon his throne, with both the Levites and the priests as my ministers.

22 Just as the stars of heaven are not able to be numbered, and the sand of the sea is not able to be measured, so will I multiply the offspring of David, my servant, and the Levites, my ministers."

23 And the word of the Lord came to Jeremiah, saying:

24 "Have you not seen what this people has spoken? They say: 'The two families which the Lord had chosen have been rejected.' And so they have despised my people, as if they were no longer a nation in their sight.

25 Thus says the Lord: If I have not established my covenant with the day and the night, and my laws over heaven and earth,

26 then truly I will also cast aside the offspring of Jacob, and of David, my servant, so that I do not take up any of his offspring to be leaders over the offspring of Abraham, Isaac, and Jacob. For I will lead back their turning way, and I will take pity on them."

Jeremiah 34

1 The word that came to Jeremiah from the Lord, when Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, and his entire army, and all the kingdoms of the earth that were under the authority of his hand, and all the people were making war against Jerusalem and against all of its cities, saying:

2 "Thus says the Lord, the God of Israel: Go, and speak to Zedekiah, the king of Judah. And you shall say to him: Thus says the Lord: Behold, I will deliver this city into the hands of the king of Babylon, and he will burn it with fire.

3 And you will not escape from his hand. Instead, you will be overtaken and captured, and you will be delivered into his hand. And your eyes will see the eyes of the king of Babylon, and his mouth will speak with your mouth, and you will enter into Babylon.

4 Even so, listen to the word of the Lord, Zedekiah, king of Judah: Thus says the Lord to you: You will not die by the sword.

5 Instead, you will die in peace. And, in accord with the burnings of your fathers, the former kings who were before you, so will they burn you. And they will mourn you, saying: 'Alas, lord!' For I have spoken the word, says the Lord."

6 And Jeremiah, the prophet, spoke all these words to Zedekiah, the king of Judah, in Jerusalem.

7 And the army of the king of Babylon fought against Jerusalem and against all the cities of Judah that remained, against Lachish and against Azekah. For only these remained out of the cities of Judah that were fortified cities.

8 The word that came to Jeremiah from the Lord, after king Zedekiah had struck a pact with all the people in Jerusalem, proclaiming

9 that each one should release his man servant, and each one his woman servant, as a free Hebrew man and a free Hebrew woman, and that they should never be rulers over them, that is, over the Jews, their own brothers.

10 Then all the leaders and all the people who entered into the pact, heard that each one should release his man servant, and each one his woman servant, to be free, and that they should no longer rule over them. Therefore, they listened, and they released them.

11 But later on, they turned back. And they took back again their man servants and their woman servants, whom they had released to be free. And they subjugated them as male and female servants.

12 And the word of the Lord came to Jeremiah from the Lord, saying:

13 "Thus says the Lord, the God of Israel: I struck a pact with your fathers in the day when I led them away from the land of Egypt, from the house of servitude, saying:

14 'When seven years have been completed, let each one release his brother, a Hebrew, who had been sold to him. And so he will serve you for six years, and then you shall release him to be free from you.' But your fathers did not listen to me, nor did they incline their ear.

15 And today you converted, and you did what is right in my eyes, so that you proclaimed liberty, each one to his friend. And you entered into a pact in my sight, in the house in which and over which my name is invoked.

16 But now you have turned back, and you have stained my name. For you have led back again, each one his man servant, and each one his woman servant, whom you had released so that they would be free and under their own authority. And you have subjugated them, so that they would be your servants and handmaids."

17 Because of this, thus says the Lord: "You have not heeded me, though you proclaimed liberty, each one to his brother and each one to his friend. Behold, I am proclaiming a liberty for you, says the Lord, to the sword, to pestilence, and to famine. And I will cause you to be removed to all the kingdoms of the earth.

18 And I will give over the men who have betrayed my covenant, and who have not observed the words of the covenant, to which they assented in my sight when they cut the calf into two parts and passed between its parts:

19 the leaders of Judah, and the leaders of Jerusalem, the eunuchs and the priests, and all the people of the land, who have passed between the parts of the calf.

20 And I will give them into the hands of their enemies and into the hands of those who are seeking their life. And their dead bodies will be food for the birds of the air and for the beasts of the earth.

21 And Zedekiah, the king of Judah, and his leaders, I will give over to the hands of their enemies, and to the hands of those who are seeking their lives, and to the hands of the armies of the king of Babylon, which had withdrawn from you.

22 Behold, I will command, says the Lord, and I will lead them back to this city, and they will fight against it, and seize it, and set it on fire. And I will make the cities of Judah into a desolation, for there shall be no inhabitant."

Jeremiah 35

1 The word that came to Jeremiah from the Lord in the days of Jehoiakim, the son of Josiah, the king of Judah, saying:

2 "Go to the house of the Rechabites, and speak to them, and lead them into the house of the Lord, into one of the halls of the treasuries. And you shall give them wine to drink."

3 And so I took Jaazaniah, the son of Jeremiah, the son of Habazziniah, and his brothers, and all his sons, and the entire house of the Rechabites,

4 and I led them into the house of the Lord, to the treasury of the sons of Hanan, the son of Igdaliah, a man of God, which was near the treasury of the princes, above the storehouse of Maaseiah, the son of Shallum, who was the guardian of the entrance.

5 And I placed before the sons of the house of the Rechabites bowls filled with wine, and chalices. And I said to them, "Drink wine."

6 And they responded: "We will not drink wine. For Jonadab, the son of Rechab, our father, instructed us, saying: 'You shall not drink wine, you and your sons, in perpetuity.

7 And you shall not build houses, and you shall not sow any seeds, and you shall not plant or have vineyards. Instead, you shall live in tents all your days, so that you may live many days upon the face of the earth, in which you are sojourners.'

8 Therefore, we have obeyed the voice of Jonadab, the son of Rechab, our father, in all that he has commanded us, so that we do not drink wine all our days, we and our wives, our sons and daughters.

9 And we do not build houses in which to live. And we do not have vineyard, or field, or seed to sow.

10 Instead, we live in tents, and we have been obedient in accord with all that Jonadab, our father, has instructed us.

11 But when Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, had ascended to our land, we said: 'Come and let us enter into Jerusalem, before the face of the army of the Chaldeans, and before the face of the army of Syria.' And we have remained in Jerusalem."

12 And the word of the Lord came to Jeremiah, saying:

13 "Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: Go, and say to the men of Judah and to the inhabitants of Jerusalem: Will you not accept discipline, so that you obey my words, says the Lord?

14 The words of Jonadab, the son of Rechab, in which he instructed his sons, so that they would not drink wine, have prevailed. And they have not drunk wine, even to this day. For they have obeyed the instruction of their father. But I have spoken to you, rising and speaking from early morning, and you did not obey me.

15 And I have sent to you all my servants, the prophets, rising at first light, and sending, and saying: 'Convert, each one from his wicked way, and make your intentions good. And do not choose to follow strange gods, nor shall you worship them. And then you shall live in the land which I gave to you and to your fathers.' And yet you have not inclined your ear, and you have not heeded me.

16 So the sons of Jonadab, the son of Rechab, have remained firm in the commandment of their father, which he instructed to them, while this people has not been obedient to me.

17 For this reason, thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: Behold, I will lead over Judah and over all the inhabitants of Jerusalem, every evil that I have declared against them. For I have spoken to them, and they have not listened. I have called to them, and they have not responded to me."

18 Then Jeremiah said to the house of the Rechabites: "Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: Because you have obeyed the commandment of Jonadab, your father, and have kept all his precepts, and have done all that he has instructed you,

19 because of this, thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: There will not be a man lacking from the stock of Jonadab, the son of Rechab, standing in my sight, for all days."

Jeremiah 36

1 And it happened in the fourth year of Jehoiakim, the son of Josiah, the king of Judah: it happened that this word came to Jeremiah from the Lord, saying:

2 "Take the volume of a book, and you shall write in it all the words that I have spoken to you against Israel and Judah, and against all the nations, from the day when I first spoke to you, from the days of Josiah, even to this day.

3 Perhaps it may be that the house of Judah, upon hearing all the evils that I have decided to do to them, may return, each one from his wicked way, and then I will forgive their iniquity and their sin."

4 Therefore, Jeremiah called Baruch, the son of Neriah, and Baruch wrote, from the mouth of Jeremiah, all the words of the Lord, which he had spoken to him, in the volume of a book.

5 And Jeremiah instructed Baruch, saying: "I am confined, and so I am unable to enter into the house of the Lord.

6 Therefore, you shall enter and read from the volume, in which you have written from my mouth the words of the Lord, in the hearing of the people in the house of the Lord on the day of the fast. Moreover, you shall also read them in the hearing of all those of Judah who are arriving from their cities.

7 Perhaps it may happen that they pray in the sight of the Lord, and each one may return from his wicked way. For great is the fury and indignation that the Lord has declared against this people."

8 And Baruch, the son of Neriah, acted in accord with all that Jeremiah, the prophet, had instructed him, reading from the volume the words of the Lord, in the house of the Lord.

9 And it happened that, in the fifth year of Jehoiakim, the son of Josiah, the king of Judah, in the ninth month, they proclaimed a fast, in the sight of the Lord, to all the people in Jerusalem, and to the entire multitude which had flowed together, from the cities of Judah, into Jerusalem.

10 And Baruch read from the volume the words of Jeremiah in the house of the Lord, at the treasury of Gemariah, the son of Shaphan, the scribe, in the upper vestibule, at the entrance to the new gate of the house of the Lord, in the hearing of all the people.

11 And when Micaiah, the son of Gemariah, the son of Shaphan, had heard all the words of the Lord from the book,

12 he descended to the house of the king, to the treasury of the scribe. And behold, all the leaders were sitting there: Elishama, the scribe, and Delaiah, the son of Shemaiah, and Elnathan, the son of Achbor, and Gemariah, the son of Shaphan, and Zedekiah, the son of Hananiah, and all the leaders.

13 And Micaiah announced to them all the words that he had heard when Baruch read from the volume to the ears of the people.

14 And so, all the leaders sent Jehudi, the son of Nethaniah, the son of Shelemiah, the son of Cushi, to Baruch, saying, "Take in your hand the volume, from which you have read in the hearing of the people, and come." Therefore, Baruch, the son of Neriah, took the volume in his hand, and he went to them.

15 And they said to him, "Sit and read these things in our hearing." And Baruch read in their hearing.

16 Therefore, when they had heard all the words, each one looked at his neighbor in astonishment, and they said to Baruch: "We ought to report all these words to the king."

17 And they questioned him, saying, "Describe to us how you wrote all these words from his mouth."

18 Then Baruch said to them: "He was speaking with his mouth, as if reading to me. And I wrote in a volume with ink."

19 And the leaders said to Baruch: "Go away and hide, you and Jeremiah, and let no one know where you are."

20 And they entered to the king, in the court. Furthermore, they stored the volume in the treasury of Elishama, the scribe. And they announced all the words in the hearing of the king.

21 And the king sent Jehudi to take the volume. And bringing it from the treasury of Elishama, the scribe, he read it in the hearing of the king and of all the leaders who were standing around the king.

22 Now the king was sitting in the winter house, in the ninth month. And there was a hearth placed before him, filled with burning coals.

23 And when Jehudi had read three or four pages, he cut it with a small knife, and he threw it into the fire which was upon the hearth, until the entire volume was consumed by the fire which was upon the hearth.

24 And the king and all his servants, who had heard all these words, were not afraid, and they did not rend their garments.

25 Yet truly, Elnathan, and Delaiah, and Gemariah contradicted the king, so that he might not burn the book. But he did not listen to them.

26 And the king instructed Jerahmeel, the son of Amelech, and Seraiah, the son of Azriel, and Shelemiah, the son of Abdeel, so that they would apprehend Baruch, the scribe, and Jeremiah, the prophet. But the Lord concealed them.

27 And after the king had burned the volume and the words that Baruch had written from the mouth of Jeremiah, the word of the Lord came to Jeremiah, the prophet, saying:

28 "Again, take another volume and write in it all the former words, which were in the first volume that Jehoiakim, the king of Judah, has burned.

29 And you shall say to Jehoiakim, the king of Judah: Thus says the Lord: You have burned that volume, saying: 'Why have you written in it, announcing that the king of Babylon will advance quickly, and will devastate this land, and will cause both man and beast to cease from it?'

30 Because of this, thus says the Lord against Jehoiakim, the king of Judah: There will be, from him, no one who may sit upon the throne of David. And his dead body shall be cast out: to the heat by day, and to the frost by night.

31 And I will visit against him, and against his offspring, and against his servants for their iniquities. And I will lead over them, and over the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and over the men of Judah, all the evil that I have declared against them, for they have not listened."

32 Then Jeremiah took up another volume, and he gave it to Baruch, the son of Neriah, the scribe, who wrote in it, from the mouth of Jeremiah, all the words of the book that Jehoiakim, the king of Judah, had burned with fire. And moreover, there were many more words added than there had been before.

Jeremiah 37

1 And then king Zedekiah, the son of Josiah, reigned in place of Jeconiah, the son of Jehoiakim. For Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, appointed him as king in the land of Judah.

2 And neither he himself, nor his servants, nor the people of the land, obeyed the words of the Lord, which he spoke by the hand of Jeremiah, the prophet.

3 And king Zedekiah sent Jehucal, the son of Shelemiah, and Zephaniah, the son of Maaseiah, the priest, to Jeremiah the prophet, saying: "Pray to the Lord our God for us."

4 Now Jeremiah was walking freely in the midst of the people. For they had not yet sent him into the custody of the prison. And then the army of Pharaoh went forth from Egypt. And hearing this, the Chaldeans, who were besieging Jerusalem, withdrew from Jerusalem.

5 And the word of the Lord came to Jeremiah the prophet, saying:

6 "Thus says the Lord, the God of Israel: So shall you say to the king of Judah, who sent you to question me: Behold, the army of Pharaoh, which has gone forth in assistance to you, will return to their own land, into Egypt.

7 And the Chaldeans will return and will make war against this city. And they will seize it and burn it with fire.

8 Thus says the Lord: Do not be willing to deceive your own souls, saying: 'The Chaldeans will certainly withdraw and go away from us.' For they will not go away.

9 But even if you were to strike down the entire army of the Chaldeans who are fighting against you, and if there were left behind from among them only a few wounded men, they would rise up, each one from his tent, and they would burn this city with fire."

10 Therefore, when the army of the Chaldeans had withdrawn from Jerusalem because of Pharaoh's army,

11 Jeremiah went forth from Jerusalem, to go into the land of Benjamin, and to distribute a possession there, in the sight of the citizens.

12 And when he had arrived at the gate of Benjamin, the keeper of the gate, whose turn it was to be there, was named Irijah, the son of Shelemiah, the son of Hananiah. And he apprehended Jeremiah the prophet, saying, "You are fleeing to the Chaldeans."

13 And Jeremiah responded: "That is false. I am not fleeing to the Chaldeans." But he did not listen to him. And so Irijah took Jeremiah, and he brought him to the leaders.

14 Therefore, the leaders were angry with Jeremiah, and so they beat him and sent him to the prison that was in the house of Jonathan, the scribe. For he was the chief over the prison.

15 And so Jeremiah went into the house of the prison and into a dungeon. And Jeremiah sat there for many days.

16 Then Zedekiah the king, sending, took him out and questioned him secretly in his house, and he said: "Do you think that there is any word from the Lord?" And Jeremiah said: "There is." And he said: "You will be delivered into the hands of the king of Babylon."

17 And Jeremiah said to king Zedekiah: "How have I sinned against you, or your servants, or your people, such that you would cast me into a house of imprisonment?

18 Where are your prophets, who were prophesying to you, and who were saying: 'The king of Babylon will not overwhelm you and this land?'

19 Now therefore, listen, I beg you, my lord the king. Let my petition prevail in your sight. And do not send me back into the house of Jonathan the scribe, lest I die there."

20 Then king Zedekiah instructed that Jeremiah be confined to the vestibule of the prison, and that they should give him a twist of bread daily, along with stew, until all the bread in the city had been consumed. And Jeremiah remained at the entrance of the prison.

Jeremiah 38

1 Then Shephatiah, the son of Mattan, and Gedaliah, the son of Pashhur, and Jehucal, the son of Shelemiah, and Pashhur, the son of Malchiah, heard the words that Jeremiah was speaking to all the people, saying:

2 "Thus says the Lord: Whoever will remain in this city will die by the sword, and by famine, and by pestilence. But whoever will flee away from the Chaldeans, will live, and his soul will dwell in safety.

3 Thus says the Lord: This city will certainly be delivered into the hand of the army of the king of Babylon, and he will capture it."

4 And the leaders said to the king: "We petition you to put this man to death. For he is deliberately weakening the hands of the men of war, who have remained in this city, and the hands of the people, by speaking to them with these words. For this man is certainly not seeking peace for this people, but evil."

5 And king Zedekiah said: "Behold, he is in your hands. For it is not fitting for the king to deny you anything."

6 Therefore, they took Jeremiah and cast him into the pit of Malchiah, the son of Amelech, which was at the entrance to the prison. And they lowered Jeremiah by ropes into the pit, in which there was no water, but only mud. And so Jeremiah descended into the mire.

7 Now Ebedmelech, an Ethiopian man, a eunuch who was in the king's house, heard that they had sent Jeremiah into the pit, and also that the king was sitting at the gate of Benjamin.

8 And so Ebedmelech departed from the king's house, and he spoke to the king, saying:

9 "My lord the king, these men have done evil in all that they have perpetrated against Jeremiah the prophet, casting him into the pit so that he would die there from famine. For there is no more bread in the city."

10 And so the king instructed Ebedmelech, the Ethiopian, saying: "Take with you thirty men from here, and lift Jeremiah the prophet from the pit, before he dies."

11 Therefore, Ebedmelech, taking the men with him, entered into the king's house to a place below the storehouse. And he took from there old garments, no longer in use, and he sent them down by rope to Jeremiah in the pit.

12 And Ebedmelech, the Ethiopian, said to Jeremiah: "Place these old garments, and these cut and decaying cloths, under your arms and over the ropes." And Jeremiah did so.

13 And they pulled up Jeremiah with the ropes, and they led him away from the pit. And Jeremiah remained in the vestibule of the prison.

14 And king Zedekiah sent and took Jeremiah the prophet to him at the third gate, which was at the house of the Lord. And the king said to Jeremiah: "I will question you about a matter. You shall conceal nothing from me."

15 Then Jeremiah said to Zedekiah: "If I announce to you, will you not put me to death? And if I give you counsel, you will not listen to me."

16 Then king Zedekiah swore to Jeremiah, secretly, saying: "As the Lord lives, who made this soul for us, I will not kill you, nor will I deliver you into the hands of those men who are seeking your life."

17 And Jeremiah said to Zedekiah: "Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: If, having set out, you go to the rulers of the king of Babylon, your soul will live, and this city will not be burned with fire. And you and your house will be safe.

18 But if you will not go to the rulers of the king of Babylon, this city will be delivered into the hands of the Chaldeans, and they will burn it with fire. And you will not escape from their hand."

19 And king Zedekiah said to Jeremiah: "I am anxious, because of the Jews who have crossed over to the Chaldeans, lest perhaps I may be delivered into their hands, and they may abuse me."

20 But Jeremiah responded: "They will not deliver you. Listen, I ask you, to the voice of the Lord, which I am speaking to you, and it will be well with you, and your soul will live.

21 But if you refuse to depart, this is the word that the Lord has revealed to me:

22 Behold, all the women who remain in the house of the king of Judah will be led away to the rulers of the king of Babylon. And the women will say: 'Your men of peacefulness have led you astray, and they have prevailed against you. They have immersed your feet in mud and have set them in a slippery place. And they have withdrawn from you.'

23 And all your wives and your sons will be led away to the Chaldeans, and you will not escape from their hands. Instead, you will be seized by the hand of the king of Babylon. And he will burn this city with fire."

24 Then Zedekiah said to Jeremiah: "Let no one know of these words, and you will not die.

25 But if the leaders hear that I have spoken with you, and if they come to you, and say to you: 'Tell us what you said to the king. Do not conceal it from us, and we will not put you to death. And tell us what the king said to you,'

26 then you shall say to them: 'I presented my supplication before the king, so that he would not order me to be led back to the house of Jonathan, to die there.' "

27 Then all the leaders came to Jeremiah, and they questioned him. And he spoke to them in accord with all the words that the king had commanded him. And they withdrew from him, for they had learned nothing.

28 Yet truly, Jeremiah remained at the entrance of the prison, until the day when Jerusalem was seized. And it happened that Jerusalem was captured.

Jeremiah 39

1 In the ninth year of Zedekiah, the king of Judah, in the tenth month, Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, came to Jerusalem, with his entire army, and they besieged it.

2 Then, in the eleventh year of Zedekiah, in the fourth month, on the fifth of the month, the city was opened.

3 And all the rulers of the king of Babylon entered and were seated at the middle gate: Nergal-Sharezer, the priest of Nebo, Sarsechim, the chief eunuch, Nergal-Sharezer, the chief magi, and all the other rulers of the king of Babylon.

4 And when Zedekiah, the king of Judah, with all the men of war, had seen them, they fled. And they departed from the city at night, by way of the king's garden, and through the gate which was between the two walls. And they departed along the way of the desert.

5 But the army of the Chaldeans pursued them. And they overtook Zedekiah in the plain of the desert of Jericho. And having captured him, they led him to Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, at Riblah, which is in the land of Hamath. And he declared a judgment against him

6 And the king of Babylon killed the sons of Zedekiah, at Riblah, before his eyes. And the king of Babylon killed all the nobles of Judah.

7 Also, he plucked out the eyes of Zedekiah. And he bound him with fetters, to be led away to Babylon.

8 Also, the Chaldeans burned the house of the king and the house of the people with fire, and they overturned the wall of Jerusalem.

9 And Nebuzaradan, the leader of the military, carried away captive to Babylon the remnant of the people who had remained in the city, and the fugitives who had fled to him, and all the rest of the people who had remained.

10 And Nebuzaradan, the leader of the military, released some of the poor people, those who had almost nothing, into the land of Judah. And he gave them vineyards and cisterns in that day.

11 Now Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, had instructed Nebuzaradan, the leader of the military, about Jeremiah, saying:

12 "Take him, and set your eyes on him, and you shall do no harm to him at all. But as he is willing, so shall you do with him."

13 Therefore, Nebuzaradan, the leader of the military, sent, and Nebushazban, the chief eunuch, and Nergal-Sharezer, the chief magi, and all the nobles of the king of Babylon sent,

14 and they took Jeremiah from the vestibule of the prison, and they delivered him to Gedaliah, the son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, so that he could enter a house and live among the people.

15 But the word of the Lord had come to Jeremiah, when he had been confined to the vestibule of the prison, saying: "Go, and speak to Ebedmelech, the Ethiopian, saying:

16 Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: Behold, I will bring my words over this city for evil, and not for good; and they shall be in your sight in that day.

17 And I will free you in that day, says the Lord. And you will not be delivered into the hands of the men whom you dread.

18 But when delivering, I will free you. And you will not fall by the sword. Instead, your life will be saved for you, because you had faith in me, says the Lord."

Jeremiah 40

1 The word that came to Jeremiah from the Lord, after Nebuzaradan, the leader of the military, had released him from Ramah, where he had taken him, bound in chains, along with all those who were being carried away from Jerusalem and from Judah, and were being led to Babylon.

2 Therefore, the leader of the military, taking Jeremiah, said to him: "The Lord your God has declared this evil over this place,

3 and he has brought it. And the Lord has done just as he has spoken. For you have sinned against the Lord, and you have not heeded his voice, and so this word has happened to you.

4 Now therefore, behold, I have released you this day from the chains which were on your hands. If it pleases you to come with me into Babylon, then come. And I will set my eyes upon you. But if it displeases you to come with me into Babylon, then remain. Behold, all the land is in your sight. Whatever you will choose, and wherever it will please you to go, so shall you go, proceeding to that place.

5 And you may decline to come with me. For you may live with Gedaliah, the son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, whom the king of Babylon has made governor over the cities of Judah. Therefore, you may live with him in the midst of the people. And you may go wherever it will please you to go." And the leader of the military also gave him foods and gifts, and he released him.

6 Then Jeremiah went to Gedaliah, the son of Ahikam, at Mizpah. And he lived with him in the midst of the people, those who had been left behind in the land.

7 And when all the leaders of the army, who had been dispersed throughout the regions, they and their associates, had heard that the king of Babylon had made Gedaliah, the son of Ahikam, governor of the land, and that he had committed to him the men, and women, and children, and the poor of the land, who had not been carried away to Babylon,

8 they went to Gedaliah at Mizpah, with Ishmael, the son of Nethaniah, and Johanan and Jonathan, the sons of Kareah, and Seraiah, the son of Tanhumeth, and the sons of Ephai, who were of Netophathi, and Jezaniah, the son of Maacathi, they and their men.

9 And Gedaliah, the son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, swore to them and to their companions, saying: "Do not be afraid to serve the Chaldeans. Live in the land, and serve the king of Babylon, and it will be well with you.

10 Behold, I live at Mizpah, so that I may follow the instruction of the Chaldeans who are sent to us. But as for you, gather the vintage, and the harvest, and the oil, and store it up in your vessels, and dwell in your cities, which you hold."

11 So then, all the Jews, who were in Moab, and among the sons of Ammon, and in Idumea, and in all the regions, when they had heard that the king of Babylon had left a remnant in Judea, and that he had made Gedaliah, the son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, governor over them,

12 all the Jews, I say, returned from all the places to which they had fled, and they came into the land of Judah, to Gedaliah at Mizpah. And they gathered wine and an exceedingly great harvest.

13 Then Johanan, the son of Kareah, and all the leaders of the army, who had been dispersed in the regions, came to Gedaliah at Mizpah.

14 And they said to him: "Know that Baalis, the king of the sons of Ammon, has sent Ishmael, the son of Nethaniah, to strike down your life." And Gedaliah, the son of Ahikam, did not believe them.

15 But Johanan, the son of Kareah, spoke to Gedaliah, separately, at Mizpah, saying: "I will go, and I will strike down Ishmael, the son of Nethaniah, without anyone knowing; otherwise he may kill you, and all the Jews will be scattered who have been gathered to you, and the remnant of Judah will perish."

16 And Gedaliah, the son of Ahikam, said to Johanan, the son of Kareah: "Do not do this word. For what you have said about Ishmael is false."

Jeremiah 41

1 And it happened that, in the seventh month, Ishmael, the son of Nethaniah, the son of Elishama of royal descent, with the nobles of the king, and accompanied by ten men, went to Gedaliah, the son of Ahikam, at Mizpah. And they ate bread together there, in Mizpah.

2 Then Ishmael, the son of Nethaniah, rose up, and the ten men who were with him, and they struck down Gedaliah, the son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, with the sword, and they killed him whom the king of Babylon had made governor over the land.

3 Likewise, Ishmael struck down all the Jews who were with Gedaliah at Mizpah, with the Chaldeans who were found there, and the men of war.

4 Then, on the second day after he had killed Gedaliah, while no one yet knew of it,

5 men arrived from Shechem, and from Shiloh, and from Samaria, eighty men, with their beards shaved, and their garments rent, and unbathed. And they had gifts and frankincense in hand, so that they might make an offering in the house of the Lord.

6 Therefore, Ishmael, the son of Nethaniah, departing from Mizpah to meet them, went forth weeping as he was walking. And when he had met them, he said to them, "Come to Gedaliah, the son of Ahikam."

7 And when they had arrived at the center of the city, Ishmael, the son of Nethaniah, put them to death around the public cistern, he and the men who were with him.

8 But ten men were found among them, who said to Ishmael: "Do not kill us! For in the field we have storehouses of grain and barley and oil and honey." And so he ceased, and he did not put them to death with their brothers.

9 Now the cistern, into which Ishmael cast all the dead bodies of the men whom he had struck down because of Gedaliah, is the same one that king Asa made out of fear of Baasha, the king of Israel. This same cistern Ishmael, the son of Nethaniah, filled with those who were slain.

10 Then Ishmael led away captive all the remnant of the people who were at Mizpah, the king's daughters as well as all the people who remained at Mizpah, whom Nebuzaradan, the leader of the military, had committed to Gedaliah, the son of Ahikam. And Ishmael, the son of Nethaniah, seized them and went away, so that he might go over to the sons of Ammon.

11 But Johanan, the son of Kareah, and all the leaders of the fighters who were with him, heard about all the evil that Ishmael, the son of Nethaniah, had done.

12 And taking all the men, they set out to make war against Ishmael, the son of Nethaniah. And they found him at the great waters that are in Gibeon.

13 And when all the people who were with Ishmael had seen Johanan, the son of Kareah, and all the leaders of the fighters who were with him, they rejoiced.

14 And all the people whom Ishmael had seized turned back to Mizpah. And they returned and went over to Johanan, the son of Kareah.

15 But Ishmael, the son of Nethaniah, fled with eight men from the face of Johanan, and they went over to the sons of Ammon.

16 Therefore, Johanan, the son of Kareah, and all the leaders of the fighters who were with him, took from Mizpah the entire remnant of the common people, whom they had led away from Ishmael, the son of Nethaniah, after he had struck down Gedaliah, the son of Ahikam. These were strong men of battle, and women, and children, and eunuchs: those whom he had led away from Gibeon.

17 And they went away and settled as sojourners at Chimham, which is near Bethlehem, so that they might continue on and enter into Egypt,

18 away from the face of the Chaldeans. For they were afraid of them, because Ishmael, the son of Nethaniah, had struck down Gedaliah, the son of Ahikam, whom the king of Babylon had made governor in the land of Judah.

Jeremiah 42

1 And all the leaders of the warriors, and Johanan, the son of Kareah, and Azariah, the son of Hoshaiah, and the rest of the common people, from the least even to the greatest, drew near.

2 And they said to Jeremiah the prophet: "Let our supplication fall before your sight. And pray for us to the Lord your God, on behalf of this entire remnant. For few out of many have been left behind, just as your eyes behold us.

3 And so, may the Lord your God announce to us the way that we must travel, and the word that we must accomplish."

4 Then Jeremiah, the prophet, said to them: "I have listened. Behold, I will pray to the Lord your God according to your words. And whatever word he will respond to me, I will declare to you. And I will conceal nothing from you."

5 And they said to Jeremiah: "May the Lord be the witness between us of truth and fidelity, if we do not act according to whatever word the Lord your God will send by you to us.

6 Whether it is for good or for harm, we will obey the voice of the Lord our God, to whom we are sending you. So may it be well with us, when we heed the voice of the Lord our God."

7 Then, when ten days had been completed, the word of the Lord came to Jeremiah.

8 And he called Johanan, the son of Kareah, and all the leaders of warriors who were with him, and all the people, from the least even to the greatest.

9 And he said to them: "Thus says the Lord, the God of Israel, to whom you have sent me, so that I may present your petitions in his sight:

10 If you dwell quietly in this land, I will build you up, and I will not tear you down. I will plant you, and I will not uproot you. For now I have been appeased by the harm that I have done to you.

11 Do not be afraid before the face of the king of Babylon, whom you have dreaded with great fear. Do not dread him, says the Lord. For I am with you, so that I may accomplish your salvation, and so that I may rescue you from his hand.

12 And I will give you mercies, and I will take pity on you, and I will cause you to live in your own land.

13 But if you say: 'We will not live in this land, nor will we heed the voice of the Lord our God,'

14 saying: 'Never! Instead, we will travel to the land of Egypt, where we will not see war, and we will not hear the blast of the trumpet, and we will not endure famine. And there we shall live.'

15 Because of this, hear now the word of the Lord, O remnant of Judah: Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: If you set your faces so as to advance into Egypt, and if you enter so that you may live there,

16 the sword which you dread will overtake you there, in the land of Egypt, and the famine, about which you are anxious, will cling to you in Egypt, and there you shall die.

17 And all the men, who have set their faces so that they may advance to Egypt in order to live there, will die by the sword, and by famine, and by pestilence. None of them will remain, nor will they escape from the face of the evil that I will bring over them.

18 For thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: Just as my fury and my indignation has been enflamed over the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so will my indignation be enflamed over you, when you will have entered into Egypt. And so you will be an oath, and an astonishment, and a curse, and a disgrace. And you will never see this place again.

19 This is the word of the Lord concerning you, O remnant of Judah: Do not choose to enter into Egypt, for certainly you understand what I have sworn to you this day.

20 For you have deceived your own souls. For you have sent me to the Lord our God, saying: 'Pray on our behalf to the Lord our God. And in accord with anything whatsoever that the Lord our God will tell you, announce this to us, and we will do it.'

21 And I have announced it to you this day, and you have not heeded the voice of the Lord your God, concerning everything about which he has sent me to you.

22 Therefore, know with certainty now, that you will die by the sword, and by famine, and by pestilence, in the place which you wish to enter so that you may live there."

Jeremiah 43

1 Then it happened that, when Jeremiah had finished speaking all the words of the Lord their God to the people, all those words concerning which the Lord their God had sent him to them,

2 Azariah, the son of Hoshaiah, and Johanan, the son of Kareah, and all the exalted men, spoke to Jeremiah, saying: "You are speaking a lie! The Lord our God has not sent you to say: 'You shall not enter into Egypt so as to live in that place.'

3 Instead, Baruch, the son of Neriah, has incited you against us, so as to deliver us into the hands of the Chaldeans, to put us to death and to cause us to be led away into Babylon."

4 And so Johanan, the son of Kareah, and all the leaders of the warriors, and all the people, did not heed the voice of the Lord to remain in the land of Judah.

5 But Johanan, the son of Kareah, and all the leaders of the warriors, took away all the remnant of Judah, who had returned from all the nations (to which they had been scattered before) to live in the land of Judah:

6 men, and women, and children, and the daughters of the king, and every soul that Nebuzaradan, the leader of the military, had left behind with Gedaliah, the son of Ahikam, the son of Shaphan, as well as Jeremiah, the prophet, and Baruch, the son of Neriah.

7 And they entered into the land of Egypt. For they did not obey the voice of the Lord. And they went as far as Tahpanhes.

8 And the word of the Lord came to Jeremiah at Tahpanhes, saying:

9 "Take great stones in your hand, and you shall conceal them in the crypt which is under the brick wall at the gate of the house of Pharaoh at Tahpanhes, in the sight of the men of Judah.

10 And you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: Behold, I will send for and take Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, my servant, and I will set his throne over these stones which I have concealed, and he will establish his throne upon them.

11 And he will come and strike the land of Egypt: those who are meant for death, shall go to death, and those for captivity, to captivity, and those for the sword, to the sword.

12 And he will kindle a fire in the shrines of the gods of Egypt, and he will burn them down, and he will lead them away captive. And he will clothe himself with the land of Egypt, just as a shepherd is clothed with his cloak. And he will go forth from that place in peace.

13 And he will crush the statues of the house of the Sun, those that are in the land of Egypt, and the shrines of the gods of Egypt he will burn up with fire."

Jeremiah 44

1 The word that came through Jeremiah to all the Jews who were living in the land of Egypt, living at Migdol, and at Tahpanhes, and at Memphis, and in the land of Pathros, saying:

2 "Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: You yourselves have seen all this evil that I have led over Jerusalem and over all the cities of Judah. And behold, they are desolate to this day, and there is no inhabitant in them,

3 because of the wickedness which they have done, so that they provoked me to wrath, and because they went to offer sacrifice and worship to strange gods, which neither they, nor you, nor your fathers knew.

4 And I sent to you all my servants, the prophets, rising in the night, and sending, and saying: 'Do not choose to do this abominable word, which I hate.'

5 But they did not listen, nor did they incline their ear, so that they would convert from their evil, and so that they would not sacrifice to strange gods.

6 And so my indignation and my fury was fanned and kindled in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem. And they have been turned into desolation and devastation, just as it is this day.

7 And now, thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: Why do you commit this great evil against your own souls, so that, among you, man and woman, child and infant would pass away from the midst of Judah, and so that no remnant at all would be left behind of you?

8 For you have provoked me by the works of your hands, by sacrificing to strange gods in the land of Egypt, into which you have entered in order to live there, and so that you would perish and become a curse and a disgrace before all the nations of the earth.

9 How could you have forgotten the evils of your fathers, and the evils of the kings of Judah, and the evils of their wives, and your own evils, and the evils of your own wives, which they have done in the land of Judah and in the regions of Jerusalem?

10 They have not been cleansed, even to this day. And they have not feared, and they have not walked in the law of the Lord and in my precepts, which I have given before you and before your fathers.

11 For this reason, thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: Behold, I will set my face upon you for evil. And I will disperse all of Judah.

12 And I will take the remnant of Judah, who had set their faces so that they would enter into the land of Egypt and live there, and they will all be consumed in the land of Egypt. They will fall by the sword and by famine. And they will be consumed, from the least, even to the greatest. By sword and by famine shall they die. And they will be an oath, and a wonder, and a curse, and a disgrace.

13 And I will visit against those who are living in the land of Egypt, just as I have visited against Jerusalem: with the sword, and with famine, and with pestilence.

14 And there will be no one who escapes, of those who remain among the remnant of the Jews, those who have gone to sojourn in the land of Egypt. And they wish to be returned to the land of Judah, for they lift up their souls so that they might return and live there. But there will be no one who may return, except those who will flee."

15 Then all the men, knowing that their wives were sacrificing to strange gods, and all of the women, a great multitude of whom were standing there, and all of the people who were living in the land of Egypt at Pathros, responded to Jeremiah, by saying:

16 "Concerning the word that you have spoken to us in the name of the Lord, we will not heed you.

17 But we will continue to do every word which proceeds from our own mouth, so that we sacrifice to the queen of heaven, and we pour out libations to her, just as we and our fathers have done, our kings and our leaders, in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem. For we were filled with bread, and it was well with us, and we saw no evil.

18 But since the time that we ceased to offer sacrifice to the queen of heaven, and to pour out libations to her, we have been in need of all things, and we have been consumed by the sword and by famine.

19 But when we offer sacrifice to the queen of heaven and pour out libations to her, do we make cakes for her worship and offer libations to her without our husbands?"

20 And Jeremiah spoke to all the people, facing the men, and facing the women, and facing all the people who had responded this word to him, saying:

21 "Was this not the sacrifice that you offered in the cities of Judah and in the streets of Jerusalem, you and your fathers, your kings and your leaders, and the people of the land, which has been called to mind by the Lord and which has entered into his heart?

22 And the Lord could no longer bear this, because of the evil of your intentions, and because of the abominations that you have done. And so, your land has become a desolation, and an astonishment, and a curse, and it is without an inhabitant, even to this day.

23 This is because you have sacrificed to idols, and you have sinned against the Lord. And you have not heeded the voice of the Lord, and you have not walked in his law, and in his precepts, and in his testimonies. It is for this reason that these evils have happened to you, just as it is today."

24 Then Jeremiah said to all the people and to all the women: "Listen to the word of the Lord, all you of Judah who are in the land of Egypt:

25 Thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel, saying: You and your wives have spoken it with your mouth, and have fulfilled it with your hands, saying: 'Let us perform our vows that we have made, so that we may offer sacrifice to the queen of heaven, and pour out libations to her.' You have fulfilled your vows and accomplished their works.

26 Because of this, listen to the word of the Lord, all you of Judah, who live in the land of Egypt: Behold, I have sworn by my great name, says the Lord, that my name will never again be invoked by the mouth of any man of Judah in the land of Egypt, saying: 'As the Lord God lives.'

27 Behold, I will be vigilant over them for harm, and not for good. And all the men of Judah who are in the land of Egypt will be consumed, by the sword and by famine, until they are thoroughly consumed.

28 And a few men, who will flee from the sword, will return from the land of Egypt into the land of Judah. And all the remnant of Judah, who had entered into the land of Egypt so as to live there, will know whose word will be completed, mine or theirs.

29 And this will be a sign to you, says the Lord, that I will visit against you in this place, so that truly you may know that my words will be completed against you for harm."

30 Thus says the Lord: "Behold, I will deliver Pharaoh Hophra, the king of Egypt, into the hand of his enemies, and into the hand of those who are seeking his life, just as I delivered Zedekiah, the king of Judah, into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, his enemy and the one who was seeking his life."

Jeremiah 46

1 The word of the Lord that came to Jeremiah the prophet against the Gentiles,

2 about Egypt, against the army of Pharaoh Neco, the king of Egypt, which was beside the river Euphrates at Carchemish, which Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, struck down, in the fourth year of Jehoiakim, the son of Josiah, the king of Judah:

3 " 'Prepare the heavy and the light shield, and advance to war!

4 Harness the horses, and let the horsemen climb upon them! Stand forth with helmets! Sharpen the lances! Clothe yourselves in armor!'

5 And what is next? I have seen them terrified, and turning their backs, their strong ones cut down. They have fled in disorder and have not looked back. Terror on every side, says the Lord.

6 Let not the swift take flight; let not the strong ones think to save themselves. They have been conquered and ruined, toward the north, near the river Euphrates.

7 Who is this, who ascends like a flood, and whose streams swell up, like those of the rivers?

8 Egypt ascends in the form of a river, and its waves will be moved like those of a river. And he will say: 'I will ascend and cover the earth! I will perish the city and its inhabitants!'

9 Mount the horses, and exult upon chariots, and let the strong ones advance: the Ethiopians, and the Libyans, who hold the heavy shield, and the Lydians, who grasp and shoot arrows.

10 For this is the day of the Lord, the God of hosts, a day of vengeance, so that he may vindicate himself of his enemies. The sword will devour, and be satiated, and be inebriated with their blood. For there is a victim of the Lord, the God of hosts, in the land of the north, beside the river Euphrates.

11 Ascend to Gilead, and take its balm, O virgin daughter of Egypt! It is in vain that you multiply medicines; there will be no health for you!

12 The nations have heard of your disgrace, and your wailing has filled the earth. For the strong have stumbled against the strong, and both have fallen together."

13 The word that the Lord spoke to Jeremiah the prophet, concerning how Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, would arrive and strike the land of Egypt:

14 "Announce it to Egypt, and make it heard in Migdol, and let it resonate in Memphis and in Tahpanhes. Say this: Stand and prepare yourself! For the sword will devour everything around you.

15 Why have your strong ones decayed? They have not stood firm, because the Lord has overthrown them.

16 He has multiplied those in ruin, and each man has fallen beside his neighbor. And they will say: 'Rise up, and let us return to our own people and to the land of our nativity, away from the face of the sword of the dove.

17 Call the name of Pharaoh, the king of Egypt: 'Time has brought tumult.'

18 As I live, says the King, whose name is the Lord of hosts, just as Tabor is among the mountains, and just as Carmel is beside the sea, so will he come.

19 Equip yourself for the transmigration, O daughter who inhabitants Egypt. For Memphis will be in desolation, and it will be deserted and uninhabited.

20 Egypt is like a stately and finely-formed calf. The one who will goad her will come from the north.

21 Her hired hands also, who move within her midst, like fatted calves have been turned back, and they have fled at the same time, and they are not able to stand firm. For the day of their passing away has overwhelmed them; it is the time of their visitation.

22 Her voice will sound out like brass. For they will rush forward with an army, and with axes they will come against her, like those who chop wood.

23 They have cut down her forest, says the Lord, which was not able to be counted. They have been multiplied more than locusts, and they are without number.

24 The daughter of Egypt has been confounded, and she has been delivered into the hand of the people of the north.

25 The Lord of hosts, the God of Israel, said: Behold, I will visit against the tumult of Alexandria, and against Pharaoh, and against Egypt, and against her gods, and against her kings, and against Pharaoh, and against those who trust in him.

26 And I will give them over to the hand of those who seek their lives, and into the hand of Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, and into the hand of his servants. And after this, it shall be inhabited, just as in the former days, says the Lord.

27 And as for you, my servant Jacob, you should not be afraid, and you should not dread, O Israel. For behold, I will bring your salvation from afar, and your offspring from the land of your captivity. And Jacob will return and have rest, and he will prosper. And there will be no one who may terrify him.

28 And as for you, my servant Jacob, do not be afraid, says the Lord. For I am with you. For I will consume all the nations to which I have cast you out. Yet truly, I will not consume you. Instead, I will chastise you in judgment, but neither will I spare you, as if you were innocent."

Jeremiah 47

1 The word of the Lord that came to Jeremiah, the prophet, against the Philistines, before Pharaoh struck Gaza.

2 Thus says the Lord: "Behold, waters will rise up from the north, and they will be like an inundating torrent, and they will cover the land and its plenitude, the city and its inhabitants. The men will cry out, and all the inhabitants of the land will wail,

3 before the uproar of a procession of weapons and of his soldiers, before the commotion of his four-horse chariots and the multitude of his wheels. The fathers have not looked back for the sons, because of feebleness of hands,

4 because of the arrival of the day on which all the Philistines will be devastated, and Tyre and Sidon will be destroyed, with all the rest of their helpers. For the Lord has depopulated the Philistines, the remnant of the island of Cappadocia.

5 Baldness has arrived over Gaza. Ashkelon has been silenced, along with the remnant of their valley. And how long will you continue to be cut down?

6 O sharp sword of the Lord, how long will you be without rest? Enter your sheath; be refreshed and silenced.

7 But how can it find rest, when the Lord has ordered it against Ashkelon and against its maritime regions, and when a task has been appointed to it there?"

Jeremiah 48

1 Against Moab, thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: "Woe upon Nebo! For it has been devastated and confounded. Kiriathaim has been seized; the strong one has been confounded and has trembled.

2 There is no longer any rejoicing in Moab over Heshbon. They have devised evil. 'Come and let us destroy it as a nation.' Then you will be utterly silenced, and the sword will pursue you.

3 A voice of clamor from Horonaim: devastation and great destruction!

4 Moab has been crushed. Announce an outcry for her little ones.

5 For, along the ascent of Luhith, the mourner will ascend with weeping. For, on the descent of Horonaim, the enemies have heard the wailing of devastation.

6 Flee, save your lives! And you shall be like a saltcedar tree in the desert.

7 For because you have had faith in your fortifications and in your storehouses, you too will be seized. And Chemosh will go into captivity: his priests and his leaders together.

8 And the despoiler will overwhelm every city, and not a single city will be saved. And the valleys will perish, and the fields will be destroyed. For the Lord has spoken.

9 Give a blossom to Moab. For it will depart when it is blossoming. And its cities will become desolate and uninhabited.

10 Cursed is he who does the work of the Lord deceitfully. And cursed is he who prohibits his sword from blood.

11 Moab has been fertile from his youth, and he has rested amid his brood. And he has not been transferred from vessel to vessel, nor has he gone into the transmigration. Therefore, his taste has remained with him, and his scent has not changed.

12 Because of this, behold, the days are approaching, says the Lord, when I will send to him those who will line up and knock down his bottles, and they will knock him down and empty his vessels, and they will break their bottles against one another.

13 And Moab will be confounded by Chemosh, just as the house of Israel was shamed by Bethel, in which they had faith.

14 How can you say: 'We are strong and robust men of battle?'

15 Moab has been devastated, and they have cut down her cities. And her elect young men have descended to slaughter. So says the King, whose name is the Lord of hosts.

16 The passing away of Moab draws near and arrives. Its evil will rush forward with great speed.

17 Console him, all you who surround him and all you who know his name. Say: 'How has the strong staff become broken, the glorious staff?'

18 Descend from your glory, and sit in thirst, O habitation of the daughter of Dibon! For the destroyer of Moab has ascended to you; he has dissipated your fortifications.

19 Stand in the way, and gaze out, O habitation of Aroer! Question him who is fleeing, and say to him who has escaped: 'What has happened?'

20 Moab has been confounded, because he has been conquered. Wail and cry out! Announce it in Arnon: Moab has been devastated,

21 and judgment has arrived upon the land of the plains: upon Holon, and upon Jahzah, and upon Mephaath,

22 and upon Dibon, and upon Nebo, and upon the house of Deblathaim,

23 and upon Kiriathaim, and upon the house of Gamul, and upon the house of Meon,

24 and upon Kerioth, and upon Bozrah, and upon all the cities of the land of Moab, those far away and those nearby.

25 The horn of Moab has been cut away, and his arm has been crushed, says the Lord.

26 Inebriate him, for he has lifted himself up against the Lord. And Moab will thrust his hand into his own vomit, and also now he himself will become a derision.

27 For Israel had been a derision to them. It was as if you had discovered him among thieves. Because of your own words, then, which you have spoken against him, you will be led away captive.

28 Relinquish the cities, and live upon a rock, O inhabitants of Moab, and be like a dove nesting at the mouth of an opening at the summit.

29 We have listened to the arrogance of Moab; he is very proud: his exaltation, and arrogance, and pride, and the loftiness of his heart.

30 I myself know, says the Lord, his boasting, and that his ability is not in accord with it, nor is it in accord with what he has been striving to do.

31 For this reason, I will wail over Moab, and I will cry out to all of Moab, to the men on the brick wall who are lamenting.

32 O vineyard of Sibmah, I will weep for you, with the mourning of Jazer. Your offshoots have crossed over the sea. They have reached even to the sea of Jazer. The despoiler has rushed over your harvest and your vintage.

33 Rejoicing and exultation has been taken away from Carmel and from the land of Moab. And I have taken the wine from the winepresses. The treader of grapes will no longer sing the usual rhythmic chant.

34 From the outcry of Heshbon, even to Elealeh and Jahzah, they have uttered their voice; from Zoar, even to Horonaim, like a three year old calf. So too, the waters of Nimrim will be very bad.

35 And I will take away from Moab, says the Lord, the one who makes offerings in exalted places, and the one who sacrifices to his gods.

36 Because of this, my heart will resound for Moab, like the pipes, and my heart will make a sound like the pipes for the men on the brick wall. For he has done more than he was able, yet still they have perished.

37 For every head will be bald, and every beard will be shaved. All the hands will be bound together, and there will be haircloth on every back.

38 Over all the rooftops of Moab, and in its streets, everyone will mourn. For I have crushed Moab like a useless vessel, says the Lord.

39 How was it conquered, so that they would wail? How is it that Moab has cast down his neck and been confounded? And Moab will be a derision and an example to everyone around him."

40 Thus says the Lord: "Behold, he will fly like the eagle, and he will extend his wings to Moab.

41 Kerioth has been captured, and the fortifications have been taken. And in that day, the heart of the strong ones of Moab will be like the heart of a woman giving birth.

42 And Moab will cease to be a people. For he has been glorified against the Lord.

43 Terror and the pit and the snare will overwhelm you, O inhabitant of Moab, says the Lord.

44 Whoever flees from the terror will fall into the pit. And whoever climbs out of the pit will be seized by the snare. For I will lead over Moab the year of their visitation, says the Lord.

45 Those fleeing from the snare stood in the shadow of Heshbon. For a fire has gone forth from Heshbon, and a flame from the midst of Sihon, and it will devour the portion of Moab, and the top of the head of the sons of tumult.

46 Woe to you, O Moab! You have been ruined, O people of Chemosh! For your sons and your daughters have been taken into captivity.

47 But I will convert the captivity of Moab in the last days, says the Lord." Such are the judgments of Moab thus far.

Jeremiah 49

1 Against the sons of Ammon. Thus says the Lord: "Does Israel have no sons? Or is there no heir for him? Then why has Milcom possessed the inheritance of Gad, and why have his people lived in his cities?

2 Therefore, behold, the days are approaching, says the Lord, when I will cause the noise of battle to be heard over Rabbah of the sons of Ammon. And it will be scattered into a tumult, and her daughters will be burned with fire. And Israel shall possess those who had possessed him, says the Lord.

3 Wail, O Heshbon! For Ai has been devastated. Cry out, O daughters of Rabbah! Wrap yourselves with haircloth. Mourn and circle the hedges. For Milcom will be led into the transmigration: his priests and his leaders together.

4 Why have you gloried in the valleys? Your valley has flowed away, O delicate daughter, for you had confidence in your treasures, and you were saying, 'Who can approach me?'

5 Behold, I will lead a terror over you, says the Lord, the God of hosts, from those who are all around you. And you will be dispersed, each one from before your sight. There will be no one who will gather together those who are fleeing.

6 And after this, I will cause the captives of the sons of Ammon to return, says the Lord."

7 Against Idumea. Thus says the Lord of hosts: "Is there no longer any wisdom in Teman? Counsel has perished from the sons. Their wisdom has become useless.

8 Flee and turn your backs! Descend into the chasm, O inhabitants of Dedan! For I have brought the perdition of Esau over him, the time of his visitation.

9 If those who gather grapes had passed by you, would they not have left behind a cluster? If there were thieves in the night, they would seize what was enough for themselves.

10 Yet truly, I have stripped Esau bare. I have revealed his secrets, and he is not able to be concealed. His offspring has been devastated, with his brothers and his neighbors, and he himself will not exist.

11 Leave behind your orphans. I will make sure that they live. And your widows will hope in me."

12 For thus says the Lord: "Behold, those who judged that they would not drink the cup, will certainly drink. And so, will you be released as if you were innocent? You will not be released as if innocent. Instead, you shall certainly drink.

13 For I have sworn by myself, says the Lord, that Bozrah will be a desolation, and a disgrace, and a wasteland, and a curse. And all her cities will be a perpetual wilderness.

14 I have heard a report from the Lord, and an legate has been sent to the nations: 'Gather yourselves together, and go forth against her, and let us rise up to battle.'

15 For behold, I have made you little among the nations, contemptible among men.

16 Your arrogance has deceived you, by the pride of your heart, you who live in the caverns of the rock and who strive to take hold of the height of the hill. But even if you make your nest like that of an eagle, I will pull you down from there, says the Lord.

17 And Idumea will be a desert. Everyone who passes by it will be stupefied and will hiss over all its wounds.

18 Just as Sodom and Gomorrah and their neighbors were overthrown, says the Lord: there will not be a man living there, and no son of man will tend it.

19 Behold, he will ascend like a lion from the arrogance of the Jordan, against the robust beauty. For I will cause him to rush against her suddenly. And who will be the elect one, whom I may appoint over her? For who is like me? And who can endure me? And who is that pastor who can withstand my countenance?

20 Because of this, listen to the counsel of the Lord, which he has undertaken concerning Edom, and to his thoughts, which he has devised concerning the inhabitants of Teman. Certainly, the little ones of the flock will cast them down, unless they scatter them with their habitation.

21 The earth has been shaken at the noise of their destruction. The outcry of their voice has been heard at the Red Sea.

22 Behold, he will ascend like an eagle and will fly. And he will spread his wings over Bozrah. And in that day, the heart of the strong ones of Idumea will be like the heart of a woman giving birth."

23 Against Damascus. "Hamath has been confounded, with Arpad. For they have heard a most grievous report. They have been stirred up like the sea. Because of anxiousness, they were not able to rest.

24 Damascus has been broken. She has been turned to flight. Trembling has taken hold of her. Anguish and sorrows have seized her, like a woman giving birth.

25 How could they have abandoned the praiseworthy city, the city of rejoicing?

26 For this reason, her young men will fall in her streets. And all the men of battle will be silenced in that day, says the Lord of hosts.

27 And I will kindle a fire at the wall of Damascus, and it will devour the defensive walls of Ben-hadad."

28 Against Kedar and against the kingdoms of Hazor, which Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, has struck down. Thus says the Lord: "Rise up and ascend to Kedar, and lay waste to the sons of the East.

29 They will seize their tabernacles and their flocks. And they will take for themselves their tents, and all their vessels, and their camels. And they will call down a terror upon them on every side.

30 Flee, go away urgently! Sit in deep pits, you who inhabit Hazor, says the Lord. For Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, has undertaken a counsel against you, and he has devised plans against you.

31 Rise up, and ascend to a nation that is quiet and lives in confidence, says the Lord. They have neither gates nor bars. They dwell alone.

32 And their camels will be a spoil, and the multitude of their cattle will be a prey. And I will disperse, into every wind, those who have shaved their hair. And from all their confines, I will lead great destruction over them, says the Lord.

33 And Hazor will be a habitation for serpents, deserted even unto eternity. No man will abide there, nor will a son of man tend it."

34 The word of the Lord that came to Jeremiah the prophet against Elam, in the beginning of the reign of Zedekiah, the king of Judah, saying:

35 "Thus says the Lord of hosts: Behold, I will break the bow of Elam, and the summit of their strength.

36 And I will lead the four winds over Elam, from the four corners of heaven. And I will scatter them into all these winds. And there will be no nation to which the fugitives of Elam will not travel.

37 And I will cause Elam to be terrified before their enemies and in the sight of those who seek their life. And I will lead an evil over them, the wrath of my fury, says the Lord. And I will send the sword after them, until I consume them.

38 And I will set my throne in Elam, and I will perish the kings and princes from there, says the Lord.

39 But in the last days, I will cause the captives of Elam to return, says the Lord."

Jeremiah 50

1 The word that the Lord has spoken about Babylon and about the land of the Chaldeans, by the hand of Jeremiah the prophet.

2 "Announce it among the Gentiles, and make it known. Lift up a sign. Proclaim it and do not conceal it. Say this: 'Babylon has been captured. Bel has been confounded. Merodach has been conquered. Their graven things have been confounded. Their idols have not survived.'

3 For a nation has ascended against her from the north, which will set her land in desolation. And there will be no one who may live within it, from man even to beast. For they have been removed and have gone away.

4 In those days and in that time, says the Lord, the sons of Israel will advance, they and the sons of Judah together. Weeping as they walk, they will hurry on, and they will seek the Lord their God.

5 They will ask the way to Zion; their faces will be set toward this place. They will arrive and will be joined to the Lord by an everlasting covenant, which nothing will wipe away into oblivion.

6 My people have become a lost flock. Their shepherds have led them astray and have caused them to wander in the mountains. They have crossed from mountain to hill. They have forgotten their resting place.

7 All whom they have found, they have devoured. And their enemies have said: 'We have not sinned. For it is they who have sinned against the Lord, the beauty of justice, and against the Lord, the hope of their fathers.'

8 Withdraw from the midst of Babylon, and go forth from the land of the Chaldeans. And be like young goats before the flock.

9 For behold, I am raising up, and I will lead against Babylon, a congregation of great nations from the land of the north. And they will be prepared against her, and from there she will be taken. Their arrows, like those of a strong man, a killer, will not return empty.

10 And Chaldea will become a prey. All who lay waste to her will be filled, says the Lord.

11 For you exult and you speak great things, plundering my inheritance. For you have spread out like calves upon the grass, and you have bellowed like bulls.

12 Your mother has been exceedingly shamed, and she who bore you has become equal to the dust. Behold, she will be the last among the nations, a desert, impassable and dry.

13 By the wrath of the Lord, it will not be inhabited. Instead, it will be entirely desolate. Every one who passes by Babylon will be stupefied and will hiss over all her wounds.

14 Prepare yourselves against Babylon, on every side, all you who bend the bow. Make war against her! You should not spare the arrows, for she has sinned against the Lord.

15 Cry out against her! For where she has put forth a hand, her foundations have fallen, her walls have been destroyed. For it is the vengeance of the Lord. Take vengeance against her! Just as she has done, do so to her.

16 Destroy the founder from Babylon, and the one who holds the sickle in the time of harvest. Before the face of the sword of the dove, each one will turn back to his people, and every one will flee to his own land.

17 Israel is a scattered flock. The lions have driven him away. First, the king of Assyria devoured him. And last, this Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, has taken away his bones.

18 Because of this, thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: Behold, I will visit the king of Babylon and his land, just as I have visited the king of Assyria.

19 And I will lead back Israel to his habitation. And he will pasture on Carmel and Bashan, and his soul will be satiated at mount Ephraim and Gilead.

20 In those days and at that time, says the Lord, the iniquity of Israel will be sought, and there will be none. And the sin of Judah will be sought, and none will be found. For I will be forgiving to them, whom I will leave behind.

21 Ascend against the land of the rulers, and visit against its inhabitants! Scatter and destroy whatever has been left behind them, says the Lord, and act according to all that I have instructed you.

22 A voice of war in the land, and great destruction!

23 How has the mallet of the entire earth been broken and crushed? How has Babylon been turned into a desert among the nations?

24 I have ensnared you, and you have been captured, O Babylon, and you did not realize it. You have been discovered and seized, because you provoked the Lord.

25 The Lord has opened his storehouse, and he has brought forth the instruments of his wrath. For there is work for the Lord, the God of hosts, within the land of the Chaldeans.

26 Advance against her from the furthest regions! Open, so that those who will trample her may go out! Take stones from the road, and gather them into piles, and destroy her. And let there be nothing left of her.

27 Scatter all her strong ones. Let them descend to the slaughter. Woe to them! For their day has arrived, the time of their visitation.

28 It is the voice of those who are fleeing and of those who have escaped from the land of Babylon: to announce in Zion the revenge of the Lord our God, the revenge of his Temple.

29 Announce it to the many in Babylon, to all who bend the bow. Stand together against her all around, and let no one escape. Repay her according to her work. In accord with all that she has done, do to her. For she has raised herself up against the Lord, against the Holy One of Israel.

30 For this reason, her young men will fall in her streets. And all her men of war will be silenced, in that day, says the Lord.

31 Behold, I am against you, O proud one, says the Lord, the God of hosts. For your day has arrived, the time of your visitation.

32 And the proud one will fall and be ruined. And there will be no one who may lift him up. And I will kindle a fire in his cities, and it will devour everything around him."

33 Thus says the Lord of hosts: "The sons of Israel and the sons of Judah have endured calumny together. All who have seized them are holding them and refusing to release them.

34 Their redeemer is strong. The Lord of hosts is his name. He will defend their case in judgment, so that he may terrify the land and disturb the inhabitants of Babylon.

35 A sword is for the Chaldeans, says the Lord, and for the inhabitants of Babylon, and for her leaders, and for her wise ones.

36 A sword is for her diviners, who will be fooled. A sword is for her strong ones, who will be afraid.

37 A sword is for their horses, and for their chariots, and for all the common people who are in her midst. And they will be like women. A sword is for her storehouses, and they will be plundered.

38 A drought is over her waters, and they will be dried up. For it is a land of graven images, and they glory in portents.

39 Because of this, dragons will live there with the fig fauns, and ostriches will live in it. And it will no longer be inhabited, even in perpetuity, nor will it be raised up, even from generation to generation.

40 Just as the Lord overthrew Sodom and Gomorrah, and their neighboring towns, says the Lord, no man will live there, and a son of man will not tend it.

41 Behold, a people arrives from the north, and a great nation. And many kings will rise up from the ends of the earth.

42 They will take up the bow and the shield. They are cruel and merciless. Their voice will sound out, like the sea, and they will ride upon horses, like a man prepared for battle against you, O daughter of Babylon.

43 The king of Babylon has heard the report about them, and his hands have been weakened. Anguish has overtaken him, like the pains of a woman giving birth.

44 Behold, he will ascend like a lion from the arrogance of the Jordan to the robust beauty. For I will cause him to rush upon her suddenly. And who will be the elect one, whom I may appoint over her? For who is like me? And who can endure me? And who is that pastor who can withstand my countenance?"

45 Because of this, listen to the counsel of the Lord, which he has conceived in his mind against Babylon, and to his thoughts, which he has devised against the land of the Chaldeans: "Certainly the little ones of the flocks will pull them down, unless their habitation will have been destroyed with them.

46 At the voice of the captivity of Babylon, the earth has been moved, and an outcry has been heard among the nations."

Jeremiah 51

1 Thus says the Lord: "Behold, I will raise up, over Babylon and over its inhabitants, who have lifted up their heart against me, something like a pestilent wind.

2 And I will send winnowers into Babylon, and they will winnow her, and they will demolish her land. For they will overwhelm her from every side in the day of her affliction.

3 Let him who draws the bow, not draw his bow. And let him who wears armor, not rise up. Do not spare her young men. Destroy her entire military.

4 And the slain will fall in the land of the Chaldeans, and the wounded in its regions.

5 Yet Israel and Judah have not been widowed by their God, the Lord of hosts, though their land has been filled with transgression against the Holy One of Israel.

6 Flee from the midst of Babylon! And let each one save his own life. Do not be silent about her iniquity. For it is the time of revenge from the Lord. He himself will repay her, in her turn.

7 Babylon is a gold cup in the hand of the Lord, inebriating the entire earth. The nations have drunk from her wine, and therefore they have staggered.

8 Suddenly, Babylon has fallen and been crushed. Wail over her! Take a balm to her pain, if perhaps she may be healed."

9 "We would have cured Babylon, but there is no cure. Let us abandon her, and let each one of us go to his own land. For her judgment has reached even to the heavens, and has been lifted up even to the clouds.

10 The Lord has brought forth our justices. Come and let us describe in Zion the work of the Lord our God."

11 Sharpen the arrows, fill the quivers. The Lord has raised up the spirit of the kings of the Medes. And his mind is against Babylon, so that he may destroy her. For this is the vengeance of the Lord, the vengeance of his temple.

12 Upon the walls of Babylon, lift up a sign. Increase the watch! Rouse the watchmen! Prepare ambushes! For the Lord has planned and has accomplished all that he has spoken, against the inhabitants of Babylon.

13 You who live above many waters, rich in treasures: your end has arrived, your measure has been cut short.

14 The Lord of hosts has sworn by himself, saying: "For I will fill you with men as with locusts, and they will sing a rhythmic chant against you."

15 The One who made the earth by his strength, who prepared the world by his wisdom, and who stretched out the heavens by his prudence:

16 when he utters his voice, the waters will be multiplied in the heavens. The One who lifts up the clouds from the ends of the earth: he has turned lightning into rain, and he has brought forth wind from his storehouses.

17 Each man has become foolish before his own knowledge. Each sculptor has been confounded by his own sculpture. For what he has formed of them is a lie, and there is no spirit in them.

18 They are empty works, deserving of ridicule. In the time of their visitation, they will perish.

19 The portion of Jacob is not like their portion. For the One who made all things is his portion, and Israel is the scepter of his inheritance. The Lord of hosts is his name:

20 "For me, you strike together the instruments of war; and with you, I will strike together nations; and with you, I will scatter the kingdoms.

21 And with you, I will strike together the horse and his rider; and with you, I will strike together the chariot and its rider.

22 And with you, I will strike together man and woman; and with you, I will strike together the old man and the boy; and with you, I will strike together the young man and the virgin.

23 And with you, I will strike together the pastor and his flock; and with you, I will strike together the farmer and his yoke of oxen; and with you, I will strike together military leaders and civil leaders.

24 And I will repay Babylon and all the inhabitants of Chaldea for all their evil that they have done in Zion, before your eyes, says the Lord.

25 Behold, I am against you, you pestilent mountain, says the Lord, for you are corrupting the entire earth. And I will extend my hand over you, and I will roll you down from the rocks, and I will make you into a burning mountain.

26 And they will not take from you a stone for the corner, nor a stone for the foundations. Instead, you will be destroyed unto eternity," says the Lord.

27 Lift up a sign in the land! Sound the trumpet among the nations! Sanctify the nations against her. Announce against her the kings of Ararat, Minni, and Ashkenaz. Number against her Taphsar. Lead in the horse, like the stinging locust.

28 Sanctify the nations against her: the kings of Media, their military leaders, and all their civil leaders, and the entire land under their authority.

29 And the earth will be shaken and will be disturbed. For the plan of the Lord against Babylon will awaken, so that he may make the land of Babylon desolate and uninhabitable.

30 The strong ones of Babylon have ceased to do battle. They have lived in fortresses. Their health has been devoured, and they have become like women. Her tabernacles have been set ablaze; her bars have been broken.

31 Runner will go forth to meet runner, and messenger will meet messenger, so as to tell the king of Babylon that his city has been captured, from one end to the other,

32 and that the fords were seized in advance, and that the marshes have been burned with fire, and that the men of war have been set in disarray.

33 For thus says the Lord of hosts, the God of Israel: "The daughter of Babylon is like a threshing floor. This is the time of her threshing. A little while longer, and the time of her harvest will arrive."

34 "Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, has consumed me, has devoured me. He has made me like an empty vessel. He has swallowed me like a dragon. He has filled his belly with my tender ones, and he has cast me out.

35 This iniquity is against me, and so my flesh is upon Babylon," says the habitation of Zion. "And my blood is upon the inhabitants of Chaldea," says Jerusalem.

36 Because of this, thus says the Lord: "Behold, I will judge your case, and I will avenge your vengeance, and I will make her sea into a desert, and I will dry up her spring.

37 And Babylon will become a tumult, the habitation of dragons, an astonishment, and a hissing, because there is no inhabitant.

38 They will roar together, like lions, they will shake their manes, like young lions.

39 In their heat, I will give them a drink, and I will inebriate them, so that they become drowsy, and sleep an everlasting sleep, and do not rise up, says the Lord.

40 I will lead them away, like lambs to the slaughter, and like rams with young goats.

41 How was Sesac captured, and how was the renowned one of all the earth seized? How has Babylon become an astonishment among the nations?

42 The sea has ascended over Babylon; she has been covered by the multitude of its waves.

43 Her cities have become an astonishment, an uninhabited and desolate land, a land in which no one may live, nor may a son of man pass through it.

44 And I will visit against Bel in Babylon, and I will cast from his mouth what he has swallowed. And the nations will no longer flow together before him. For even the wall of Babylon will also fall.

45 Go forth from her midst, my people, so that each one may save his life from the wrath of the fury of the Lord.

46 For otherwise, your heart may faint, and you may be afraid at the news that is heard in the land. And the news will arrive within a year, and after that year more news will arrive. And iniquity will be in the land, and one ruler will be over another ruler.

47 Because of this, behold, the days are approaching, when I will visit against the graven images of Babylon. And her entire land will be confounded, and all her slain will fall in her midst.

48 And the heavens and the earth, and all the things that are in them, will give praise over Babylon. For despoilers will approach her from the north, says the Lord.

49 And in the manner that Babylon has caused the slain to fall in Israel, so the slain of Babylon will fall over the entire earth.

50 You who have fled from the sword, approach, do not stand still. Remember from afar the Lord, and let Jerusalem rise up in your heart.

51 We have been confounded, for we heard reproach. Shame has covered our faces, for strangers have overwhelmed the holiness of the house of the Lord.

52 Because of this, behold, the days are approaching, says the Lord, when I will visit against her graven images, and within all her land the wounded will groan.

53 If Babylon were to ascend to heaven, and establish her strength on high, her despoilers would go forth from me, says the Lord."

54 A voice of outcry from Babylon, and great destruction from the land of the Chaldeans!

55 For the Lord has despoiled Babylon, and he has perished the great voice from her. And their wave will make a sound like many waters. Their voice has uttered a noise.

56 For the despoiler has overwhelmed her, that is, Babylon, and her strong ones have been apprehended, and their bow has been weakened. For the Lord, the powerful revenger, will certainly repay.

57 "And I will inebriate her leaders, and her wise ones, and her military rulers, and her civil rulers, and her strong ones. And they will sleep an everlasting sleep, and they will not awaken," says the King: the Lord of hosts is his name.

58 Thus says the Lord of hosts: "That very wide wall of Babylon will be utterly overturned, and her exalted gates will be burned with fire, and the labors of the people will be as nothing, and the labors of the nations will be sent into the fire and will perish."

59 The word that Jeremiah, the prophet, instructed to Seraiah, the son of Neriah, the son of Mahseiah, when he traveled with king Zedekiah into Babylon, in the fourth year of his reign. Now Seraiah was the leader of the prophets.

60 And Jeremiah wrote in one book all the evil that was to overwhelm Babylon; all these words were written against Babylon.

61 And Jeremiah said to Seraiah: "When you will enter into Babylon, and you will see and read all these words,

62 you will say: 'O Lord, you have spoken against this place so that you may destroy it, so that there would not be anyone, from man even to beast, who may live in it, and so that it may be desolate forever.'

63 And when you will have completed reading this book, you will tie a stone to it, and you will cast it into the midst of the Euphrates.

64 And you will say: 'So shall Babylon be submerged! And she will not rise up before the face of the affliction that I will lead over her. And she will be broken.' " The words of Jeremiah thus far.

Jeremiah 52

1 Zedekiah was a son of twenty-one years when he first began to reign. And he reigned for eleven years in Jerusalem. And the name of his mother was Hamutal, the daughter of Jeremiah from Libnah.

2 And he did what was evil in the eyes of the Lord, in accord with all that Jehoiakim had done.

3 And so the fury of the Lord was toward Jerusalem, and toward Judah, even until he cast them away from his face. And Zedekiah drew away from the king of Babylon.

4 And it happened that, in the ninth year of his reign, in the tenth month, on the tenth of the month, Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, he and his entire army, came against Jerusalem. And they besieged it, and they built fortifications against it, on every side.

5 And the city was besieged, until the eleventh year of king Zedekiah.

6 Then, in the fourth month, on the ninth of the month, a famine gripped the city. And there was no nourishment for the people of the land.

7 And the city was broken, and all the men of war fled, and they departed from the city at night by way of the gate which is between the two walls, and which leads to the king's garden, while the Chaldeans were besieging the city all around, and they went away by the road that leads to the wilderness.

8 But the army of the Chaldeans pursued the king. And they overtook Zedekiah in the desert which is near Jericho. And all of his companions fled away from him.

9 And when they had captured the king, they led him away to the king of Babylon at Riblah, which is in the land of Hamath. And he spoke a judgment against him.

10 And the king of Babylon cut the throats of the sons of Zedekiah before his eyes, and he also killed all the leaders of Judah at Riblah.

11 And he plucked out the eyes of Zedekiah, and he bound him with shackles, and the king of Babylon led him away to Babylon, and he placed him in the prison house, even until the day of his death.

12 Then, in the fifth month, on the tenth of the month, which is the nineteenth year of Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, Nebuzaradan, the leader of the military, arrived. And he was standing before the king of Babylon at Jerusalem.

13 And he set fire to the house of the Lord, and to the house of the king, and to all the houses of Jerusalem. And every great house he burned with fire.

14 And the entire army of the Chaldeans, who were with the chief of the military, destroyed the entire wall all around Jerusalem.

15 Then Nebuzaradan, the leader of the military, took away some of the poor people, and some of the rest of the common people, who had remained in the city, and some of the fugitives, who had fled over to the king of Babylon, and the rest of the multitude.

16 Yet truly, some of the poor of the land, Nebuzaradan, the leader of the military, left behind as vinedressers and farmers.

17 The Chaldeans also broke apart the bronze pillars that were in the house of the Lord, and the bases, and the sea of brass that was in the house of the Lord. And they took all the brass of these things to Babylon.

18 And they took the cooking pots, and the hooks, and the psalteries, and the bowls, and the little mortars, and all the bronze vessels that had been used in the ministry.

19 And the chief of the military took the water pots, and the censers, and the pitchers, and the basins, and the lampstands, and the mortars, and the little cups, whatever was gold, for the gold, and whatever was silver, for the silver,

20 as well as the two pillars, and the one brass sea, and the twelve oxen of brass that were under the bases, which king Solomon had made in the house of the Lord. There was no weight of brass left behind out of all these vessels.

21 Now concerning the pillars, one pillar was eighteen cubits high, and a cord of twelve cubits encircled it. Moreover, its thickness was four fingers, and the interior was hollow.

22 And heads of brass were upon both. And the height of one head was five cubits. And little nets with pomegranates were upon the heads all around, all of brass. The second pillar was similar, and the pomegranates.

23 And there were ninety-six pomegranates hanging down; and there were one hundred pomegranates in all, surrounded by the little nets.

24 And the chief of the military took Seraiah, the first priest, and Zephaniah, the second priest, and the three keepers of the vestibule.

25 He also took from the city one eunuch who was in charge of the men of war, and seven men among those who served before the face of the king, who were found in the city, and a scribe, a leader of the military, who tested the new recruits, and sixty men from the people of the land, who were found in the midst of the city.

26 Then Nebuzaradan, the chief of the military, took them, and he led them to the king of Babylon at Riblah.

27 And the king of Babylon struck them and put them to death at Riblah, in the land of Hamath. And Judah was carried away from his land.

28 This is the people whom Nebuchadnezzar carried away: in the seventh year, three thousand and twenty-three Jews;

29 in the eighteenth year of Nebuchadnezzar, eight hundred thirty-two souls from Jerusalem;

30 in the twenty-third year of Nebuchadnezzar, Nebuzaradan, the chief of the military, carried away of the Jews seven hundred forty-five souls. Therefore, all the souls were four thousand six hundred.

31 And it happened that, in the thirty-seventh year of the transmigration of Jehoiachin, the king of Judah, in the twelfth month, on the twenty-fifth of the month, Evilmerodach, the king of Babylon, in the very first year of his reign, lifted up the head of Jehoiachin, the king of Judah, and he brought him out of the prison house.

32 And he spoke with him for good, and he set his throne above the thrones of the kings who were after him in Babylon.

33 And he changed his prison garments, and he ate bread in his sight always, all the days of his life.

34 And for his meals, a continual provision was allotted to him by the king of Babylon, a measure for every single day, until the day of his death, all the days of his life.

Lamentations 1

1 ALEPH. O how a city once filled with people now sits alone! The Governess of the Gentiles has become like a widow. The Prince of the provinces has been placed under tribute.

2 BETH. Weeping, she has wept through the night, and her tears are on her cheeks. There is no one to be a comfort to her and to all her beloved. All her friends have spurned her, and they have become her enemies.

3 GHIMEL. Judah has migrated because of affliction and great servitude. She has lived among the nations and not found rest. All of her persecutors have apprehended her, amid torments.

4 DALETH. The pathways of Zion mourn, because there are none who approach for the solemnity. All her gates are destroyed. Her priests groan. Her virgins are filthy. And she is overwhelmed with bitterness.

5 HE. Her enemies have been made her leaders; her adversaries have been enriched. For the Lord has spoken against her, because of the multitude of her iniquities. Her little ones have been led into captivity before the face of the tribulator.

6 VAU. And all her elegance has departed, from the daughter of Zion. Her leaders have become like rams that cannot find pasture, and they have gone away without strength before the face of the pursuer.

7 ZAIN. Jerusalem has remembered the days of her affliction and the betrayal of all her desirable ones, whom she held from the days of antiquity, when her people fell into the hand of the enemy, and there was no one to be a helper. The enemies have looked upon her and mocked her Sabbaths.

8 HETH. Jerusalem has sinned a grievous sin. Because of this, she has become unstable. All who glorified her have spurned her, because they have looked upon her disgrace. Then she groaned and turned away again.

9 TETH. Her filth is on her feet, and her end has not been remembered. She has been vehemently put down, having no consolation. O Lord, look upon my affliction, for the adversary has been lifted up.

10 JOD. The enemy has sent his hand against all her desirable ones. For she has watched the Gentiles enter her sanctuary, even though you instructed that they should not enter into your church.

11 CAPH. All her people are groaning and seeking bread. They have given up whatever was precious in exchange for food, so as to remain alive. See, O Lord, and consider, for I have become vile.

12 LAMED. O all you who pass by the way, attend, and see if there is any sorrow like my sorrow. For he has made me a vintage, just as the Lord has spoken in the day of his furious anger.

13 MEM. From on high, he has sent fire into my bones, and he has educated me. He has spread a net for my feet; he has turned me back. He has placed me in desolation, consumed by grief, all day long.

14 NUN. Vigilant is the yoke of my iniquities. They have been folded together in his hand and imposed on my neck. My virtue has been weakened. The Lord has given me into a hand, out of which I am not able to rise.

15 SAMECH. The Lord has taken away all of my great ones from my midst. He has called forth time against me, so as to crush my elect ones. The Lord has trampled the winepress, which was for the virgin daughter of Judah.

16 AIN. For this I weep, and my eyes bring forth water. For the consoler has been far away from me, changing my soul. My sons have become lost, because the enemy has prevailed.

17 PHE. Zion has reached out her hands; there is no one to console her. The Lord has given orders against Jacob; his enemies are all around him. Jerusalem among them is like a woman made unclean by menstruation.

18 SADE. The Lord is just, for it is I who has provoked his mouth to wrath. I beg all people to listen and to see my sorrow. My virgins and my youths have gone into captivity.

19 COPH. I called for my friends, but they deceived me. My priests and my elders have been consumed in the city. For they were seeking their food, so as to revive their life.

20 RES. See, O Lord, that I am in tribulation. My bowels have been disturbed, my heart has been subverted within me, for I am filled with bitterness. Outside, the sword puts to death, and at home there is a similar death.

21 SIN. They have heard that I groan and that there is no one to console me. All my enemies have heard of my misfortune; they have rejoiced that you caused it. You have brought in a day of consolation, and so they shall become like me.

22 THAU. Let all their evil enter before you. And make vintage of them, just as you made vintage of me, because of all my iniquities. For my sighs are many, and my heart is grieving.

Lamentations 2

1 ALEPH. O how the Lord has covered the daughter of Zion with gloom in his fury! O how he has thrown down from heaven to earth the famous one of Israel, and he has not remembered his footstool in the day of his fury.

2 BETH. The Lord has cast down, and he has not been lenient, with all the beauties of Jacob. In his fury, he has destroyed the fortifications of the virgin of Judah, and he has thrown them down to the ground. He has polluted the kingdom and its leaders.

3 GHIMEL. In the anger of his fury, he has broken the entire horn of Israel. He has drawn back his right hand before the face of the enemy. And he has kindled within Jacob a flaming fire, devouring all around.

4 DALETH. He has bent his bow like an enemy. He has fixed his right hand like an adversary. And he has cut down all that was beautiful to behold in the tabernacle of the daughter of Zion. He has poured out his indignation like fire.

5 HE. The Lord has become like an enemy. He has thrown down Israel. He has thrown down all of his defenses. He has torn apart his fortifications. And he has filled the daughter of Judah with humbled men and humbled women.

6 VAU. And he has torn apart her tent like a garden. He has demolished her tabernacle. In Zion, the Lord has delivered feast and Sabbath into oblivion, and king and priest into disgrace, and into the indignation of his fury.

7 ZAIN. The Lord has pushed away his own altar. He has cursed his own sanctuary. He has delivered the walls of its towers into the hand of the enemy. They have made a noise in the house of the Lord, as if on the day of a solemnity.

8 HETH. The Lord has decided to tear down the wall of the daughter of Zion. He has stretched out his measuring line, and he has not turn away his hand from perdition. And the rampart has mourned, and with the wall it has been torn apart.

9 TETH. Her gates have been buried in the ground. He has ruined and crushed its bars. Her king and her princes are with the Gentiles. There is no law, and her prophets have found no vision from the Lord.

10 JOD. The elders of the daughter of Zion have become idle; they sit on the ground. They have sprinkled their heads with ashes. They have been wrapped with haircloth. The virgins of Jerusalem have cast their heads down to the ground.

11 CAPH. My eyes have exhausted their tears. My internal organs have become disturbed. My liver has been poured out on the earth, over the grief of the daughter of my people, when the little ones and the infants passed away in the streets of the town.

12 LAMED. They said to their mothers, "Where is the wheat and the wine?" when they fell like the wounded in the streets of the city, when they breathed out their lives into the bosoms of their mothers.

13 MEM. To what shall I compare you, or to what shall I liken you, O daughter of Jerusalem? To what shall I equate you, so as to console you, O virgin daughter of Zion? For your destruction is as great as the sea. Who will cure you?

14 NUN. Your prophets have seen false and foolish things for you. And they have not laid open your iniquity, so as to provoke you to repentance. Yet they have seen for you false revelations and banishments.

15 SAMECH. All those who passed by the way have clapped their hands over you. They have hissed and shook their heads over the daughter of Jerusalem, saying, "Is this the city of perfect dignity, the joy of all the earth?"

16 PHE. All your enemies have opened their mouth over you. They have hissed and gnashed their teeth, and they said: "We will devour her. Yes, this is the day we waited for. We have found it, we have seen it."

17 AIN. The Lord has done what he decided to do. He has fulfilled his word, which he instructed since the days of antiquity. He has destroyed, and he has not been lenient, and he has caused the enemy to rejoice over you, and he has exalted the horn of your adversaries.

18 SADE. Their heart cried out to the Lord from the walls of the daughter of Zion. Let tears run down like a torrent throughout the day and the night. Do not give rest to yourself, and do not allow the pupil of your eye to cease.

19 COPH. Rise up. Give praise in the night, in the first of the watches. Pour out your heart like water before the sight of the Lord. Lift up your hands to him on behalf of the souls of your little ones, who have passed away from famine at the head of all the crossroads.

20 RES. O Lord, see and consider those whom you have made into a such vintage. So then, shall women eat their own fruit, little ones measured by the palm of the hand? Shall priest and prophet be killed in the sanctuary of the Lord?

21 SIN. The boy and the old man lie down on the ground outside. My virgins and my youths have fallen by the sword. You have slain them in the day of your fury. You have struck down, and you have not shown pity.

22 THAU. You have called, as if to a day of solemnity, those who would terrify me all around. And there was no one, in the day of the fury of the Lord, who escaped or was left behind. Those whom I educated and nourished, my enemy has consumed.

Lamentations 3

1 ALEPH. I am a man watching my own poverty by the rod of his indignation.

2 ALEPH. He has driven me and led me into darkness, and not into light.

3 ALEPH. Against me only, he has turned and turned again his hand, all day long.

4 BETH. My skin and my flesh, he has made old; he has crushed my bones.

5 BETH. He has built all around me, and he has encircled me with gall and hardship.

6 BETH. He has gathered me into darkness, like those who are forever dead.

7 GHIMEL. He has built against me all around, so that I may not depart. He has increased the burden of my confinement.

8 GHIMEL. Yet even when I cry out and beg, he excludes my prayer.

9 GHIMEL. He has enclosed my ways with square stones; he has subverted my paths.

10 DALETH. He has become to me like a bear lying in ambush, like a lion in hiding.

11 DALETH. He has subverted my paths, and he has broken me. He has placed me in desolation.

12 DALETH. He has bent his bow, and he has positioned me like a target for his arrows.

13 HE. He has shot into my kidneys the daughters of his quiver.

14 HE. I have become a derision to all my people, their song throughout the day.

15 HE. He has filled me with bitterness; he has inebriated me with wormwood.

16 VAU. And he has broken each one of my teeth; he has fed me with ashes.

17 VAU. And my soul has been driven away from peace; I have forgotten what is good.

18 VAU. And I said, "My end and my hope from the Lord has perished."

19 ZAIN. Remember my poverty and my transgression, the wormwood and the gall.

20 ZAIN. I will call to mind the past, and my soul shall languish within me.

21 ZAIN. These recollections are in my heart; therefore, I shall hope.

22 HETH. By the mercies of the Lord, we are not consumed. For his compassion has not passed away.

23 HETH. I know it at first light; great is your faithfulness.

24 HETH. "The Lord is my portion," said my soul. Because of this, I will wait for him.

25 TETH. The Lord is good to those who hope in him, to the soul that seeks him.

26 TETH. It is good to stand ready in silence for the salvation of God.

27 TETH. It is good for a man, when he has carried the yoke from his youth.

28 JOD. He shall sit solitary and silent. For he has lifted it upon himself.

29 JOD. He shall place his mouth in the dirt, if perhaps there may be hope.

30 JOD. He shall give his cheek to those who strike him; he shall be saturated with reproaches.

31 CAPH. For the Lord will not rebuke forever.

32 CAPH. For, if he has cast down, he will also have compassion, according to the multitude of his mercies.

33 CAPH. For he has not humiliated from his heart, nor has he thrown aside the sons of men,

34 LAMED. as if to crush under his feet all the prisoners of the land,

35 LAMED. as if to turn aside the judgment of a man in the sight of the presence of the Most High,

36 LAMED. as if to pervert a man in his judgment: the Lord does not do this.

37 MEM. Who is this, who said to do what the Lord did not command?

38 MEM. Does not both misfortune and good proceed from the mouth of the Most High?

39 MEM. Why has a living man murmured, a man suffering for his sins?

40 NUN. Let us examine our ways, and seek out, and return to the Lord.

41 NUN. Let us lift up our hearts, with our hands, toward the Lord in the heavens.

42 NUN. We have acted sinfully, and we have provoked to wrath. About this, you are relentless.

43 SAMECH. You have covered us in your fury, and you have struck us. You have killed, and have not spared.

44 SAMECH. You have set a cloud opposite you, lest our prayer pass through.

45 SAMECH. In the midst of the peoples, you have uprooted me and cast me out.

46 PHE. All our enemies have opened their mouths over us.

47 PHE. Prediction has become for us a dread, and a snare, and a grief.

48 PHE. My eye has brought forth streams of water at the contrition of the daughter of my people.

49 AIN. My eye has been afflicted, and it has not been quieted, because there would be no rest

50 AIN. until the Lord looked down and saw from the heavens.

51 AIN. My eye has exhausted my soul over every one of the daughters of my city.

52 SADE. My enemies have chased me, and they have caught me like a bird, without reason.

53 SADE. My life has fallen into a pit, and they have placed a stone over me.

54 SADE. The waters have flooded over my head. I said, "I am lost."

55 COPH. I called upon your name, O Lord, from the furthest pit.

56 COPH. You have heard my voice. Do not turn away your ear from my sobbing and my cries.

57 COPH. You drew near in the daytime, when I called upon you. You said, "Fear not."

58 RES. You have judged, O Lord, the case of my soul. You are the Redeemer of my life.

59 RES. You have seen, O Lord, their iniquity against me. Judge my case.

60 RES. You have seen all their fury, every one of their thoughts is against me.

61 SIN. You have heard their reproach, O Lord, all their thoughts are against me.

62 SIN. The lips of those who rise up against me, and their meditations, are against me all day long.

63 SIN. Watch their sitting down and their rising up: I am their psalm.

64 THAU. You shall pay a recompense to them, O Lord, according to the works of their hands.

65 THAU. You shall give them a heavy shield of the heart: your hardship.

66 THAU. You shall pursue them in fury, and you shall destroy them under the heavens, O Lord.

Lamentations 4

1 ALEPH. O how the gold has become dulled, the finest color has been altered, the stones of the sanctuary have been scattered at the head of every street.

2 BETH. The famous sons of Zion, and those clothed with the foremost gold: how they have become like earthen vessels, the work of the hands of a potter.

3 GHIMEL. Yet even savages expose their breast and give milk to their young. But the daughter of my people is cruel, like the ostrich in the desert.

4 DALETH. The tongue of the infant adheres to his palate out of thirst. The little ones have asked for bread, and there was no one to break it for them.

5 HE. Those who were fed indulgently have passed away in the roads. Those who were nourished with saffron have welcomed filth.

6 VAU. And the iniquity of the daughter of my people has been made greater than the sin of Sodom, which was overthrown in a moment, and yet hands did not take captives in her.

7 ZAIN. Her Nazirites were whiter than snow, shinier than milk, more ruddy than ancient ivory, more beautiful than sapphire.

8 HETH. Their face has been blacked more than coals, and they are not recognized in the streets. Their skin has adhered to their bones; it dried out and became like wood.

9 TETH. It was better for those slain by the sword, than for those put to death by famine. For these waste away, being consumed by the sterility of the land.

10 JOD. The hands of pitiable women have boiled their sons. They became their food in the grief of the daughter of my people.

11 CAPH. The Lord has completed his fury; he has poured out the wrath of his indignation. And he has kindled a fire in Zion, and it has devoured its foundations.

12 LAMED. The kings of the earth, and all the inhabitants of the world, did not believe that the adversary and the enemy would enter through the gates of Jerusalem.

13 MEM. It is because of the sins of her prophets, and the iniquities of her priests, who have shed the blood of the just in her midst.

14 NUN. They have wandered in the streets like the blind; they have been defiled with blood. And when they were not able, they held their garments.

15 SAMECH. "Go back, you polluted ones!" they cried out to them. "Go back, go away, do not touch!" Of course, they argued, and being removed, they said among the Gentiles, "He will no longer dwell among them."

16 PHE. The face of the Lord has divided them. He will no longer respect them. They were not ashamed before the faces of the priests, nor did they take pity on the elderly.

17 AIN. While we were still standing, our eyes failed, expecting help for us in vain, when we looked attentively toward a nation that was not able to save.

18 SADE. Our footsteps have slipped on the paths of our own streets. Our end draws near. Our days have been completed, for our end has arrived.

19 COPH. Our persecutors have been swifter than the eagles of the sky. They have been pursuing us above the mountains; they have lain in wait for us in the desert.

20 RES. The spirit of our mouth, Christ the Lord, has been captured by our sins; to him, we said, "In your shadow, we will live among the Gentiles."

21 SIN. Be glad and rejoice, O daughter of Edom, who dwells in the Land of Uz. The cup will also pass to you; you will be inebriated as well as naked.

22 THAU. Your iniquity has been completed, O daughter of Zion. He will no longer send you away to captivity. He has visited your iniquity, O daughter of Edom; he has uncovered your sins.

Lamentations 5

1 Remember, O Lord, what has befallen us. Consider and look kindly upon our disgrace.

2 Our inheritance has been turned over to foreigners; our houses to outsiders.

3 We have become orphans without a father; our mothers are like widows.

4 We paid for our drinking water. We acquired our wood for a price.

5 We were dragged by our necks. Being weary, no rest was given to us.

6 We have given our hand to Egypt and to the Assyrians, so that we may be satisfied with bread.

7 Our fathers have sinned, and are not. And we have carried their iniquities.

8 Servants have become rulers over us. There was no one to redeem us from their hand.

9 We obtained our bread at the risk of our lives, before the face of the sword, in the wilderness.

10 Our skin was burned, as if by an oven, before the face of the tempest of the famine.

11 They humiliated the women in Zion and the virgins in the cities of Judah.

12 The leaders were suspended by their hand. They were not ashamed before the faces of the elders.

13 They have sexually abused the adolescents, and the children were corrupted in the wood.

14 The elders have ceased from the gates, the youths from the choir of the psalms.

15 The gladness of our heart has failed, our singing has been turned into mourning.

16 The crown has fallen from our head. Woe to us, for we have sinned.

17 Because of this, our heart became gloomy; for this reason, our eyes have been darkened:

18 because of mount Zion, because it was ruined. Foxes have wandered upon it.

19 But you, O Lord, shall remain for eternity, your throne from generation to generation.

20 Why would you forget us forever? Why would you forsake us for a long time?

21 Convert us, O Lord, to you, and we shall be converted. Renew our days, as from the beginning.

22 But you have utterly rejected us; you are vehemently angry against us.

Ezekiel 1

1 And it happened that, in the thirtieth year, in the fourth month, on the fifth of the month, when I was in the midst of the captives beside the river Chebar, the heavens were opened, and I saw the visions of God.

2 On the fifth of the month, the same is the fifth year of the transmigration of king Joachin,

3 the word of the Lord came to Ezekiel, a priest, the son of Buzi, in the land of the Chaldeans, next to the river Chebar. And the hand of the Lord was over him there.

4 And I saw, and behold, a whirlwind arrived from the north. And a great cloud, wrapped in fire and brightness, was all around it. And from its midst, that is, from the midst of the fire, there was something with the appearance of amber.

5 And in its midst, there was the likeness of four living creatures. And this was their appearance: the likeness of a man was in them.

6 Each one had four faces, and each one had four wings.

7 Their feet were straight feet, and the sole of their foot was like the sole of the foot of a calf, and they sparkled with the appearance of glowing brass.

8 And they had the hands of a man under their wings on the four sides. And they had faces with the wings on the four sides.

9 And their wings were joined to one another. They did not turn as they went. Instead, each one advanced before his face.

10 But as for the likeness of their face, there was the face of a man, and the face of a lion on the right of each of the four, then the face of an ox on the left of each of the four, and the face of an eagle above each of the four.

11 Their faces and their wings were extended above: two wings of each one were joined together, and two covered their bodies.

12 And each one of them advanced before his face. Wherever the impetus of the spirit was to go, there they went. And they did not turn as they advanced.

13 And as for the likeness of the living creatures, their appearance was like that of burning coals of fire, and like the appearance of lamps. This was the vision dashing in the midst of the living creatures, a bright fire, with lightning going forth from the fire.

14 And the living creatures went and returned like flashes of lightning.

15 And as I beheld the living creatures, there appeared above the earth, next to the living creatures, one wheel having four faces.

16 And the appearance of the wheels and their work was like the appearance of the sea. And each of the four were similar to one another. And their appearance and work was like a wheel in the center of a wheel.

17 Going forth, they went by means of their four parts. And they did not turn as they went.

18 Also, the size and height and appearance of the wheels was dreadful. And the entire body was full of eyes all around each of the four.

19 And when the living creatures advanced, the wheels advanced together with them. And when the living creatures were lifted up from the earth, the wheels, too, were lifted up at the same time.

20 Wherever the spirit went, as the spirit was going forth to that place, the wheels, too, were lifted up together, so as to follow them. For the spirit of life was in the wheels.

21 When going forth, they went forth, and when standing still, they stood still. And when they were lifted up from the earth, the wheels, too, were lifted up together, so as to follow them. For the spirit of life was in the wheels.

22 And above the heads of the living creatures was the likeness of a firmament: similar to crystal, but dreadful to behold, and extending over their heads from above.

23 And their wings were straight under the firmament, one toward the other. One of them was covered by two wings on his body, and the other was covered similarly.

24 And I heard the sound of their wings, like the sound of many waters, like the sound of the sublime God. When they walked, it was like the sound of a multitude, like the sound of an army. And when they stood still, their wings were let down.

25 For when a voice came from above the firmament, which was over their heads, they stood still, and they put down their wings.

26 And above the firmament, which was suspended over their heads, there was the likeness of a throne, with the appearance of the sapphire stone. And over the likeness of the throne, there was a likeness with the appearance of a man above it.

27 And I saw something with the appearance of amber, with the likeness of fire within it and all around it. And from his waist and upward, and from his waist downward, I saw something with the appearance of fire shining all around.

28 There was the appearance of the rainbow, as when it is in a cloud on a rainy day. This was the appearance of the splendor on every side.

Ezekiel 2

1 This was the vision of the likeness of the glory of the Lord. And I saw, and I fell on my face, and I heard the voice of someone speaking. And he said to me: "Son of man, stand on your feet, and I will speak with you."

2 And after this was spoken to me, the Spirit entered into me, and he set me on my feet. And I heard him speaking to me,

3 and saying: "Son of man, I am sending you to the sons of Israel, to an apostate nation, which has withdrawn from me. They and their fathers have betrayed my covenant, even to this day.

4 And those to whom I am sending you are sons with a hard face and an unyielding heart. And you shall say to them: 'Thus says the Lord God.'

5 Perhaps it may be that they will hear, and perhaps they may be quieted. For they are a provoking house. And they shall know that there has been a prophet in their midst.

6 But as for you, son of man, you should not fear them, and you should not dread their words. For you are among unbelievers and subversives, and you are living with scorpions. You should not fear their words, and you should not dread their faces. For they are a provoking house.

7 Therefore, you shall speak my words to them, so that perhaps they may hear and be quieted. For they are provoking.

8 But as for you, son of man, listen to all that I say to you. And do not choose to be provoking, as that house is a provoker. Open your mouth, and eat whatever I give to you."

9 And I looked, and behold: a hand was put forth toward me; there was a scroll rolled up in it. And he spread it out before me, and there was writing on the inside and on the outside. And there were written in it lamentations, and verses, and woes.

Ezekiel 3

1 And he said to me: "Son of man, eat whatever you will find; eat this scroll, and, going forth, speak to the sons of Israel."

2 And I opened my mouth, and he fed me that scroll.

3 And he said to me: "Son of man, your stomach shall eat, and your interior shall be filled with this scroll, which I am giving to you." And I ate it, and in my mouth it became as sweet as honey.

4 And he said to me: "Son of man, go to the house of Israel, and you shall speak my words to them.

5 For you will be sent, not to a people of profound words or of an unknown language, but to the house of Israel,

6 and not to many peoples of profound words or of an unknown language, whose words you would not be able to understand. But if you were sent to them, they would listen to you.

7 Yet the house of Israel is not willing to listen to you. For they are not willing to listen to me. Certainly, the entire house of Israel has a brazen forehead and a hardened heart.

8 Behold, I have made your face stronger than their faces, and your forehead harder than their foreheads.

9 I have made your face like hardened iron and like flint. You should not fear them, and you should not have dread before their face. For they are a provoking house."

10 And he said to me: "Son of man, listen with your ears, and take into your heart, all my words, which I am speaking to you.

11 And go forth and enter to those of the transmigration, to the sons of your people. And you shall speak to them. And you shall say to them: 'Thus says the Lord God.' Perhaps it may be that they will listen and be quieted."

12 And the Spirit took me up, and I heard behind me the voice of a great commotion, saying, "Blessed is the glory of the Lord from his place,"

13 and the voice of the wings of the living creatures striking against one another, and the voice of the wheels following the living creatures, and the voice of a great commotion.

14 Then the Spirit lifted me and took me away. And I went forth in bitterness, with the indignation of my spirit. For the hand of the Lord was with me, strengthening me.

15 And I went to those of the transmigration, to the stockpile of new crops, to those who were living beside the river Chebar. And I sat where they were sitting. And I remained there for seven days, while mourning in their midst.

16 Then, when seven days had passed, the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

17 "Son of man, I have made you a watchman for the house of Israel. And so, you shall listen to the word from my mouth, and you shall announce it to them from me.

18 If, when I say to the impious man, 'You shall certainly die,' you do not announce it to him, and you do not speak so that he may turn aside from his impious way and live, then the same impious man will die in his iniquity. But I will attribute his blood to your hand.

19 But if you announce it to the impious man, and he is not converted from his impiety and from his impious way, then indeed he will die in his iniquity. But you will have delivered your own soul.

20 Moreover, if the just man turns aside from his justice and commits iniquity, I will place a stumbling block before him. He shall die, because you have not announced to him. He shall die in his sin, and his justices that he did shall not be remembered. Yet truly, I will attribute his blood to your hand.

21 But if you announce to the just man, so that the just man may not sin, and he does not sin, then he shall certainly live, because you have announced to him. And you will have delivered your own soul."

22 And the hand of the Lord was over me. And he said to me: "Rise up, and go out to the plain, and there I will speak with you."

23 And I rose up, and I went out to the plain. And behold, the glory of the Lord was standing there, like the glory that I saw beside the river Chebar. And I fell upon my face.

24 And the Spirit entered into me, and set me upon my feet. And he spoke to me, and he said to me: "Enter and enclose yourself in the midst of your house.

25 And as for you, son of man, behold: they shall put chains upon you and bind you with them. And you shall not go out from their midst.

26 And I will cause your tongue to adhere to the roof of your mouth. And you will be mute, not like a man who reproaches. For they are a provoking house.

27 But when I will speak to you, I will open your mouth, and you shall say to them: 'Thus says the Lord God.' Whoever is listening, let him hear. And whoever is quieted, let him be quieted. For they are a provoking house."

Ezekiel 4

1 "And as for you, son of man, take up for yourself a tablet, and you shall set it before you. And you shall draw upon it the city of Jerusalem.

2 And you shall set up a blockade against it, and you shall build fortifications, and you shall put together a rampart, and you shall encamp opposite it, and you shall place battering rams around it.

3 And you shall take up for yourself an iron frying pan, and place it as an iron wall between you and the city. And harden your face against it, and it shall be under a siege, and you shall surround it. This is a sign to the house of Israel.

4 And you shall sleep on your left side. And you shall place the iniquities of the house of Israel on it by the number of days that you will sleep on it. And you shall take upon yourself their iniquity.

5 For I have given to you the years of their iniquity, by the number of the days: three hundred and ninety days. And you shall bear the iniquity of the house of Israel.

6 And when you will have completed this, you shall sleep a second time, on your right side, and you shall assume the iniquity of the house of Judah for forty days: one day for each year; one day, I say, for each year, have I given to you.

7 And you shall turn your face toward the siege of Jerusalem, and your arm shall be extended. And you shall prophesy against it.

8 Behold, I have surrounded you with chains. And you shall not turn yourself from one side to the other side, until you have completed the days of your siege.

9 And you shall take for yourself wheat, and barley, and beans, and lentils, and millet, and vetch. And you shall set them in one vessel, and you shall make for yourself bread by the number of days that you will sleep upon your side: three hundred and ninety days shall you shall eat from it.

10 But your food, which you will eat, shall be in weight twenty staters a day. You shall eat it from time to time.

11 And you shall drink water by measure, one sixth part of a hin. You shall drink it from time to time.

12 And you shall eat it like barley bread baked under ashes. And you shall cover it, in their sight, with the dung that goes out of a man."

13 And the Lord said: "So shall the sons of Israel eat their bread, polluted among the Gentiles, to whom I will cast them out."

14 And I said: "Alas, alas, alas, O Lord God! Behold, my soul has not been polluted, and from my infancy even until now, I have not eaten anything that has died of itself, nor that which has been torn up by beasts, and no unclean flesh at all has entered into my mouth."

15 And he said to me: "Behold, I have given to you cow manure in place of human dung, and you shall make your bread with it."

16 And he said to me: "Son of man, behold: I will crush the staff of bread in Jerusalem. And they will eat bread by weight and with anxiety. And they will drink water by measure and with anguish.

17 So then, when bread and water fail, each one may fall against his brother. And they shall waste away in their iniquities."

Ezekiel 5

1 "And as for you, son of man, obtain for yourself a sharp knife for shaving hair, and you shall take it and draw it across your head and across your beard. And you shall obtain for yourself a balance for weighing, and you shall divide the hair.

2 A third part you shall burn with fire in the midst of the city, according to the completion of the days of the siege. And you shall take a third part, and you shall cut it with the knife all around. Yet truly, the other third, you shall scatter to the wind, for I will unsheathe the sword after them.

3 And you shall take from there a small number. And you shall bind them in the end of your cloak.

4 And again, you shall take from them, and you shall throw them into the midst of the fire, and you shall burn them with fire. And from it, there shall go forth a fire to the entire house of Israel."

5 Thus says the Lord God: "This is Jerusalem. I have placed her in the midst of the Gentiles and of the lands all around her.

6 And she has despised my judgments, so as to be more impious than the Gentiles, and my precepts, more so than the lands that are all around her. For they have cast aside my judgments, and they have not walked in my precepts."

7 For this reason, thus says the Lord God: "Since you have surpassed the Gentiles who are all around you, and have not walked in my precepts, and have not accomplished my judgments, and have not even acted in accord with the judgments of the Gentiles who are all around you:

8 therefore, thus says the Lord God: Behold, I am against you, and I myself will accomplish judgments in your midst, in the sight of the Gentiles.

9 And I will do in you what I have not done before, and the likes of which I will not do again, because of all your abominations.

10 Therefore, the fathers shall consume the sons in your midst, and the sons shall consume their fathers. And I will execute judgments in you, and I will winnow your entire remnant in every wind.

11 Therefore, as I myself live says the Lord God, because you have violated my sanctuary with all your offenses and with all your abominations, I also will break into pieces, and my eye will not be lenient, and I will not take pity.

12 One third part of you will die by pestilence or be consumed by famine in your midst. And one third part of you will fall by the sword all around you. Yet truly, one third part of you I will scatter to every wind, and I will unsheathe the sword after them.

13 And I will fulfill my fury, and I will cause my indignation to rest upon them, and I will be consoled. And they shall know that I, the Lord, have spoken in my zeal, when I will have fulfilled my indignation in them.

14 And I will make you desolate, and a disgrace among the Gentiles, who are all around you, in the sight of all who pass by.

15 And you shall be a disgrace and a blasphemy, an example and an astonishment, among the Gentiles, who are all around you, when I will have executed judgments in you, in fury and in indignation and with rebukes of wrath.

16 I, the Lord, have spoken. At that time, I will send among them the most grievous arrows of famine, which shall bring death, and which I will send so that I may destroy you. And I will gather a famine over you, and I will crush the staff of bread among you.

17 And I will send among you famine and very harmful beasts, even unto utter ruin. And pestilence and blood shall pass through you. And I will bring the sword over you. I, the Lord, have spoken."

Ezekiel 6

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, set your face toward the mountains of Israel, and you shall prophesy against them,

3 and you shall say: O mountains of Israel, listen to the word of the Lord God! Thus says the Lord God to the mountains and hills and cliffs and valleys: Behold, I will lead over you the sword. And I will destroy your exalted places.

4 And I will demolish your altars. And your graven images will be broken apart. And I will throw down your slain before your idols.

5 And I will lay the dead bodies of the sons of Israel before the face of your idols. And I will scatter your bones around your altars.

6 In all of your habitations, the cities will be made desolate, and the exalted places will be torn down and scattered. And your altars will be broken and destroyed. And your idols will cease to exist. And your shrines will be crushed. And your works will be wiped away.

7 And the slain will fall in your midst. And you shall know that I am the Lord.

8 And I will leave among you those who will escape the sword among the Gentiles, when I will have dispersed you upon the earth.

9 And your liberated shall remember me among the nations to which they were led away as captives. For I have crushed their heart, which fornicated and withdrew from me, and their eyes, which fornicated after their idols. And they will be displeased with themselves over the evils that they have done by all their abominations.

10 And they shall know that I, the Lord, have not spoken in vain, that I would do this evil to them."

11 Thus says the Lord God: "Strike with your hand, and stomp with your foot, and say: 'Alas, to all the abominations of the evils of the house of Israel!' For they will fall by the sword, by famine, and by pestilence.

12 Whoever is far away will die of pestilence. But whoever is near will fall by the sword. And whoever remains and is besieged will die by famine. And I will fulfill my indignation among them.

13 And you shall know that I am the Lord, when your slain will be in the midst of your idols, all around your altars, on every exalted hill, and on the summits of all the mountains, and under every dense tree, and under every leafy oak: the places where they burned sweet-smelling incense to all their idols.

14 And I will extend my hand over them. And I will make the earth desolate and destitute: from the desert of Riblah to all their dwelling places. And they shall know that I am the Lord."

Ezekiel 7

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "And as for you, son of man: Thus says the Lord God to the land of Israel: The end is coming, the end is coming, over the four regions of the earth.

3 Now the end is over you, and I will send my fury upon you. And I will judge you according to your ways. And I will place all your abominations before you.

4 And my eye will not be lenient over you, and I will not take pity. Instead, I will set your ways upon you, and your abominations will be in your midst. And you shall know that I am the Lord."

5 Thus says the Lord God: "One affliction, behold, one affliction is approaching.

6 The end is coming, the end is coming. It has been vigilant against you. Behold, it is approaching.

7 Destruction is coming over you, who live upon the earth. The time is approaching, the day of slaughter is near, and it is not of the glory of the mountains.

8 Now, very soon, I will pour out my wrath upon you, and I will fulfill my fury in you. And I will judge you according to your ways, and I will set upon you all your crimes.

9 And my eye will not be lenient, nor will I take pity. Instead, I will place your ways upon you, and your abominations will be in your midst. And you shall know that I am the Lord, who is striking.

10 Behold, the day! Behold, it approaches! Destruction has gone forth, the rod has blossomed, arrogance has germinated.

11 Iniquity has risen up into a rod of impiety. There shall be nothing left of them, and of their people, and of the sound of them. And there shall be no rest for them.

12 The time is approaching; the day is very near. Whoever buys should not rejoice. And whoever sells should not mourn. For wrath is over all of their people.

13 For whoever sells will not return to what he has sold, but as yet their life will be among the living. For the vision concerning their entire multitude will not turn back. And man will not be strengthened in the iniquity of his life.

14 Sound the trumpet! Let everyone be prepared! And yet there is no one who may go to battle. For my wrath is over all their people.

15 The sword is outside, and the pestilence and the famine are inside. Whoever is in the field will die by the sword. And whoever is in the city will be devoured by the pestilence and the famine.

16 And those who flee from among them will be saved. And they will be among the mountains, like doves in steep valleys, with everyone of them trembling, each one because of his iniquity.

17 All hands will be weakened, and all knees will flow with water.

18 And they will wrap themselves with haircloth, and dread will cover them. And shame will be upon every face, and baldness will be upon all of their heads.

19 Their silver will be thrown away, and their gold will be like a dunghill. Their silver and their gold will have no power to free them in the day of the fury of the Lord. They will not satisfy their soul, and their bellies will not be filled, because of the scandal of their iniquity.

20 And they have set arrogance as the ornament of their necklaces, and they have made images of their abominations and graven idols. Because of this, I have let it be an uncleanness for them.

21 And I will give it into the hands of foreigners as a spoil, and to the impious of the earth as a prey, and they will defile it.

22 And I will avert my face from them, and they will violate my place of mystery. And untamed persons will enter into it, and they will defile it.

23 Cause it to be closed. For the land has been filled with the judgment of blood, and the city is full of iniquity.

24 And I will lead in the most sinful among the Gentiles, and they will possess their houses. And I will cause the arrogance of the powerful to be quieted. And they will possess their sanctuaries.

25 When anguish overwhelms them, they will seek peace, and there will be none.

26 Disturbance will follow after disturbance, and rumor after rumor. And they will seek the vision of the prophet, and the law will perish from the priest, and counsel will perish from the elders.

27 The king will mourn, and the prince will be clothed with grief, and the hands of the people of the earth will be greatly disturbed. I will act toward them in accord with their own way, and I will judge them in accord with their own judgments. And they shall know that I am the Lord."

Ezekiel 8

1 And it happened that, in the sixth year, in the sixth month, on the fifth of the month, I was sitting in my house, and the elders of Judah were sitting before me, and the hand of the Lord God fell upon me there.

2 And I saw, and behold, there was an image with the appearance of fire. From the appearance of his waist, and downward, there was fire. And from his waist, and upward, there was the appearance of splendor, like the sight of amber.

3 And as the image of a hand went out, it took hold of me by a lock of my head. And the Spirit lifted me up between earth and heaven. And he brought me into Jerusalem, within a vision of God, next to the inner gate that looked toward the north, where there was stationed an idol of rivalry, so as to provoke an envious emulation.

4 And behold, the glory of the God of Israel was there, in accord with the vision that I had seen in the plain.

5 And he said to me: "Son of man, lift up your eyes to the way of the north." And I lifted up my eyes to the way of the north. And behold, from the north of the gate of the altar was the idol of rivalry, at the same entrance.

6 And he said to me: "Son of man, you see what these ones are doing, the great abominations that the house of Israel is committing here. Do you not think, then, that I should withdraw far away from my own sanctuary? But if you turn again, you will see even greater abominations."

7 And he led me in by the door of the atrium. And I saw, and behold, there was an opening in the wall.

8 And he said to me: "Son of man, dig in the wall." And when I had dug in the wall, there appeared one door.

9 And he said to me: "Enter and see the most wicked abominations which they are committing here."

10 And entering, I saw, and behold, every kind of image of reptiles and animals, the abominations, and all of the idols of the house of Israel were depicted on the wall all around, throughout the entire place.

11 And there were seventy men out of the elders of the house of Israel, with Jaazaniah, the son of Shaphan, standing in their midst, and they stood before the pictures. And each one had a censer in his hand. And a cloud of smoke rose up from the incense.

12 And he said to me: "Certainly, son of man, you see what the elders of the house of Israel are doing in the darkness, each one while hidden in his chamber. For they say: 'The Lord does not see us. The Lord has forsaken the earth.' "

13 And he said to me: "If you turn again, you will see even greater abominations, which these ones are committing."

14 And he led me in through the door of the gate of the Lord's house, which looked toward the north. And behold, women were sitting there, mourning for Adonis.

15 And he said to me: "Certainly, son of man, you have seen. But if you turn again, you will see even greater abominations than these."

16 And he led me into the inner atrium of the house of the Lord. And behold, at the door of the temple of the Lord, between the vestibule and the altar, there were about twenty-five men with their backs toward the temple of the Lord, and their faces toward the east. And they were adoring toward the rising of the Sun.

17 And he said to me: "Certainly, son of man, you have seen. Can this be so trivial to the house of Judah, when they commit these abominations, just as they have committed here, that, having filled the earth with iniquity, they now turn to provoke me? And behold, they are applying a branch to their nose.

18 Therefore, I also will act toward them in my fury. My eye will not be lenient, nor will I take pity. And when they will have cried out to my ears with a loud voice, I will not heed them."

Ezekiel 9

1 And he cried out in my ears with a loud voice, saying: "The visitations of the city have drawn near, and each one has equipment for killing in his hand."

2 And behold, six men were approaching from the way of the upper gate, which looks to the north. And each one had equipment for killing in his hand. Also, one man in their midst was clothed with linen, and an instrument for writing was at his waist. And they entered and stood beside the bronze altar.

3 And the glory of the Lord of Israel was taken up, from the cherub upon which he was, to the threshold of the house. And he called out to the man who was clothed with linen and had an instrument for writing at his waist.

4 And the Lord said to him: "Cross through the middle of the city, in the center of Jerusalem, and seal a Tau upon the foreheads of the grieving men, who are mourning over all the abominations which are being committed in its midst."

5 And he said to the others, in my hearing: "Cross through the city after him, and strike! Your eye shall not be lenient, and you shall not take pity.

6 Kill, even to utter destruction, old men, young men, and virgins, little ones, and women. But all upon whom see the Tau, you shall not kill. And begin from my sanctuary." Therefore, they began with the men among the elders, who were before the face of the house.

7 And he said to them: "Defile the house, and fill its courts with the slain! Go forth!" And they went forth and struck down those who were in the city.

8 And when the slaughter was completed, I remained. And I fell upon my face, and crying out, I said: "Alas, alas, alas, O Lord God! Will you now destroy the entire remnant of Israel, by pouring out your fury upon Jerusalem?"

9 And he said to me: "The iniquity of the house of Israel, and of Judah, is vast and exceedingly great, and the land has been filled with blood, and the city has been filled with what is abhorrent. For they have said: 'The Lord has forsaken the earth,' and, 'The Lord does not see.'

10 Therefore, my eye will not be lenient, and I will not take pity. I will repay their own way upon their head."

11 And behold, the man who was clothed with linen, who had a writing instrument at his back, responded a word, saying: "I have done just as you instructed me."

Ezekiel 10

1 And I saw, and behold, in the firmament that was over the heads of the cherubim, there appeared above them something like the sapphire stone, with the sight of the likeness of a throne.

2 And he spoke to the man who was clothed with linen, and he said: "Enter, between the wheels that are under the cherubim, and fill your hand with the coals of fire that are between the cherubim, and pour them upon the city." And he entered, in my sight.

3 Now the cherubim were standing before the right side of the house, when the man entered. And a cloud filled the inner court.

4 And the glory of the Lord was lifted up, from above the cherubim, to the threshold of the house. And the house was filled with the cloud. And the court was filled with the splendor of the glory of the Lord.

5 And the sound of the wings of the cherubim was heard even in the outer court, like the voice of Almighty God speaking.

6 And when he had instructed the man who was clothed with linen, saying, "Take fire from the midst of the wheels that are between the cherubim," he entered and stood next to the wheel.

7 And one cherub extended his hand, from the midst of the cherubim, to the fire that was between the cherubim. And he took and gave it into the hands of the one who was clothed with linen, and he accepted it and went forth.

8 And there appeared amid the cherubim the likeness of the hand of a man, under their wings.

9 And I saw, and behold, there were four wheels beside the cherubim. One wheel was next to one cherub, and another wheel was next to another cherub. And the appearance of the wheels was like the sight of the chrysolite stone.

10 And in their appearance, each one of the four were similar, as if a wheel were in the midst of a wheel.

11 And when they went, they advanced in four parts. And they did not turn as they went. Instead, to the place to which they were inclined to go at first, the rest also followed, and they did not turn back.

12 And their entire body, with their necks and their hands and their wings and the circles, were full of eyes all around the four wheels.

13 And in my hearing, he called these wheels: "constantly changing."

14 Now each one had four faces. One face was the face of a cherub, and the second face was the face of a man, and in the third was the face of a lion, and in the fourth was the face of an eagle.

15 And the cherubim were lifted up. This is the living creature, which I had seen beside the river Chebar.

16 And when the cherubim advanced, the wheels also went beside them. And when the cherubim lifted up their wings in order to be raised up from the earth, the wheels did not remain behind, but they also were beside them.

17 When they were standing, these stood still. And when they were lifted up, these were lifted up. For the spirit of life was in them.

18 And the glory of the Lord went forth from the threshold of the temple, and stood above the cherubim.

19 And the cherubim, lifting up their wings, were raised up from the earth in my sight. And as they went away, the wheels also followed. And it stood at the entrance to the east gate of the house of the Lord. And the glory of the God of Israel was over them.

20 This is the living creature, which I saw under the God of Israel beside the river Chebar. And I understood that they were cherubim.

21 Each one had four faces, and each one had four wings. And the likeness of the hand of a man was under their wings.

22 And, concerning the appearance of their faces, these were the same faces that I had seen beside the river Chebar, and the gaze and force of each one of them was to go before his face.

Ezekiel 11

1 And the Spirit lifted me up, and he brought me to the east gate of the house of the Lord, which looks toward the rising of the sun. And behold, at the entrance to the gate were twenty-five men. And I saw, in their midst, Jaazaniah, the son of Azzur, and Pelatiah, the son of Benaiah, leaders of the people.

2 And he said to me: "Son of man, these are men who devise iniquity. And they offer a wicked counsel in this city,

3 saying: 'Was it so long ago that houses were being built? This city is a cooking pot, and we are the meat.'

4 Therefore, prophesy against them, prophesy, O son of man."

5 And the Spirit of the Lord fell upon me, and he said to me: "Speak: Thus says the Lord: So have you spoken, O house of Israel. And I know the thoughts of your heart.

6 You have killed very many in this city, and you have filled its streets with the slain.

7 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: Your slain, whom you have placed in its midst, these are the meat, and this city is the cooking pot. And I will draw you out of its midst.

8 You have dread the sword, and so I will lead the sword over you, says the Lord God.

9 And I will cast you out of its midst, and I will give you over to the hand of the enemies, and I will execute judgments among you.

10 You will fall by the sword. I will judge you within the borders of Israel. And you shall know that I am the Lord.

11 This city will not be a cooking pot for you, and you will not be like meat in its midst. I will judge you within the borders of Israel.

12 And you shall know that I am the Lord. For you have not walked in my precepts, and you have not accomplished my judgments. Instead, you have acted in accord with the judgments of the Gentiles, who are all around you."

13 And it happened that, when I prophesied, Pelatiah, the son of Benaiah, died. And I fell upon my face, and I cried out with a loud voice, and I said: "Alas, alas, alas, O Lord God! Will you cause the consummation of the remnant of Israel?"

14 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

15 "Son of man, your brothers, the men among your close relatives, your brothers and the entire house of Israel, are all among those to whom the inhabitants of Jerusalem have said: 'Withdraw far from the Lord; the earth has been given to us as a possession.'

16 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: Since I have caused them to be far away, among the Gentiles, and since I have dispersed them among the lands, I will be a little sanctuary for them within the lands to which they have gone.

17 Because of this, say to them: Thus says the Lord God: I will gather you from among the peoples, and I will unite you, from the lands into which you were dispersed, and I will give the soil of Israel to you.

18 And they shall go to that place, and they shall remove all the offenses and all its abominations from that place.

19 And I will give them one heart. And I will distribute a new spirit to their interior. And I will take away the heart of stone from their body. And I will give them a heart of flesh.

20 So may they may walk in my precepts, and observe my judgments, and accomplish them. And so may they be my people, and I will be their God.

21 But as for those whose heart walks after their offenses and abominations, I will set their own way upon their head, says the Lord God."

22 And the cherubim lifted up their wings, and the wheels with them. And the glory of the God of Israel was above them.

23 And the glory of the Lord ascended from the midst of the city and stood above the mountain, which is to the east of the city.

24 And the Spirit lifted me up, and he brought me into Chaldea, to those of the transmigration, in a vision, in the Spirit of God. And the vision that I had seen was raised up, away from me.

25 And I spoke, to those of the transmigration, all the words of the Lord that he had revealed to me.

Ezekiel 12

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, you live in the midst of a provoking house. They have eyes to see, and they do not see; and ears to hear, and they do not hear. For they are a provoking house.

3 As for you, then, son of man, prepare for yourself the supplies for traveling far away, and travel away in the daytime in their sight. And you shall travel from your place to another place in their sight, so that perhaps they may consider it. For they are a provoking house.

4 And you shall carry your supplies outside, like the supplies of one who is traveling far away, in the daytime in their sight. Then you shall go forth in the evening in their presence, just as one goes forth who is moving far away.

5 Dig for yourself through the wall, before their eyes. And you shall go out through it.

6 In their sight, you shall be carried on shoulders, you shall be carried in the dark. You shall cover your face, and you shall not see the ground. For I have appointed you as a portent for the house of Israel."

7 Therefore, I did just as he had instructed me. I brought out my supplies in the daytime, like the supplies of one who is moving far away. And in the evening, I dug myself through the wall by hand. And I went out in the dark, and I was carried on shoulders, in their sight.

8 And the word of the Lord came to me, in the morning, saying:

9 "Son of man, has not the house of Israel, the provoking house, said to you: 'What are you doing?'

10 Say to them: Thus says the Lord God: This is the burden concerning my leader who is in Jerusalem, and concerning the entire house of Israel, who are in their midst.

11 Say: I am your portent. Just as I have done, so shall it be done to them. They will be taken captive and moved far away.

12 And the leader who is in their midst will be carried on shoulders; he will go forth in darkness. They will dig through the wall, so that they may lead him away. His face will be covered, so that he may not see the land with his eye.

13 And I will extend my net over him, and he will be captured in my dragnet. And I will lead him to Babylon, into the land of the Chaldeans, but he himself will not see it. And there he shall die.

14 And all who are around him, his guards and his companies, I will scatter into every wind. And I will unsheathe the sword after them.

15 And they shall know that I am the Lord, when I will have dispersed them among the Gentiles, and will have sowed them among the lands.

16 And I will leave behind a few men of them, apart from the sword, and the famine, and the pestilence, so that they may declare all their wicked deeds among the Gentiles, to whom they will go. And they shall know that I am the Lord."

17 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

18 "Son of man, eat your bread in consternation. Moreover, drink your water hurriedly and in sorrow.

19 And say to the people of the land: Thus says the Lord God, to those who are living in Jerusalem, in the land of Israel: They shall eat their bread in anxiety, and drink their water in desolation, so that the land may be desolate before its multitude, because of the iniquity of all who are living in it.

20 And cities that are now inhabited will become desolate, and the land will be forsaken. And you shall know that I am the Lord."

21 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

22 "Son of man, what is this proverb that you have in the land of Israel? saying: 'The days shall be extended in length, and every vision shall perish.'

23 Therefore, say to them: Thus says the Lord God: I will cause this proverb to cease, and it shall no longer be a common saying in Israel. And tell them that the days are approaching, and the word of every vision.

24 For there shall be no longer be any empty visions, nor any ambiguous divination in the midst of the sons of Israel.

25 For I, the Lord, will speak. And whatever word I will speak, it shall be done, and it shall not be delayed any more. Instead, in your days, O provoking house, I will speak a word and do it, says the Lord God."

26 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

27 "Son of man, behold the house of Israel, those who are saying: 'The visions that this one sees is many days away,' and, 'This man prophesies about times that are far away.'

28 Because of this, say to them: Thus says the Lord God: No word of mine will be delayed any longer. The word that I will speak will be fulfilled, says the Lord God."

Ezekiel 13

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, prophesy to the prophets of Israel who are prophesying, and you shall say to those who prophesy from their own heart: Hear the word of the Lord:

3 Thus says the Lord God: Woe to the foolish prophets, who are following their own spirit, and who see nothing.

4 Your prophets, O Israel, were like foxes in the deserts.

5 You have not gone up against the adversary, and you have not established a wall for the house of Israel, so as to stand in battle on the day of the Lord.

6 They see emptiness, and they foretell falsehoods, saying, 'The Lord says,' though the Lord has not sent them. And they continued to affirm what they said.

7 Have you not seen a futile vision and spoken a lying divination? And yet you say, 'The Lord says,' though I have not spoken.

8 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: Since you have spoken emptiness and have seen falsehoods, therefore: behold, I am against you, says the Lord God.

9 And my hand will be over the prophets who are seeing emptiness and divining lies. They shall not be in the council of my people, and they shall not be written in the writing of the house of Israel. Neither shall they enter into the land of Israel. And you shall know that I am the Lord God.

10 For they have deceived my people, saying, 'Peace,' and there is no peace. And they have built a wall, but they have covered it in clay without straw.

11 Say to those who spread mortar without mixing, that it will fall apart. For there will be an inundating rain, and I will cause full-grown hailstones to rush down from above, and a windstorm to dissipate it.

12 So then, behold: when the wall has fallen, will it not be said to you: 'Where is the mortar with which you covered it?'

13 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: And I will cause a violent wind to burst forth in my indignation, and there will be an inundating rain in my fury, and great hailstones in wrath, to consume.

14 And I will destroy the wall that you have covered without tempering it. And I will level it to the ground, and its foundation will be revealed. And it will fall and be consumed in its midst. And you shall know that I am the Lord.

15 And I will fulfill my indignation against the wall, and against those who cover it without mixing the mortar, and I will say to you: The wall is no more, and those who covered it are no more:

16 the prophets of Israel, who prophesy to Jerusalem, and who see visions of peace for her when there is no peace, says the Lord God.

17 And as for you, son of man, set your face against the daughters of your people, who prophesy from their own heart. And prophesy about them,

18 and say: Thus says the Lord God: Woe to those who sew together little pillows under every forearm, and who make little cushions for the heads of every stage of life, in order to capture souls. And when they have seized the souls of my people, they became the life of their souls.

19 And they violated me among my people, for the sake of a handful of barley and a fragment of bread, so that they would kill the souls that should not die, and enliven the souls that should not live, lying to my people who believe in falsehoods.

20 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: Behold, I am against your little pillows, with which you catch flying souls. And I will tear them away from your arms. And I will release the souls that you are capturing, the souls that should fly.

21 And I will tear away your little cushions. And I will free my people from your hand. And they shall no longer be a prey in your hands. And you shall know that I am the Lord.

22 For by deception you have caused the heart of the just to grieve, whom I would not sadden. And I have strengthened the hands of the impious, so that he would not be turned back from his evil way and live.

23 Therefore, you shall not see emptiness, and you shall not divine divinations, any more. And I will rescue my people from your hand. And you shall know that I am the Lord."

Ezekiel 14

1 And men among the elders of Israel came to me, and they sat down before me.

2 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

3 "Son of man, these men have placed their uncleanness in their hearts, and they have stationed the scandal of their iniquities before their face. So why should I respond when they inquire of me?

4 Because of this, speak to them, and you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord God: The man, the man of the house of Israel, who places his uncleanness in his heart, and who stations the scandal of his iniquities before his face, and who approaches a prophet, so as to inquire of me through him: I, the Lord, will respond to him in accord with the multitude of his uncleannesses,

5 so that the house of Israel may be seized within their own heart, by which they have withdrawn from me to all their idols.

6 Because of this, say to the house of Israel: Thus says the Lord God: Be converted, and withdraw from your idols, and turn your faces away from all your abominations.

7 For the man, the man of the house of Israel, and the new arrival among the converts who may be in Israel, if he is alienated from me, and he sets his idols in his heart, and he stations the scandal of his iniquity before his face, and he approaches the prophet, so that he may inquire of me through him: I, the Lord, will respond to him through myself.

8 And I will set my face against that man, and I will make him an example and a proverb. And I will perish him from the midst of my people. And you shall know that I am the Lord.

9 And when a prophet has gone astray and has spoken a word: I, the Lord, have deceived that prophet. And I will extend my hand over him, and I will wipe him away from the midst of my people, Israel.

10 And they shall bear their iniquity. In accord with the iniquity of the one who inquires, so shall the iniquity of the prophet be.

11 So may the house of Israel no longer go astray from me, nor be polluted by all their transgressions. Instead, may they be my people, and may I be their God, says the Lord of hosts."

12 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

13 "Son of man, when a land will have sinned against me, so that it transgresses grievously, I will extend my hand over it, and I will crush the staff of its bread. And I will send a famine upon it, and I will destroy from it both man and beast.

14 And if these three men, Noah, Daniel, and Job, were in it, they would deliver their own souls by their justice, says the Lord of hosts.

15 And if I also lead in very harmful beasts upon the land, so that I devastate it, and it becomes impassable, so that no one may cross through it because of the beasts,

16 if these three men were in it, as I live, says the Lord God, they will deliver neither sons, nor daughters. But only they themselves will be delivered, for the land shall be desolated.

17 Or if I lead in the sword upon that land, and if I say to the sword, 'Pass through the land,' and so I destroy from it both man and beast,

18 and if these three men were in its midst, as I live, says the Lord God, they will deliver neither sons, nor daughters, but only they themselves will be delivered.

19 Then, if I also send the pestilence upon that land, and I pour out my indignation upon it with blood, so that I take away from it both man and beast,

20 and if Noah, and Daniel, and Job were in its midst, as I live, says the Lord God, they will deliver neither son, nor daughter, but they will deliver only their own souls by their justice.

21 For thus says the Lord God: Even though I will send upon Jerusalem my four most grievous judgments, sword and famine and harmful beasts and pestilence, so that I destroy from it both man and beast,

22 yet still there shall be left within it some who will be saved, who shall lead away their own sons and daughters. Behold, they will enter to you, and you will see their way and their accomplishments. And you shall be consoled concerning the evil that I have brought upon Jerusalem, concerning all the things that I have brought to bear upon it.

23 And they shall console you, when you see their ways and their accomplishments. And you shall know that I have not acted to no purpose in all that I have done within it, says the Lord God."

Ezekiel 15

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, what can be made from the stalk of a vine, compared to all the plants of the woods that are among the trees of the forests?

3 Can any wood be taken from it, so that it may be made into a work, or formed into a peg so as to hang some kind of vessel upon it?

4 Behold, it is used in the fire as fuel. The fire consumes both its ends; and its middle is reduced to ashes. So how can it be useful for any work?

5 Even when it was whole, it was unsuitable for a work. How much more so, when fire has devoured it and burned it up, will nothing of it be useful?

6 Therefore, thus says the Lord God: Like the stalk of the vine among the trees of the forests, which I have given to be devoured by fire, so will I deliver the inhabitants of Jerusalem.

7 And I will set my face against them. They will go away from fire, and yet fire will consume them. And you shall know that I am the Lord, when I will have set my face against them,

8 and when I will have made their land impassable and desolate. For they have stood forth as transgressors, says the Lord God."

Ezekiel 16

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, make known to Jerusalem her abominations.

3 And you shall say: Thus says the Lord God to Jerusalem: Your root and your lineage is from the land of Canaan; your father was an Amorite, and your mother was a Cethite.

4 And when you were born, on the day of your nativity, your umbilical cord was not cut, and you were not washed with water for health, nor salted with salt, nor wrapped with cloths.

5 No eye took pity on you, so as to do even one of these things to you, out of compassion for you. Instead, you were cast upon the face of the earth, in the abjection of your soul, on the day when you were born.

6 But, passing by you, I saw that you were wallowing in your own blood. And I said to you, when you were in your blood: 'Live.' I tell you that I said to you, in your blood: 'Live.'

7 I multiplied you like the seedling of the field. And you were multiplied and became great, and you advanced and arrived at the ornament of a woman. Your breasts rose up, and your hair grew. And you were naked and full of shame.

8 And I passed by you and saw you. And behold, your time was the time of lovers. And I spread my garment over you, and I covered your disgrace. And I swore to you, and I entered into a covenant with you, says the Lord God, and you became mine.

9 And I washed you with water, and I cleansed you of your blood. And I anointed you with oil.

10 And I covered you with embroidery, and I put violet shoes upon you, and I wrapped you in fine linen, and I clothed you with delicate garments.

11 I adorned you with ornaments, and I put bracelets upon your hands and a necklace around your neck.

12 And I put gold upon your face, and earrings in your ears, and a beautiful crown upon your head.

13 And you were adorned with gold and silver, and you were clothed in fine linen, woven with many colors. You ate fine flour, and honey, and oil. And you became very beautiful. And you advanced to royal power.

14 And your renown went forth among the Gentiles, because of your beauty. For you were perfected by my beauty, which I had placed upon you, says the Lord God.

15 But, having confidence in your own beauty, you fornicated in your fame. And you presented your fornication to every passer-by, so as to become his.

16 And taking from your garments, you made for yourself exalted things, having sewed together disparate pieces. And you fornicated upon them, in a way that has not been done before, nor will be in the future.

17 And you took your beautiful items, made of my gold and my silver, which I gave to you, and you made for yourself images of men, and you fornicated with them.

18 And you used your multicolored vestments to cover these things. And you placed my oil and my incense before them.

19 And my bread, which I gave to you, the fine flour, and the oil, and the honey, by which I nourished you, you placed in their sight as a sweet fragrance. And so it was done, says the Lord God.

20 And you took your sons and your daughters, whom you bore for me, and you immolated them to be devoured. Is your fornication a small matter?

21 You have immolated my sons, and you have consecrated and delivered my sons to them.

22 And after all your abominations and fornications, you have not remembered the days of your youth, when you were naked and full of shame, wallowing in your own blood.

23 And it happened that, after all your wickedness, (woe, woe to you, says the Lord God)

24 you built for yourself a brothel, and you made for yourself a place of prostitution in every street.

25 At the head of every way, you set up a banner of your prostitution. And you caused your beauty to become abominable. And you distributed your feet to every passer-by. And you multiplied your fornications.

26 And you fornicated with the sons of Egypt, your neighbors, who have large bodies. And you multiplied your fornications, so as to provoke me.

27 Behold, I will extend my hand over you, and I will take away your justification. And I will give you to the souls of those who hate you, the daughters of the Philistines, who are ashamed of your wicked way.

28 You also fornicated with the sons of the Assyrians, for you were not yet done. And after you fornicated, even then, you were not satisfied.

29 And you multiplied your fornications in the land of Canaan with the Chaldeans. And even then, you were not satisfied.

30 With what can I cleanse your heart, says the Lord God, since you do all these things, the works of a woman who is a shameless prostitute?

31 For you have built your brothel at the head of every way, and you have made your exalted place on every street. And you have not even been like a choosy prostitute, increasing her price,

32 but instead like a woman who is an adulteress, who prefers strangers to her own husband.

33 Wages are given to all prostitutes. But you have given wages to all your lovers, and you have given gifts to them, so that they would enter to you from every side, in order to fornicate with you.

34 And it is done with you, in your fornications, contrary to the custom of women, and even after you, there will be no such fornication. For in as much as you have given payment, and not taken payment, what has been done in you is the contrary."

35 Because of this, O harlot, listen to the word of the Lord.

36 Thus says the Lord God: "Because your money has been poured out, and your disgrace has been uncovered, in your fornications with your lovers and with the idols of your abominations, in the blood of your sons, whom you gave to them:

37 Behold, I will gather all your lovers, with whom you have united, and all those whom you have loved, together with all those whom you have hated. And I will gather them together against you on every side. And I will uncover your disgrace before them, and they will see all your indecency.

38 And I will judge you with the judgment of adulteresses and of those who shed blood. And I will give you over to blood, in fury and in zeal.

39 And I will deliver you into their hands. And they will destroy your brothel and demolish your place of prostitution. And they will strip you of your vestments. And they will take away the ornaments of your beauty. And they will leave you behind, naked and full of disgrace.

40 And they will lead over you a multitude. And they will stone you with stones, and massacre you with their swords.

41 And they will burn up your houses with fire, and they will carry out judgments against you in the sight of many women. And you will cease from fornication, and no longer give payment.

42 And my indignation will be quieted in you. And my zeal will be taken from you. And I will rest, and no longer be angry.

43 For you have not remembered the days of your youth, and you have provoked me in all these things. Because of this, I also have delivered all your ways upon your head, says the Lord God, but I have not acted in accord with your wickedness in all your abominations.

44 Behold, all who speak a common proverb will take this up against you, saying: 'Like the mother, so also is her daughter.'

45 You are your mother's daughter, for she cast away her husband and her children. And you are the sister of your sisters, for they cast away their husbands and their children. Your mother was a Cethite, and your father was an Amorite.

46 And your older sister is Samaria, she and her daughters are those who live to your left. But your younger sister, who lives to your right, is Sodom and her daughters.

47 But neither have you walked in their ways. For you have done only a little less compared to their wickedness. You have acted almost more wickedly, in all your ways, than they have acted.

48 As I live, says the Lord God, your sister Sodom herself, and her daughters, have not done as you and your daughters have done.

49 Behold, this was the iniquity of Sodom, your sister: arrogance, indulgence in bread and abundance, and the idleness of her and her daughters; and they did not reach out their hand to the needy and the poor.

50 And they were exalted, and they committed abominations before me. And so I took them away, just as you have seen.

51 But Samaria has not committed even half of your sins. For you have exceeded them in your wickedness, and you have justified your sisters by all your abominations, which you have wrought.

52 Therefore, you also bear your shame, for you have exceeded your sisters with your sins, acting more wickedly than they did. So they have been justified above you. By this also, you are confounded, and you bear your disgrace, for you have justified your sisters.

53 But I will convert and restore them, by converting Sodom with her daughters, and by converting Samaria and her daughters. And I will convert your return in their midst.

54 So may you bear your disgrace and be confounded over all that you have done, consoling them.

55 And your sister Sodom and her daughters will return to their ancient state. And Samaria and her daughters will return to their ancient state. And you and your daughters will be returned to your ancient state.

56 Your sister Sodom was not heard from your mouth, then, in the day of your pride,

57 before your malice was revealed, as it is at this time, with the reproach of the daughters of Syria and of all the daughters of Palestine, who surround you, who encircle you on every side.

58 You have borne your wickedness and your disgrace, says the Lord God."

59 For thus says the Lord God: "I will act toward you, just as you have despised the oath, so that you would make void the covenant.

60 And I will remember my covenant with you in the days of your youth. And I will raise up for you an everlasting covenant.

61 And you shall remember your ways and be confounded, when you will have received your sisters, your elder with your younger. And I will give them to you as daughters, but not by your covenant.

62 And I will raise up my covenant with you. And you shall know that I am the Lord.

63 So may you remember and be confounded. And it will no longer be for you to open your mouth, because of your shame, when I will have been pacified toward you over all that you have done, says the Lord God."

Ezekiel 17

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, propose an enigma and describe a parable to the house of Israel,

3 and you shall say: Thus says the Lord God: A large eagle, with great wings and elongated pinions, full of feathers with many colors, came to Lebanon. And he took the kernel of the cedar.

4 He tore off the summit of its branches, and he transported it to the land of Canaan; he placed it in a city of merchants.

5 And he took from the seed of the land and placed it in the ground for seed, so that it might take firm root above many waters; he placed it at the surface.

6 And when it had germinated, it increased into a more extensive vine, low in height, with its branches facing toward itself. And its roots were underneath it. And so, it became a vine, and sprouted branches, and produced shoots.

7 And there was another large eagle, with great wings and many feathers. And behold, this vine seemed to bend its roots towards him, extending its branches toward him, so that he might irrigate it from the garden of its germination.

8 It had been planted in a good land, above many waters, so that it would produce branches and bear fruit, so that it would become a large vine.

9 Speak: Thus says the Lord God: What if it does not prosper? Should he not pull up its roots, and strip off its fruit, and dry up all the branches that it has produced, and let it wither, though he is without a strong arm and without many people to pull it up by the root?

10 Behold, it has been planted. What if it does not prosper? Should it not be dried up when the burning wind touches it, and should it not wither in the garden of its germination?"

11 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

12 "Say to the provoking house: Do you not know what these things signify? Say: Behold, the king of Babylon arrives in Jerusalem. And he will take away its king and princes, and he will lead them away to himself in Babylon.

13 And he will take one from the offspring of the king, and he will strike a pact with him and receive an oath from him. Moreover, he will take away the strong ones of the land,

14 so that it may be a lowly kingdom, and may not lift itself up, and may instead keep his pact and serve it.

15 But, withdrawing from him, he sent messengers to Egypt, so that it would give him horses and many people. Should he who has done these things prosper and obtain safety? And should he who has broken the pact go free?

16 As I live, says the Lord God, in the place of the king, who appointed him as king, whose oath he has made void, and whose pact he has broken, under which he was living with him, in the midst of Babylon, he shall die.

17 And not with a great army, nor with many people will Pharaoh undertake a battle against him, when he will cast up ramparts and build defenses, in order to put to death many souls.

18 For he has despised an oath, in that he broke the pact. And behold, he had given his hand. And so, since he has done all these things, he shall not escape.

19 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: As I live, I will place upon his head the oath that he has spurned and the pact that he has betrayed.

20 And I will spread my net over him, and he will be captured in my dragnet. And I will lead him into Babylon, and I will judge him there for the transgression by which he has despised me.

21 And all his fugitives, with all his procession, will fall by the sword. Then the remainder will be scattered into every wind. And you shall know that I, the Lord, have spoken."

22 Thus says the Lord God: "I myself will take from the kernel of the exalted cedar, and I will establish it. I will tear off a tender twig from the top of its branches, and I will plant it on a mountain, lofty and exalted.

23 On the sublime mountains of Israel, I will plant it. And it shall spring forth in buds and bear fruit, and it shall be a great cedar. And all the birds will live under it, and every bird will make its nest under the shadow of its branches.

24 And all the trees of the regions will know that I, the Lord, have brought low the sublime tree, and have exalted the lowly tree, and have dried up the green tree, and have caused the dry tree to flourish. I, the Lord, have spoken and acted."

Ezekiel 18

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Why is it that you circulate among yourselves this parable, as a proverb in the land of Israel, saying: 'The fathers ate a bitter grape, and the teeth of the sons have been affected.'

3 As I live, says the Lord God, this parable shall no longer be a proverb for you in Israel.

4 Behold, all souls are mine. Just as the soul of the father is mine, so also is the soul of the son. The soul that sins, the same shall die.

5 And if a man is just, and he accomplishes judgment and justice,

6 and if he does not eat upon the mountains, nor lifted up his eyes to the idols of the house of Israel, and if he has not violated the wife of his neighbor, nor approached a menstruating woman,

7 and if he has not grieved any man, but has restored the collateral to the debtor, if he has seized nothing by violence, has given his bread to the hungry, and has covered the naked with a garment,

8 if he has not lent upon usury, nor taken any increase, if he has averted his hand from iniquity, and has executed true judgment between man and man,

9 if he has walked in my precepts and kept my judgments, so that he acts in accord with truth, then he is just; he shall certainly live, says the Lord God.

10 But if he raises a son who is a robber, who sheds blood, and who does any of these things,

11 (even though he himself does not do any of these things,) and who eats upon the mountains, and who defiles the wife of his neighbor,

12 who grieves the needy and the poor, who seizes with violence, who does not restore the collateral, and who lifts up his eyes to idols, committing abomination,

13 who lends upon usury, and who takes an increase, then shall he live? He shall not live. Since he has done all these detestable things, he shall certainly die. His blood shall be upon him.

14 But if he raises a son, who, seeing all his father's sins that he has done, is afraid and so does not act in a way similar to him,

15 who does not eat upon the mountains, nor lift up his eyes to the idols of the house of Israel, and who does not violate the wife of his neighbor,

16 and who has not grieved any man, nor withheld the collateral, nor seized by violence, but instead has given his bread to the hungry, and has covered the naked with a garment,

17 who has averted his hand from injuring the poor, who has not taken usury and an overabundance, who has acted according to my judgments and walked in my precepts, then this one shall not die for the iniquity of his father; instead, he shall certainly live.

18 As for his father, because he oppressed and did violence to his brother, and worked evil in the midst of his people, behold, he has died by his own iniquity.

19 And you say, 'Why has not the son borne the iniquity of the father?' Clearly, since the son has worked judgment and justice, has observed all my precepts, and has done them, he shall certainly live.

20 The soul that sins, the same shall die. The son shall not bear the iniquity of the father, and the father shall not bear the iniquity of the son. The justice of the just man shall be upon himself, but the impiety of the impious man shall be upon himself.

21 But if the impious man does penance for all his sins which he has committed, and if he keeps all my precepts, and accomplishes judgment and justice, then he shall certainly live, and he shall not die.

22 I will not remember all his iniquities, which he has worked; by his justice, which he has worked, he shall live.

23 How could it be my will that an impious man should die, says the Lord God, and not that he should be converted from his ways and live?

24 But if a just man turns himself away from his justice, and does iniquity in accord with all the abominations that the impious man so often does, why should he live? All his justices, which he has accomplished, shall not be remembered. By the transgression, in which he has transgressed, and by his sin, in which he has sinned, by these he shall die.

25 And you have said, 'The way of the Lord is not fair.' Therefore, listen, O house of Israel. How could it be that my way is not fair? And is it not instead your ways that are perverse?

26 For when the just man turns himself away from his justice, and commits iniquity, he shall die by this; by the injustice that he has worked, he shall die.

27 And when the impious man turns himself away from his impiety, which he has done, and accomplishes judgment and justice, he shall cause his own soul to live.

28 For by considering and turning himself away from all his iniquities, which he has worked, he shall certainly live, and he shall not die.

29 And yet the sons of Israel say, 'The way of the Lord is not fair.' How could it be that my ways are not fair, O house of Israel? And is it not instead your ways that are perverse?

30 Therefore, O house of Israel, I will judge each one according to his ways, says the Lord God. Be converted, and do penance for all your iniquities, and then iniquity will not be your ruin.

31 Cast all your transgressions, by which you have transgressed, away from you, and make for yourselves a new heart and a new spirit. And then why should you die, O house of Israel?

32 For I do not desire the death of one who dies, says the Lord God. So return and live."

Ezekiel 19

1 "And as for you, take up a lament over the leaders of Israel,

2 and you shall say: Why did your mother, the lioness, recline among the male lions, and raise her little ones in the midst of young lions?

3 And she led away one of her little ones, and he became a lion. And he learned to seize prey and to consume men.

4 And the Gentiles heard about him, and they seized him, but not without receiving wounds. And they led him away in chains to the land of Egypt.

5 Then, when she had seen that she was weakened, and that her hope had perished, she took one of her little ones, and appointed him as a lion.

6 And he advanced among the lions, and he became a lion. And he learned to seize prey and to devour men.

7 He learned to make widows, and to lead their citizens into the desert. And the land, with its plenitude, was made desolate by the voice of his roaring.

8 And the Gentiles came together against him, on every side, from the provinces, and they spread their net over him; by their wounds, he was captured.

9 And they put him into a cage; they led him in chains to the king of Babylon. And they cast him into a prison, so that his voice would no longer be heard upon the mountains of Israel.

10 Your mother is like a vine, in your blood, planted by the water; her fruit and her branches have increased because of many waters.

11 And her strong branches were made into scepters for the rulers, and her stature was exalted among the branches. And she saw her own loftiness among the multitude of her branches.

12 But she was uprooted in wrath, and cast upon the ground. And the burning wind dried up her fruit. Her robust branches withered and were dried up. A fire consumed her.

13 And now she has been transplanted into the desert, into a land impassable and dry.

14 And a fire has gone forth from a rod of her branches, which has consumed her fruit. And there is no strong branch in her to become a scepter for the rulers. This is a lamentation, and it shall be a lamentation."

Ezekiel 20

1 And it happened that, in the seventh year, in the fifth month, on the tenth of the month, men from the elders of Israel arrived, so that they might inquire of the Lord, and they sat before me.

2 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

3 "Son of man, speak to the elders of Israel, and you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord God: Have you arrived in order to inquire of me? As I live, I will not answer you, says the Lord God.

4 If you judge them, if you judge, O son of man, reveal to them the abominations of their fathers.

5 And you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord God: In the day when I chose Israel, and I lifted up my hand on behalf of the stock of the house of Jacob, and I appeared to them in the land of Egypt, and I lifted up my hand on their behalf, saying, 'I am the Lord your God,'

6 in that day, I lifted up my hand for their sake, so that I would lead them away from the land of Egypt, into a land which I had provided for them, flowing with milk and honey, which was singular among all lands.

7 And I said to them: 'Let each one cast away the offenses of his eyes, and do not choose to defile yourselves with the idols of Egypt. I am the Lord your God.'

8 But they provoked me, and they were not willing to listen to me. Each one of them did not cast away the abominations of his eyes, nor did they leave behind the idols of Egypt. And so, I said that I would pour out my indignation upon them, and fulfill my wrath against them, in the midst of the land of Egypt.

9 But I acted for the sake of my name, so that it would not be violated in the sight of the Gentiles, in the midst of whom they were, and among whom I appeared to them, so that I might lead them away from the land of Egypt.

10 Therefore, I cast them out of the land of Egypt, and I led them away into the desert.

11 And I gave them my precepts, and I revealed to them my judgments, which, if a man does them, he shall live by them.

12 Moreover, I also gave to them my Sabbaths, so that these would be a sign between me and them, and so that they would know that I am the Lord, who sanctifies them.

13 But the house of Israel provoked me in the desert. They did not walk in my precepts, and they cast aside my judgments, which, if a man does them, he shall live by them. And they grievously violated my Sabbaths. Therefore, I said that I would pour out my fury upon them in the desert, and that I would consume them.

14 But I acted for the sake of my name, lest it be violated before the Gentiles, from whom I cast them out, in their sight.

15 And so I lifted up my hand over them in the desert, so as not to lead them into the land that I had given to them, flowing with milk and honey, the foremost of all lands.

16 For they cast aside my judgments, and they did not walk in my precepts, and they violated my Sabbaths. For their heart went after idols.

17 Yet my eye was lenient concerning them, so that I did not utterly destroy them, nor did I consume them in the desert.

18 Then I said to their sons in the wilderness: 'Do not choose to advance by the precepts of your fathers, nor should you observe their judgments. And do not be defiled by their idols.

19 I am the Lord your God. Walk in my precepts, and observe my judgments, and accomplish them.

20 And sanctify my Sabbaths, so that these may be a sign between me and you, and so that you may know that I am the Lord your God.'

21 But their sons provoked me. They did not walk in my precepts. And they did not observe my judgments, so as to do them; for if a man does them, he shall live by them. And they violated my Sabbaths. And so, I threatened that I would pour out my fury upon them, and that I would fulfill my wrath among them in the desert.

22 But I turned aside my hand, and I acted for the sake of my name, so that it would not be violated before the Gentiles, from whom I cast them out, before their eyes.

23 Again, I lifted up my hand against them, in the wilderness, so that I would disperse them among the nations, and scatter them among the lands.

24 For they had not accomplished my judgments, and they had rejected my precepts, and they had violated my Sabbaths. And their eyes had been after the idols of their fathers.

25 Therefore, I also gave them precepts that were not good, and judgments by which they shall not live.

26 And I defiled them by their own gifts, when they offered everything that opened the womb, because of their offenses. And they shall know that I am the Lord.

27 For this reason, son of man, speak to the house of Israel, and you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord God. Yet also in this did your fathers blaspheme me, after they had spurned and despised me,

28 though I had led them into the land, about which I lifted up my hand, so that I might give it to them: They saw every lofty hill and every leafy tree, and there they immolated their victims, and there they presented the provocation of their oblations, and there they stationed their sweet fragrances, and poured out their libations.

29 And I said to them, 'What is exalted about the place to which you go?' And yet its name is called 'Exalted,' even to this day.

30 Because of this, say to the house of Israel: Thus says the Lord God: Certainly, you are defiled by the way of your fathers, and you have fornicated after their stumbling blocks.

31 And you are being defiled by all of your idols, even to this day, by the oblation of your gifts, when you lead your sons through the fire. And should I respond to you, O house of Israel? As I live, says the Lord God, I will not answer you.

32 And the plan of your mind will not occur, saying: 'We will be like the Gentiles, and like the families of the earth, so that we worship what is wood and stone.'

33 As I live, says the Lord God, I will reign over you with a strong hand, and with an outstretched arm, and with fury poured forth.

34 And I will lead you away from the peoples. And I will gather you from the lands into which you were dispersed. I will reign over you with a powerful hand, and with an outstretched arm, and with fury poured out.

35 And I will lead you into the desert of the peoples, and there I will enter into judgment with you, face to face.

36 Just as I contended in judgment against your fathers in the desert of the land of Egypt, so also will I enter into judgment with you, says the Lord God.

37 And I will subject you to my scepter, and I will lead you into the bonds of the covenant.

38 And I will select, from among you, the transgressors and the impious. And I will lead them away from the land of their sojourn, but they shall not enter into the land of Israel. And you shall know that I am the Lord.

39 And as for you, house of Israel: thus says the Lord God: Walk, each one of you, after your idols and serve them. But if in this also you will not listen to me, and you continue to defile my holy name with your gifts and with your idols,

40 on my holy mountain, on the exalted mountain of Israel, says the Lord God, there all the house of Israel shall serve me; all of them, I say, in the land in which they shall please me, and there I will require your first-fruits, and the foremost of your tithes, with all your sanctifications.

41 I will receive from you a fragrance of sweetness, when I will have led you away from the peoples, and gathered you from the lands into which you were dispersed. And I will be sanctified in you before the eyes of the nations.

42 And you shall know that I am the Lord, when I will have led you into the land of Israel, into the land about which I lifted up my hand, so that I would give it to your fathers.

43 And there you shall remember your ways and all your wickedness, by which you have been defiled. And you will be displeased with yourselves in your own sight, over all your evil deeds which you did.

44 And you shall know that I am the Lord, when I will have acted well toward you for the sake of my name, and not according to your evil ways, nor according to your very great wickedness, O house of Israel, says the Lord God."

45 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

46 "Son of man, set your face against the way of the south, and pour in drops toward Africa, and prophesy against the forest of the field of the meridian.

47 And you shall say to the meridian forest: Listen to the word of the Lord. Thus says the Lord God: Behold, I will kindle a fire in you, and I will burn up within you every green tree and every dry tree. The flame of the kindling will not be extinguished. And every face will be burned up within it, from the south, even to the north.

48 And all flesh will see that I, the Lord, have kindled it, and that it will not be extinguished."

49 And I said: "Alas, alas, alas, O Lord God! They are saying about me: 'Does this man not speak except through parables?' "

Ezekiel 21

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, set your face toward Jerusalem, and pour in drops toward the sanctuaries, and prophesy against the soil of Israel.

3 And you shall say to the land of Israel: Thus says the Lord God: Behold, I am against you, and I will cast my sword from its sheath, and I will slay the just and the impious among you.

4 But in as much as I have slain among you the just and the impious, for this reason my sword will go forth from its sheath against all flesh, from the south even to the north.

5 So may all flesh know that I, the Lord, have led my sword out of its sheath irrevocably.

6 And as for you, son of man, groan in the breaking of your back, and groan in bitterness before them.

7 And when they will say to you, 'Why are you groaning?' you shall say: 'On behalf of the report, For it is approaching. And every heart will waste away, and every hand will be broken, and every spirit will be weakened, and water will flow across every knee.' Behold, it is approaching and it will happen, says the Lord God."

8 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

9 "Son of man, prophesy, and you shall say: Thus says the Lord God: Speak: The sword! The sword has been sharpened and polished!

10 It has been sharpened, so that it may cut down victims! It has been polished, so that it may shine! You are disturbing the scepter of my son. You have cut down every tree.

11 And I have sent it to be made smooth, so that it may be handled. This sword has been sharpened, and it has been polished, so that it may be in the hand of the one who kills.

12 Cry out and wail, O son of man! For this has been done among my people, this is among all the leaders of Israel, who have fled. They have been handed over to the sword, with my people. Therefore, slap your thigh,

13 for it has been tested. And this one, when he will have overthrown the scepter, will not be, says the Lord God.

14 You therefore, O son of man, prophesy, and strike hand against hand, and let the sword be doubled, and let the sword of the slain be tripled. This is the sword of the great slaughter, which causes them to be utterly stupefied,

15 and to waste away in heart, and which multiplies ruin. At all their gates, I have presented the consternation of the sword, which has been sharpened and polished so as to shine, which has been dressed for the slaughter.

16 Be sharpened! Go to the right or to the left, whichever way is the desire of your face.

17 And then I will clap hand against hand, and I will fulfill my indignation. I, the Lord, have spoken."

18 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

19 "And as for you, son of man, set for yourself two ways, so that the sword of the king of Babylon may approach. Both shall go forth from one land. And with a hand, he will grasp and cast lots; he will cast at the head of the way of the community.

20 You shall appoint a way, so that the sword may approach to Rabbah of the sons of Ammon, or to Judah, into Jerusalem, greatly fortified.

21 For the king of Babylon stood at the fork, at the head of the two ways, seeking divination, shuffling arrows; he inquired of idols, and he consulted entrails.

22 To his right was set the divination over Jerusalem, to place battering rams so as to open a mouth for the slaughter, to lift up the voice of wailing, to place battering rams opposite the gates, to cast up a rampart, to build fortifications.

23 And he shall be, in their eyes, like someone consulting an oracle in vain, or imitating the leisure of Sabbaths. But he will call to mind iniquities, so that it will be captured.

24 Therefore, thus says the Lord God: Because you have been remembered in your iniquities, and you have revealed your betrayals, and your sins have appeared within all your plans, because, I say, you have been remembered, you will be captured by a hand.

25 But as for you, O impious leader of Israel, whose day has arrived that was predetermined at the time of iniquity:

26 Thus says the Lord God: Take away the diadem, remove the crown. Is this not what has exalted the lowly one, and brought low the sublime one?

27 Iniquity, iniquity, iniquity I will make it. And this was not done until the one arrived to whom judgment belongs, and I will hand it over to him.

28 And as for you, son of man, prophesy, and say: Thus says the Lord God to the sons of Ammon, and to their disgrace, and you shall say: O sword, O sword, unsheathe yourself so as to slay; polish yourself so as to kill and to shine,

29 while they look upon you in vain, and they divine lies, so that you may be given over to the necks of the wounded impious, whose day has arrived that was predetermined at the time of iniquity.

30 Be returned to your sheath! I will judge you in the place where you were created, in the land of your nativity.

31 And I will pour out upon you my indignation. In the fire of my fury, I will fan you, and I will give you over to the hands of cruel men, who have devised destruction.

32 You will be food for the fire; your blood will be in the midst of the land; you will be delivered to oblivion. For I, the Lord, have spoken."

Ezekiel 22

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "And you, son of man, should you not judge, should you not judge the city of blood?

3 And you shall reveal to her all her abominations. And you shall say: Thus says the Lord God: This is the city which sheds blood in her midst, so that her time may come, and which has made idols against herself, so that she may be defiled.

4 You have offended by your blood, which you shed from yourself. And you have been defiled by your idols which you yourself made. And you have caused your days to approach, and you have brought on the time of your years. Because of this, I have made you a disgrace to the Gentiles, and a derision to all the lands.

5 Those that are near and those that are far from you will triumph over you. You are filthy, infamous, great in destruction.

6 Behold, the leaders of Israel have each used his arm to shed blood within you.

7 They have abused father and mother within you. The new arrival has been oppressed in your midst. They have grieved the orphan and the widow among you.

8 You have spurned my sanctuaries, and you have defiled my Sabbaths.

9 Maligning men were within you, in order to shed blood, and they have eaten upon the mountains within you. They have worked wickedness in your midst.

10 They have uncovered the nakedness of their father within you. They have debased the uncleanness of the menstruous woman within you.

11 And each one has committed abomination with the wife of his neighbor. And the father-in-law has heinously defiled his daughter-in-law. The brother has oppressed his sister, the daughter of his father, within you.

12 They have accepted bribes among you to shed blood. You have received usury and superabundance, and in avarice you have oppressed your neighbors. And you have forgotten me, says the Lord God.

13 Behold, I have clapped my hands over your avarice, which you have worked, and over the blood that has been shed in your midst.

14 How can your heart endure, or your hands prevail, in the days that I will bring upon you? I, the Lord, have spoken, and I will act.

15 And I will disperse you among the nations, and I will scatter you among the lands, and I will cause your uncleanness to fade away from you.

16 And I will possess you in the sight of the Gentiles. And you shall know that I am the Lord."

17 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

18 "Son of man, the house of Israel has become like dross to me. All these are brass, and tin, and iron, and lead in the midst of the furnace; they have become like the dross of silver.

19 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: Since you have all turned into dross, therefore, behold, I will gather you together in the midst of Jerusalem,

20 just as they gather silver, and brass, and tin, and iron, and lead in the midst of the furnace, so that I may kindle in it a fire to melt it. So will I gather you together in my fury and in my wrath, and I will be quieted, and I will melt you down.

21 And I will gather you together, and I will burn you in the fire of my fury, and you will be melted in its midst.

22 Just as silver is melted in the midst of the furnace, so will you be in its midst. And you shall know that I am the Lord, when I will have poured out my indignation upon you."

23 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

24 "Son of man, say to her: You are a land unclean and not rained upon, in the day of fury.

25 There is a conspiracy of prophets in her midst. Like a lion, roaring and seizing the prey, they have devoured souls. They have taken riches and a price. They have multiplied widows in her midst.

26 Her priests have despised my law, and they have defiled my sanctuaries. They have held no distinction between holy and profane. And they have not understood the difference between defiled and clean. And they have averted their eyes from my Sabbaths. And I was profaned in their midst.

27 Her leaders in her midst are like wolves seizing the prey: to shed blood, and to perish souls, and to continually pursue profit with avarice.

28 And her prophets have covered them without tempering the mortar, seeing emptiness, and divining lies for them, saying, 'Thus says the Lord God,' when the Lord has not spoken.

29 The people of the land have oppressed with slander and have seized with violence. They have afflicted the needy and the poor, and they have oppressed the new arrival by accusations without judgment.

30 And I sought among them for a man who might set up a hedge, and stand in the gap before me on behalf of the land, so that I might not destroy it; and I found no one.

31 And so I poured out my indignation upon them; in the fire of my wrath I consumed them. I have rendered their own way upon their head, says the Lord God."

Ezekiel 23

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, two women were daughters of one mother,

3 and they fornicated in Egypt; they committed fornication in their youth. In that place, their breasts were conquered; the breasts of their adolescence were subdued.

4 Now their names were Oholah, the elder, and Oholibah, her younger sister. And I held them, and they bore sons and daughters. As for their names: Oholah is Samaria, and Oholibah is Jerusalem.

5 And then, Oholah committed fornication against me, and she acted madly with her lovers, with the Assyrians who approached her,

6 who were clothed with hyacinth: rulers and magistrates, passionate youths and all of the horsemen, mounted on horses.

7 And she distributed her fornications to those chosen men, all of them sons of the Assyrians. And she defiled herself with the uncleanness of all those whom she madly desired.

8 Moreover, she also did not abandon her fornications, which she had done in Egypt. For they also slept with her in her youth, and they bruised the breasts of her virginity, and they poured out their fornication upon her.

9 Because of this, I have delivered her into the hands of her lovers, into the hands of the sons of the Assur, whom she has lustfully desired.

10 They uncovered her shame; they took away her sons and daughters; and they slew her with the sword. And they became infamous women. And they carried out judgments in her.

11 And when her sister, Oholibah, had seen this, she was even more mad with lust than the other. And her fornication was beyond the fornication of her sister.

12 She shamelessly offered herself to the sons of the Assyrians, to the rulers and magistrates who brought themselves to her clothed with colorful garments, to the horsemen who were carried by horses, and to the youths, all of them exceptional in appearance.

13 And I saw that she had been defiled, and that they both took the same path.

14 And she increased her fornications. And when she had seen men depicted on the wall, the images of the Chaldeans, expressed in colors,

15 with belts wrapped around the waist, and with dyed headdresses on their heads, having seen the appearance of all the rulers, the likenesses of the sons of Babylon and of the land of the Chaldeans in which they were born,

16 she became mad for them with the desire of her eyes, and she sent messengers to them in Chaldea.

17 And when the sons of Babylon had gone to her, to the bed of breasts, they defiled her with their fornications, and she was polluted by them, and her soul was gorged by them.

18 Also, her fornications were uncovered, and her shame was revealed. And my soul withdrew from her, as my soul had withdrawn from her sister.

19 For she multiplied her fornications, remembering the days of her youth, in which she fornicated in the land of Egypt.

20 And she was mad with lust after lying with them, whose flesh is like the flesh of donkeys, and whose flow is like the flow of horses.

21 And you have revisited the crimes of your youth, when your breasts were conquered in Egypt, and the breasts of your adolescence were subdued.

22 Because of this, Oholibah, thus says the Lord God: Behold, I will raise up against you all of your lovers, with whom your soul has been gorged. And I will gather them together against you all around:

23 the sons of Babylon, and all the Chaldeans, the nobles, the sovereigns and princes, all the sons of the Assyrians, youths of exceptional form, all the rulers and magistrates, the leaders among leaders, and the renowned riders of horses.

24 And they will overwhelm you, well-equipped with chariot and wheel, a multitude of peoples. They will be armed against you on every side with armor and shield and helmet. And I will give judgment to their eyes, and they will judge you with their judgments.

25 And against you, I will set my zeal, which they will execute upon you with fury. They will cut off your nose and your ears. And what remains will fall by the sword. They will seize your sons and your daughters, and your youngest will be devoured by fire.

26 And they will strip you of your vestments, and take away the articles of your glory.

27 And I will cause your wickedness to cease from you, and your fornication to cease from the land of Egypt. Neither shall you lift up your eyes toward them, and you shall no longer remember Egypt.

28 For thus says the Lord God: Behold, I will deliver you into the hands of those whom you have hated, into the hands by which your soul has been gorged.

29 And they will act toward you with hatred, and they will take away all your labors, and they will send you away naked and filled with disgrace. And the shame of your fornication will be revealed: your crimes and your fornications.

30 They have done these things to you, because you have fornicated after the Gentiles, among whom you were defiled by their idols.

31 You have walked in the way of your sister, and so I will give her chalice into your hand.

32 Thus says the Lord God: You will drink the chalice of your sister, deep and wide. You will be held in derision and in ridicule, to a very great extent.

33 You will be filled with inebriation and sorrow, by the chalice of grief and sadness, by the chalice of your sister Samaria.

34 And you will drink it, and you will empty it, even to the dregs. And you will consume even its particles. And you will wound your own breasts. For I have spoken, says the Lord God.

35 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: Since you have forgotten me, and you have cast me behind your body, so also will you bear your wickedness and your fornications."

36 And the Lord spoke to me, saying: "Son of man, should you not judge Oholah and Oholibah, and announce to them their crimes?

37 For they are adulteresses, and blood is in their hands, and they have fornicated with their idols. Moreover, they have offered even their children, whom they bore for me, to them to be devoured.

38 But they have done even this to me: They have defiled my sanctuary on the same day, and they have profaned my Sabbaths.

39 And when they immolated their children to their idols, they also entered my sanctuary on the same day, so that they defiled it. They have done these things, even in the midst of my house.

40 They sent for men who were coming from far away, to whom they had sent a messenger. And so, behold, they arrived, those for whom you washed yourself, and smeared cosmetics around your eyes, and were adorned with feminine ornaments.

41 You sat upon a very beautiful bed, and a table was adorned before you, on which you placed my incense and my ointment.

42 And the voice of a multitude was exulting within her. And concerning certain men, who were being led out of a multitude of persons, and who were arriving from the desert, they placed bracelets on their hands and beautiful crowns on their heads.

43 And I said about her, as she was being worn away by her adulteries, 'Even now, she continues in her fornication!'

44 And they entered to her, as if to a kept woman. So did they enter to Oholah and Oholibah, nefarious women.

45 But there are just men; these shall judge them with the judgment of adulteresses and with the judgment of those who shed blood. For they are adulteresses, and blood is on their hands.

46 For thus says the Lord God: Lead upon them a multitude, and hand them over to tumult and to pillaging.

47 And may they be stoned with the stones of the peoples, and may they be pierced with their own swords. They will put to death their sons and daughters, and they will burn their houses with fire.

48 And I will take away wickedness from the land. And all women shall learn not to act according to their wickedness.

49 And they will set your own crimes upon you, and you will bear the sins of your idols. And you shall know that I am the Lord God."

Ezekiel 24

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, in the ninth year, in the tenth month, on the tenth day of the month, saying:

2 "Son of man, write for yourself the name of this day, on which the king of Babylon was confirmed against Jerusalem today.

3 And you shall speak, through a proverb, a parable to the inciting house. And you shall say to them: Thus says the Lord God: Set out a cooking pot; set it out, I say, and put water into it.

4 Pile together within it every morsel, every good piece, the thigh and the shoulder, the choice pieces and those full of bones.

5 Take the fattest from the flock, and arrange also a heap of bones under it. Its cooking has boiled over, and its bones in its midst have been thoroughly cooked.

6 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: Woe to the city of blood, to the cooking pot that has rust in it, and whose rust has not gone out of it! Cast it out piece by piece! No lot has fallen upon it.

7 For her blood is in her midst; she has shed it upon the smoothest rock. She has not shed it upon the ground, so that it could be covered with dust.

8 So shall I bring my indignation over her, and take my vengeance. I have presented her blood upon the smoothest rock, so that it would not be covered.

9 Because of this, thus says the Lord God: Woe to the city of blood, out of which I will make a great funeral pyre.

10 Pile together the bones, which I will burn with fire. The flesh shall be consumed, and the entire composition shall be boiled, and the bones shall deteriorate.

11 Also, place it empty on burning coals, so that it may be heated, and its brass may melt. And let the filth of it be melted in its midst, and let its rust be consumed.

12 There has been much sweat and labor, and yet its extensive rust has not gone out of it, not even by fire.

13 Your uncleanness is execrable. For I wanted to cleanse you, and you have not been cleansed from your filth. So then, neither will you be cleansed before I cause my indignation over you to cease.

14 I, the Lord, have spoken. It shall happen, and I will act. I will not pass over, nor be lenient, nor be placated. I will judge you according to your ways and according to your intentions, says the Lord."

15 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

16 "Son of man, behold, I am taking away from you, with a stroke, the desire of your eyes. And you shall not lament, and you shall not weep. And your tears shall not flow down.

17 Groan silently; you shall make no mourning for the dead. Let the band of your crown be on you, and let your shoes be on your feet. And you shall not cover your face, nor shall you eat the food of those who mourn."

18 Therefore, I spoke to the people in the morning. And my wife died in the evening. And in the morning, I did just as he had instructed me.

19 And the people said to me: "Why won't you explain to us what these things signify, which you are doing?"

20 And I said to them: "The word of the Lord came to me, saying:

21 'Speak to the house of Israel: Thus says the Lord God: Behold, I will defile my sanctuary, the pride of your realm, and the desire of your eyes, and the dread of your soul. Your sons and your daughters, whom you have forsaken, will fall by the sword.'

22 And so, you shall do just as I have done. You shall not cover your faces, and you shall not eat the food of those who mourn.

23 You shall have crowns on your heads, and shoes on your feet. You shall not lament, and you shall not weep. Instead, you will waste away in your iniquities, and each one will groan to his brother.

24 'And Ezekiel shall be a portent for you. In accord with all that he has done, so shall you do, when this will happen. And you shall know that I am the Lord God.' "

25 "And as for you, son of man, behold, in the day when I will take away from them their strength, and the joy of their dignity, and the desire of their eyes, in which their souls find rest: their sons and their daughters,

26 in that day, when one who is fleeing will come to you, so that he may report to you,

27 in that day, I say, your mouth shall be opened to him who has fled. And you shall speak, and you shall no longer be silent. And you shall be for them a portent. And you shall know that I am the Lord."

Ezekiel 25

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, set your face against the sons of Ammon, and you shall prophesy about them.

3 And you shall say to the sons of Ammon: Listen to the word of the Lord God: Thus says the Lord God: Because you have said, 'Well, well!' over my sanctuary, when it was profaned, and over the land of Israel, when it was desolated, and over the house of Judah, when they were led into captivity,

4 therefore, I will deliver you to the sons of the East, as an inheritance. And they will arrange their fences within you, and they will place their tents within you. They will eat your crops, and they will drink your milk.

5 And I will make Rabbah into the habitation of camels, and the sons of Ammon into the resting place of cattle. And you shall know that I am the Lord.

6 For thus says the Lord God: Because you have clapped your hands and stomped your foot, and have rejoiced with all your heart against the land of Israel,

7 therefore, behold, I will extend my hand over you, and I will deliver you as a spoil of the Gentiles. And I will destroy you from the peoples, and I will perish you from the lands, and I will crush you. And you shall know that I am the Lord.

8 Thus says the Lord God: Because Moab and Seir have said, 'Behold, the house of Judah is like all the Gentiles!'

9 therefore, behold, I will open the shoulder of Moab from the cities, from his cities, I say, and from his borders, the famous cities of the land of Beth-Jesimoth, and Baal-meon, and Kiriathaim,

10 with the sons of Ammon, to the sons of the East, and I will give it to them as an inheritance, so that there may no longer be a remembrance of the sons of Ammon among the Gentiles.

11 And I will execute judgments in Moab. And they shall know that I am the Lord.

12 Thus says the Lord God: Because Idumea has taken vengeance, so as to vindicate herself against the sons of Judah, and has sinned grievously, and has sought revenge against them,

13 therefore, thus says the Lord God: I will extend my hand over Idumea, and I will take from it both man and beast, and I will make it desolate from the south. And those who are in Dedan will fall by the sword.

14 And I will issue my vengeance upon Idumea, by the hand of my people, Israel. And they shall act in Idumea in accord with my wrath and my fury. And they shall know my vengeance, says the Lord God.

15 Thus says the Lord God: Because the Philistines have taken vengeance, and have revenged themselves with all their soul, destroying, and fulfilling ancient hostilities,

16 because of this, thus says the Lord God: Behold, I will extend my hand over the Philistines, and I will destroy those who destroy, and I will perish the remnant of the maritime regions.

17 And I will execute great vengeance against them, reproving them in fury. And they shall know that I am the Lord, when I will send my vengeance upon them."

Ezekiel 26

1 And it happened that, in the eleventh year, on the first of the month, the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, because Tyre has said about Jerusalem: 'It is Well! The gates of the peoples have been broken! She has been turned toward me. I will be filled. She will be deserted!'

3 because of this, thus says the Lord God: Behold, I am against you, O Tyre, and I will cause many nations to rise up against you, just as the waves of the sea rise up.

4 And they will break apart the walls of Tyre, and they will destroy its towers. And I will scrape her dust from her, and I will make her into the barest rock.

5 She will be a drying place for nets from the midst of the sea. For I have spoken, says the Lord God. And she will be a spoil for the Gentiles.

6 Likewise, her daughters who are in the field will be slain by the sword. And they shall know that I am the Lord.

7 For thus says the Lord God: Behold, I will lead into Tyre: Nebuchadnezzar, the king of Babylon, a king among kings, from the north, with horses, and chariots, and horsemen, and companies, and a great people.

8 Your daughters who are in the field, he will kill with the sword. And he will surround you with fortifications, and he will put together a rampart on all sides. And he will lift up a shield against you.

9 And he will combine moveable shelters and battering rams before your walls, and he will destroy your towers with his armaments.

10 He will cover you with the inundation of his horses and with their dust. Your walls will shake at the sound of horsemen and wheels and chariots, when they will have entered your gates, as if through the entrance of a city that has been broken open.

11 With the hoofs of his horses, he will trample all your streets. He will cut down your people with the sword, and your noble statues will fall to the ground.

12 They will lay waste to your wealth. They will despoil your businesses. And they will tear down your walls and overturn your eminent houses. And they will put your stones and your timber and your dust into the midst of the waters.

13 And I will cause the multitude of your songs to cease. And the sound of your stringed instruments will no longer be heard.

14 And I will make you like the barest rock; you will be a drying place for nets. And you will no longer be built up. For I have spoken, says the Lord God."

15 Thus says the Lord God to Tyre: "Will not the islands shake at the sound of your ruin and at the groans of your slain, when they will have been cut down in your midst?

16 And all the leaders of the sea will descend from their thrones. And they will cast aside their outer garments and their colorful clothing, and they will be clothed in stupor. They will sit on the ground, and they will wonder with astonishment at your sudden downfall.

17 And taking up a lamentation over you, they will say to you: 'How could you have perished, you who live in the sea, the famous city that was strong in the sea, with your inhabitants, of whom the whole world was in dread?'

18 Now the ships will be stupefied, in the day of your terror. And the islands of the sea will be disturbed, because no one goes out from you.

19 For thus says the Lord God: When I will have made you a desolate city, like the cities that are uninhabited, and when I will have led the abyss over you, and many waters will have covered you,

20 and when I will have dragged you down with those who descend into the pit to the everlasting people, and when I will have assembled you in the lowest parts of the earth, like the desolate places of antiquity, with those who have been brought down into the pit, so that you will be uninhabited, and moreover, when I will have given glory to the land of the living:

21 I will reduce you to nothing, and you shall not be, and if you are sought, you will no longer be found, in perpetuity, says the Lord God."

Ezekiel 27

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "You, therefore, son of man, take up a lamentation over Tyre.

3 And you shall say to Tyre, which lives at the entrance to the sea, which is the marketplace of the peoples for the many islands: Thus says the Lord God: O Tyre, you have said, 'I am of perfect beauty,

4 for I have been positioned at the heart of the sea!' Your neighbors, who built you, have filled up your beauty.

5 They constructed you with spruce from Senir, with all the planks of the sea. They have taken cedars from Lebanon, so that they might make a mast for you.

6 They have formed your oars from the oaks of Bashan. And they have made your crossbeams from Indian ivory, and the pilothouse is from the islands of Italy.

7 Colorful fine linen from Egypt was woven for you as a sail to be placed upon the mast; hyacinth and purple from the islands of Elishah were made into your covering.

8 The inhabitants of Sidon and of Arwad were your rowers. Your wise ones, O Tyre, were your navigators.

9 The elders of Gebal and its experts were considered as sailors making use of your diverse equipment. All the ships of the sea and their sailors were your merchants among the people.

10 The Persians, and the Lydians, and the Libyans were your men of war in your army. They suspended shield and helmet within you for your adornment.

11 The sons of Arwad were with your army upon your walls all around. And even the Gammadim, who were in your towers, suspended their quivers on your walls on all sides; they completed your beauty.

12 The Carthaginians, your merchants, supplied your festivals with a multitude of diverse riches, with silver, iron, tin, and lead.

13 Greece, Tubal, and Meshech, these were your peddlers; they traveled to your people with slaves and with brass vessels.

14 From the house of Togarmah, they brought horses, and horsemen, and mules to your market.

15 The sons of Dedan were your merchants. The many islands were the marketplace of your hand. They traded teeth of ivory and of ebony for your price.

16 The Syrian was your merchant. Because of the multitude of your works, they offered jewels, and purple, and patterned cloth, and fine linen, and silk, and other valuables in your market.

17 Judah and the land of Israel, these were your peddlers of the best grain; they offered balsam, and honey, and oil, and resins at your festivals.

18 The Damascene was your trader in the multitude of your works, in greatly diverse wealth, in rich wine, in wool with the finest coloring.

19 Dan, and Greece, and Mosel have offered works made of iron at your festivals. Storax ointment and sweet flag were in your marketplace.

20 The men of Dedan were your peddlers of tapestries used as seats.

21 Arabia and all the leaders of Kedar, these were the merchants at your hand. Your merchants came to you with lambs, and rams, and young goats.

22 The vendors of Sheba and Raamah, these were your merchants, with all the finest aromatics, and precious stones, and gold, which they offered in your marketplace.

23 Haran, and Canneh, and Eden were your merchants. Sheba, Assur, and Chilmad were your sellers.

24 These were your merchants in many places, with windings of hyacinth and of colorful weavings, and with precious treasures, which were wrapped and bound with cords. Also, they had works of cedar among your merchandise.

25 The ships of the sea were important to your business dealings. For you were replenished and exceedingly glorified in the heart of the sea.

26 Your rowers have brought you into many waters. The south wind has worn you down in the heart of the sea.

27 Your riches, and your treasures, and your versatile equipment, your sailors and your navigators, who handle your goods and who were first among your people, likewise your men of war, who were among you, and your entire multitude that is in your midst: they will fall in the heart of the sea on the day of your ruin.

28 Your fleets will be disturbed by the sound of an outcry from your navigators.

29 And all who were handling the oar will descend from their ships; the sailors and all the navigators of the sea will stand upon the land.

30 And they will howl over you with a great voice, and they will cry out with bitterness. And they will cast dust upon their heads, and they will be sprinkled with ashes.

31 And they will shave their heads because of you, and they will be wrapped in haircloth. And they will weep for you with bitterness of soul, with a very bitter weeping.

32 And they will take up a mournful verse over you, and they will lament you: 'What city is like Tyre, which has become mute in the midst of the sea?'

33 For by the going forth of your merchandise by sea, you supplied many peoples; by the multitude of your riches and of your people, you enriched the kings of the earth.

34 Now you have been worn away by the sea, your opulence is in the depths of the waters, and your entire multitude that was in your midst has fallen.

35 All the inhabitants of the islands have been stupefied over you; and all their kings, having been struck by the tempest, have changed their expression.

36 The merchants of the peoples have hissed over you. You have been reduced to nothing, and you shall not be again, even forever."

Ezekiel 28

1 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

2 "Son of man, say to the leader of Tyre: Thus says the Lord God: Because your heart has been exalted, and you have said, 'I am God, and I sit in the chair of God, in the heart of the sea,' though you are a man, and not God, and because you have presented your heart as if it were the heart of God:

3 Behold, you are wiser than Daniel; no secret is concealed from you.

4 By your wisdom and prudence, you have made yourself strong, and you have acquired gold and silver for your storehouses.

5 By the multitude of your wisdom, and by your business dealings, you have multiplied strength for yourself. And your heart has been exalted by your strength.

6 Therefore, thus says the Lord God: Because your heart has been exalted as if it were the heart of God,

7 for this reason, behold, I will lead over you foreigners, the most robust among the Gentiles. And they will bare their swords over the beauty of your wisdom, and they will defile your beauty.

8 They will destroy you and pull you down. And you will die the death of those slain in the heart of the sea.

9 So then, will you speak, in the presence of those who are destroying you, before the hand of those who are killing you, saying, 'I am God,' though you are a man, and not God?

10 You will die the death of the uncircumcised at the hand of foreigners. For I have spoken, says the Lord God."

11 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying: "Son of man, take up a lamentation over the king of Tyre,

12 and you shall say to him: Thus says the Lord God: You were the seal of similitudes, full of wisdom and perfect in beauty.

13 You were with the delights of the Paradise of God. Every precious stone was your covering: sardius, topaz, and jasper, chrysolite, and onyx, and beryl, sapphire, and garnet, and emerald. The work of your beauty was of gold, and your fissures were ready in the day when you were formed.

14 You were a cherub, stretched out and protecting, and I stationed you on the holy mountain of God. You have walked in the midst of stones containing fire.

15 You were perfect in your ways, from the day of your formation, until iniquity was found in you.

16 By the multitude of your business dealings, your interior was filled with iniquity, and you sinned. And I cast you away from the mountain of God, and I perished you, O protecting cherub, from the midst of the stones containing fire.

17 And your heart was exalted by your beauty; you have destroyed your own wisdom by your beauty. I have cast you to the ground. I have presented you before the face of kings, so that they may examine you.

18 You have defiled your sanctuaries, by the multitude of your iniquities and by the iniquity of your business dealings. Therefore, I will produce a fire from your midst, which will consume you, and I will make you into ashes upon the earth, in the sight of all who are watching you.

19 All who gaze upon you among the Gentiles will be stupefied over you. You were made out of nothing, and you shall not be, forever."

20 And the word of the Lord came to me, saying:

21 "Son of man, set your face against Sidon, and you shall prophesy about it.

22 And you shall say: Thus says the Lord God: Behold, I am against you, Sidon, and I will be glorified in your midst. And they shall know that I am the Lord, when I will have executed judgments in her, and when I will have been sanctified in her.

23 And I will send a pestilence upon her, and there will be blood in her streets. And they will fall, slain by the sword, on every side in her midst. And they shall know that I am the Lord.

24 And the house of Israel will no longer be a stumbling block of bitterness, nor a thorn bringing pain everywhere around them, to those who turn against them. And they shall know that I am the Lord God."

25 Thus says the Lord God: "When I will have gathered together the house of Israel, from the peoples among whom they have been dispersed, I shall be sanctified in them in the sight of the Gentiles. And they shall live in their own land, which I gave to my servant Jacob.

26 And they shall live within it securely. And they shall build houses and plant vineyards. And they shall live in confidence, when I will have executed judgments upon all those who turn against them on every side. And they shall know that I am the Lord their God."